<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Review on Semi-author-ized writer</title>
    <link>http://ljwrites.blog/tags/review/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Review on Semi-author-ized writer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>CC BY-NC</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0900</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://ljwrites.blog/tags/review/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>[Review] The Lantern and the Night Moths</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/lantern-night-moths-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/lantern-night-moths-review/</guid>
      <description>A remarkable new collection of translated Chinese poetry and original essays by the translator.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://ljwrites.blog/img/covers/lantern_night_moths.jpg"
         alt="The cover of The Lantern and the Night Moths by Yilin Wang, with  an ethereal moth dancing around the warm gold glow of a lamp against a backdrop of midnight blue sky and what might be white snow or sand."/> 
</figure>

<p><em>The Lantern and the Night Moths</em> (2024 Invisible Publishing) is a collection of modern and contemporary Chinese poetry translated by Yilin Wang and accompanied by Wang&rsquo;s original essays.
The diverse works and voices represented are made accessible by the lyrical, heartfelt translations no matter what the reader&rsquo;s relationship with the original language:
Shaky and uncertain in my case, but with no barriers to non-speakers and likely enjoyable even to fluent Chinese speakers for the lesser-traveled route through modernist Chinese poetry and the author&rsquo;s deft guide through poetics, literary history, and the art of translation.</p>
<p>It was quite the experience to be immersed in such different ages and styles in one volume, from feminist revolutionary Qiu Jin&rsquo;s fierce yearnings expressed in classical form, to early modernist Fei Ming&rsquo;s bridging between the old and new in experimental, enigmatic verse.
Poet-translator Dai Wangshu&rsquo;s wistful reflections, together with contemporary poets Zhang Qiaohui and Xiao Xi&rsquo;s everyday imagery and vivid poetic language, completed the journey through modernity to the present.</p>
<p>The effect is one of lively dialogue between these remarkable poets through their differences and convergences in style and imagery.
&ldquo;I shall declare, I have swept the dust of the world away,&rdquo; proclaims the rebellious warrior Qiu Jin, while Fei Ming philosophically muses, &ldquo;the universe is a particle of indestructible dust floating in the air.&rdquo;
Zhang Qiaohui patiently builds narrative in weighty blocks of language (&ldquo;a pseudo-classical reconstruction made of bricks and reinforced concrete/It comforts me with its mundanity&rdquo;) while Xiao Xi throws searing moments packaged in the rhythm of hyper-condensed language that beats with the consciousness of the now (&ldquo;some people . . . auction their kidneys off to pay for iPhones&rdquo;).
Dai Wangshu, a seasoned flyer between worlds of thought and language, casually melds Asian and European philosophy together (&ldquo;I think, therefore I am a butterfly&hellip;&rdquo;) and sinks deep into existential meditations that waver like a flame between meanings, skillfully captured by the translator.</p>
<p>A must-read for anyone with a stake in the art of poetry and its translation, <em>The Lantern and the Night Moths</em> is a unique and necessary collection that raises urgent questions about the future of translation and translators in an age of upheaval, where old forms of devaluation and exploitation&mdash;as brought home by the British Museum&rsquo;s uncredited and unpaid use of Wang&rsquo;s Qiu Jin translations for its 2023 exhibit&mdash;coexist with the new in the use of technological sleight-of-hand to erase and appropriate translators&rsquo; labor.
<em>The Lantern and the Night Moths</em> is both a literary treat and a clarion call that contains multitudes in a slim volume, a celebration, mourning, and hopeful anticipation of what has been and might yet be.</p>
<p>Note: I have received an advance copy of The Lantern and the Night Moths to write a review for Exchanges <a href="https://exchanges.uiowa.edu/reviews/the-lantern-and-the-night-moths/">available here</a>, but have also pre-ordered it on my own since.
This post was adapted from my <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6276127275">Goodreads review</a> posted on February 19, 2024.
<em>The Lantern and the Night Moths</em> is now available whereever books are sold!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Review] Sad Sacked by Liz Alterman</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/sad-sacked-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/sad-sacked-review/</guid>
      <description>This memoir of a middle-class family&amp;rsquo;s brush with unemployment was funny and vivid in parts, but ultimately unsatisfying.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://ljwrites.blog/img/covers/sad_sacked.jpg"
         alt="An unhappy-looking person runs in high heels hugging a folder and carrying two bags. Entangled in her legs is the title &#39;Sad Sacked&#39; against a background of running paint. Also included are review excerpts, &#39;Will have you laughing and crying... you need this book&#39; and &#39;A sweaty, funny examination into suburban marriage.&#39;"/> 
</figure>

<p>I was given an advance reader copy of this book through <a href="https://booksirens.com/">BookSirens</a>.
This post is an edited version of the  <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6460306678?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_source=like_notification&amp;ref_=pe_7171740_475446060">Goodreads review</a> I posted.
If you care about spoilers for non-fiction books, this review contains a discussion of the ending.</p>
<p>Also a warning for discussion of interpersonal antisemitism, which I did not include in the original Goodreads review.</p>
<p>Sad Sacked is a humorous and vividly-written exploration of a U.S. middle-class suburban family&rsquo;s brush with financial insecurity when the author&rsquo;s husband Rich loses his job and the family lives for a year on his severance package.
The whole time the author scrambles to keep everything together, taking on crappy writing jobs to pay the bills while trying to motivate Rich to get a new job.</p>
<p>I sympathized deeply with the author&rsquo;s growing anxiety and frustration as the shadow of her husband&rsquo;s unemployment grew longer and financial apocalypse loomed, all the while squeezed by the pressure to keep up with the Jones in her affluent New Jersey neighborhood.
It&rsquo;s both an intimate portrayal of one family&rsquo;s struggle and a dark look into the evaporation of employment and financial security even for the more affluent classes of U.S. society and elsewhere.</p>
<p>That said, I found the narrative ultimately limited by a seeming inability to think outside the status quo.
(This is solely based on what was in the book, of course, since no doubt a lot more took place in real life than could be written about.)
I found myself annoyed by the author and her husband&rsquo;s seeming unwillingness to communicate about what seemed like conflicting goals and wants.
The possibility of moving to a less expensive neighborhood is brought up but never seriously discussed or planned for in the narrative of the book, even though Rich drags his feet on looking for a new job for half a year.
It&rsquo;s mentioned from the start that he&rsquo;s unhappy and disenchanted with his job, yet this appears to be dismissed as unimportant in the overriding quest to keep the family in their current lifestyle and neighborhood.</p>
<p>This unwillingness to communicate builds up resentments and ugly fights between the couple as pressures and anxieties mount, culminating in an antisemitic moment over the holidays when the author tells her husband that Christmas&mdash;a holiday he had been celebrating with her and their three children all their marriage and possibly before&mdash;isn&rsquo;t his holiday.</p>
<p>It felt weird  because there&rsquo;s no self-reflection in the book about making such a hurtful and exclusionary comment, or a serious apology from what I could tell.
It&rsquo;s even more surreal because the very next scene is of their neighbor making a comment stereotyping Jewish people and the author, while recognizing the bigotry, doesn&rsquo;t push back against it.
So what I get out of what Liz Alterman has chosen to present in her own memoir, leaving aside the complexities of real life that I&rsquo;m not privy to, is that she gets bigoted toward her own husband when she&rsquo;s angry enough, doesn&rsquo;t apologize for it, and also doesn&rsquo;t defend him when others are bigoted against him.
That was certainly a choice.</p>
<p>Moving on to the ending: I usually wouldn&rsquo;t discuss endings in a review of a book that has a narrative, even non-fiction, but it&rsquo;s a big chunk of what spoiled (heh) the book for me so I figured I&rsquo;d go into it.
Spoiler alert, the husband does get a new and higher-paying job at the last minute as his severance runs out.
The family get to keep the house and go on as before.
Yay, all&rsquo;s well that ends well, right?</p>
<p>Unfortunately it rang hollow for me, because the only thing the couple seems to have learned from this time in their life is that they need to be grateful, not take anything for granted, and work hard.
Evidently it doesn&rsquo;t matter that the husband was miserable working in this field.
No, he should be grateful to have a job at all and he&rsquo;s learned his lesson!
Don&rsquo;t even think about the possibility of a new career/lifestyle or stepping off the light-speed social prestige treadmill, just keep your head down, say yes sir and yes ma&rsquo;am, and keep working!</p>
<p>The final chapter/epilogue where the author states these lessons felt creepily docile and saccharine, so unlike the verve and humor that had attracted me to the book in the first place.
Maybe that&rsquo;s appropriate for an ending that may read on the surface as happy but is actually one of accepting the status quo and learning to comply with it.
This lack of imagination, this beaten-down acquiescence to social pressure, may be the most sadsack thing about Sad Sacked.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overthinking the Schwarzschild Defence</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/overthinking-black-hole/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/overthinking-black-hole/</guid>
      <description>Fact-checking the 2023 short story The Schwarzschild Defence because I am a killjoy.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This post was adapted from a <a href="https://writeout.ink/@ljwrites/109724660651747328">Mastodon post</a> I wrote on January 21, 2023.</p>
<h2 id="read-the-story-first">Read the story first!</h2>
<p><a href="https://archive.is/SZbHa">The Schwarzschild Defence</a> (2023) by M. V. Melcer is a very fun short science fiction story and highly recommended reading.
(June 23, 2024 UPDATE: Given the story is now paywalled, I replaced the link with an archived version.)
I particularly love its punchy style that delivers so much in so few words.
Its choices are effective for the story told, from the format giving only one side of the interview to the downright chilling twists, delivered so nonchalantly.
It feels fresh while maintaining a classic sci-fi feel, down to the commentary on gender roles and violence against women (consider that a content warning).</p>
<p>Still, I can&rsquo;t be the only one who thinks the argument as presented doesn&rsquo;t work legally or even physics-wise, right?
If you like overthinking things, and more importantly if you&rsquo;ve read the story, maybe you&rsquo;d like  to join me in overthinking a delightful story!</p>
<p>Seriously. Read it. It&rsquo;s less than a thousand words and brilliantly written. I&rsquo;ll wait.</p>
<h2 id="checking-the-laws">Checking the laws</h2>
<p>So, can you see which parts don&rsquo;t hold up?
Legally speaking, even if we take the narrator of the story, let&rsquo;s call her &ldquo;Mileva,&rdquo; at her word that Xavier will not die (a claim I highly doubt, see below), she has by her admission committed some pretty serious crimes.</p>
<p>One is the crime of false imprisonment, meaning detaining someone against their will without legal justification.
Mileva sabotaged Xavier into an inescapable prison and there&rsquo;s no way this doesn&rsquo;t count as false imprisonment, <em>especially</em> when she was reckless enough to admit at least twice to the police that this wasn&rsquo;t what Xavier intended or wanted with the flight.</p>
<p>In the jurisdiction I live in, false imprisonment carries a penalty of up to 10 years&rsquo; incarceration if committed against a spouse or other close family member.
Committing cruel acts against a close family member while keeping them falsely imprisoned carries a penalty of at <em>least</em> 2 years&rsquo; imprisonment.
The penalty is increased by up to 50% if the false imprisonment is done with the possession of a dangerous object, and both the black hole and the tampered-with spaceship arguably qualify.</p>
<p>Overall, Mileva is looking at some pretty heavy charges and had better get her lawyers scrambling.
Given the severity of the effects, the incontrovertible evidence, and her intent, freely admitted to a police detective&mdash;without a lawyer to advise her, what was she thinking?!&mdash;to trap Xavier in the black hole, it is <em>very</em> likely she will have the book thrown at her.</p>
<p>Mileva has also, by her admission, tampered with sensitive equipment, damaging Xavier&rsquo;s property knowing he is undertaking a dangerous and sensitive flight.
Through this she caused Xavier to make unwanted contact with the event horizon of the black hole, which is battery.</p>
<p>Even <em>if</em> Xavier suffers no other physical harm (which I doubt, more on that soon), slowing down his physical process well beyond human levels is unwanted interference with his body, a form of inflicted physical injury that exacerbates the crimes of false imprisonment and battery.
I&rsquo;m sure there have been more crimes committed, but these are some of the big ones.</p>
<h2 id="checking-the-laws-of-physics">Checking the laws of physics</h2>
<p>The charges outlined above rest on Mileva&rsquo;s insistence that Xavier is physically unharmed and will live a long, long time in the black hole.
But will he?
I&rsquo;m not formally trained in physics so I&rsquo;m on less certain ground here, but it doesn&rsquo;t seem that way to me, and discussions like <a href="https://math.ucr.edu/home/baez/physics/Relativity/BlackHoles/fall_in.html">this one</a> seem to confirm my suspicion.</p>
<p>If time slows down as you go down a black hole and the gravitational pull becomes inescapable, wouldn&rsquo;t the parts of the spaceship and of Xavier be pulled down at different rates, meaning he and the spaceship will be literally atomized?
If anything he&rsquo;s going to have the longest, most protracted death ever.
Not that I care, the guy&rsquo;s an ass and deserves it, but the whole twist of the story depends on Mileva&rsquo;s actions not being murder.</p>
<p>I mean maybe Mileva is right, and the story was worded very cleverly here, that this Xavier-molasses and his eventual atom-level dissolution will happen so slowly in a Schwarzschild black hole, at a time scale well beyond everyone&rsquo;s lifespans, that it can&rsquo;t be murder in the conventional sense.
Murder revolves around the idea of cutting someone&rsquo;s life short, so what do you do when someone stretches it <em>out,</em> longer and longer beyond the shape lives were ever meant to take, before a horrible end?</p>
<p>This is why I believe the better legal tacks to take are false imprisonment, battery, and attendant serious injury with property damage and sabotage sprinkled in for spice.
But under no circumstance can Mileva get away scot-free as she claims.</p>
<h2 id="notes-and-conclusions">Notes &amp; conclusions</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;d like to note this isn&rsquo;t me endorsing the incarceral state, far less the misogyny and threats Mileva was subjected to by her account.
All I&rsquo;m doing is analyzing the internal logic of the story, which is remarkable for raising these questions at all.
If Isaac Asimov in his classic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Billiard_Ball">The Billiard Ball</a> (1967) can stretch, or shall we say fail to stretch, the science in almost exactly the same way,<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>  I don&rsquo;t see why M. V. Melcer can&rsquo;t be afforded the same leniency.
Science fiction is <em>fiction</em> in the end, and between perfect fidelity to the facts and a good story there&rsquo;s no harm in choosing the latter.</p>
<p>I also think that, if we read the story &ldquo;straight&rdquo; along with the fact-checking, a very different reading can emerge than the original impression of a domestic violence survivor putting her abuser away from good and walking away cackling with his fortune:
Instead the story can become one of a traumatized survivor who saved herself with an unthinkable act of desperation that has changed her forever, and ended up self-sabotaging herself in her panic and inability to accept the reality of what she&rsquo;s done.
That&rsquo;s another thing about fiction, that it&rsquo;s roomy enough for different interpretations, and arguably it&rsquo;s a great story that can admit so many readings in such an economy of words.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>In the author&rsquo;s notes for the edition of The Billiard Ball in one of his short story collections, Asimov freely admitted to fudging the science for that story to make the plot work. That discussion was a basis for my suspicion that the science in The Schwarzschild Defence doesn&rsquo;t quite hold together&mdash;any better than Xavier&rsquo;s body would! Too soon? :P&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Heroine of the Game Carto Is Nonspeaking (and It&#39;s Totally Cool)</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/carto-game-nonspeaking/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 May 2022 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/carto-game-nonspeaking/</guid>
      <description>The heroine of the indie game Carto is a nonspeaking girl, and it&amp;rsquo;s neither tragic nor remarkable.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I had a lot of fun playing the indie game <em>Carto</em> (2020), an innovative and enjoyable puzzle game where you put map pieces together, changing in-game reality itself to overcome obstacles and help reunite our heroine Carto and her grandmother.
I don&rsquo;t think I could add much to what has already been said about its gameplay and narrative, and there&rsquo;s a good selection of reviews linked from the game&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.metacritic.com/game/switch/carto">Metacritic page</a>.</p>
<p>What I haven&rsquo;t seen discussed as much is that the titular protagonist Carto appears to be a nonspeaking person, or one who only occasionally speaks.
Though reviews like <a href="https://worthplaying.com/article/2021/3/5/reviews/124568-switch-review-carto/">this one</a> or <a href="https://cogconnected.com/review/carto-review/">this one</a> alluded to her silence, they generally put it down to her being quiet or shy.
Carto may be quiet, but shy? Nah.
There&rsquo;s no reason to discount neurodivergence as an explanation and here&rsquo;s my case for it.</p>
<p><strong>SPOILER WARNING:</strong> The rest of this post contains spoilers about the world and story of the game <em>Carto.</em></p>
<h2 id="a-smile-is-worth-a-thousand-words">A smile is worth a thousand words :-)</h2>
<p>From the first I found it slightly odd that Carto&rsquo;s &ldquo;dialogue&rdquo; was represented by emojis, most commonly the smile emoji :-) accompanied by her sprite representation smiling.
Every other character&rsquo;s lines were represented by actual words, after all.
She also did not seem to be deaf, since she understood when other characters addressed her in spoken language.</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ljwrites.blog/img/carto/carto-smile.png"
         alt="Carto, a young girl in white with chin-length dark hair, smiles at a man in glasses. There is a smile emoji :-) representing a smiling face turned sideways in her speech bubble."/> 
</figure>

<p>I was excited at the thought that Carto might be hearing but nonspeaking, since my son is mostly nonspeaking and I&rsquo;m always thrilled at good autistic representation in media.
Still, I thought the emojis could be an abstraction of Carto&rsquo;s lines rather than a literal depiction so I didn&rsquo;t get my hopes up too much.
There was so much else to enjoy about the game, after all.</p>
<p>Undoubted confirmation came toward the end of the game, like a gift.
When Carto finally meets up with her grandmother, her best friend Shianan jokes about not hearing much about the grandmother because Carto is so quiet.</p>
<p>It looks like Shianan could have heard a lot about Grandma if she&rsquo;d had time to learn sign language, though, because Grandma&rsquo;s last letter prior to the meeting has a sketch of her and Carto signing to each other.</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ljwrites.blog/img/carto/carto-sign.jpg"
         alt="Part of a letter reading &#39;I can&#39;t wait to hold you in my arms. We have so much to explore together! Love, Granny,&#39; with a sketch of a larger hand and a smaller one making a sign with thumb and pinkie extended and the other fingers curled."/> 
</figure>

<p>Carto also speaks a little toward the end, mostly names&ndash;&ldquo;Grandma!&rdquo; &ldquo;Carto and Shianan!&rdquo; and so on, showing that her earlier emoji-talk was not an abstraction but actual representations of facial expressions without spoken words.</p>
<p>So there you have it, Carto is a hearing and nonspeaking or minimally speaking character who speaks primarily in sign language.
She seems to have little trouble with verbal comprehension or writing, the latter seen in a letter she sends Shianan in the epilogue.</p>
<p>It was such a rare case of a nonspeaking character, the main character at that, shown in a way that&rsquo;s not left open for interpretation or headcanons but made explicitly clear as canon.
It&rsquo;s hard to express the depth of my appreciation for this, except maybe by writing a giant review and shoutout post on that one subject I guess.</p>
<h2 id="no-big-deal-because-it-isn-t">No big deal, because it isn&rsquo;t</h2>
<p>Something else I found refreshing is that Carto&rsquo;s being nonspeaking is no big deal at all to the other characters.
Shianan mentions it once, as discussed above, in a gently teasing/apologetic way after she and Carto have become good friends.
Otherwise, the characters Carto comes across don&rsquo;t bring it up, interacting without making a fuss when Carto communicates nonverbally, such as by signing or showing &ldquo;sand&rdquo; to them when she wants directions to the desert.</p>
<p>One moment of respectful but casual accommodation that comes to mind is when Carto was at the volcano hotel<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> rebooting their water heating system.
The machinery is accessible by climbing a rope down a pit, and one of the hotel&rsquo;s proprietors remains at the top while Carto climbs down.
When Carto reaches the boiler room at the bottom, the proprietor calls out to her to pull on the rope when she wants to climb back up.</p>
<p>This left an impression because the two characters are never out of shouting distance from each other, and the proprietor guides Carto through the ultimately disastrous reboot sequence by vocal instruction.
The proprietor, in other words, noticed Carto doesn&rsquo;t speak and made no comment about it, but opted to give her the instruction to pull on the rope rather than shout, accommodating the lack of vocal communication.</p>
<p>In a better world this is how all accommodation would happen, respectfully and with minimal comment.
In an even better world hotel proprietors would also not send guests into dangerous locations to do their repair work.
But we can&rsquo;t have everything now, can we?</p>
<p>Maybe one reason the characters find Carto&rsquo;s neurodivergence entirely unremarkable is that the world of the game is itself diverse, with many different ways of life coexisting.
Carto&rsquo;s own clan fly all around the world on blimps.
We start her in-game adventures on an island where no one comes back home after leaving as a teenager.
Later we move on to a forest where people grow huge beards, have animal companions, and one chosen person guards a giant growing tree for decades, away from human settlements.</p>
<p>Against this backdrop a girl who doesn&rsquo;t speak is positively ordinary, and whether the reasons are neurological, cultural, or otherwise it doesn&rsquo;t seem to be considered anyone else&rsquo;s business.
Is she physically or neurologically unable to speak?
Does she not speak the local language?
Did she take a vow of silence?
Who knows, and what does it matter?</p>
<p>Cultural diversity leading to neurodivergence acceptance makes sense to me because neurotype normativity is just one of the many pressures for conformity that form the basis of bigotry in our world.
This kind of coexistence between vastly different peoples is a fascinating aspect of Carto&rsquo;s world.</p>
<h2 id="i-guess-there-should-be-a-conclusion">I guess there should be a conclusion</h2>
<p>Carto is a great little game that puzzle game lovers are likely to enjoy, one with a straightforward and entertaining story.
It may also enhance your enjoyment that the hero of the game is a nonspeaking and, to my mind, autistic girl who enjoys full respect from the people around her, who is at no point seen as an aberration or tragedy.</p>
<p>Needless to say, I highly recommend the game.
It&rsquo;s fun and a little different, like Carto herself.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Is anyone going to talk about how the volcano stage contains homage to <em>Legend of Kyrandia 2: The Hand of Fate,</em> much like the icebergs stage does for Tetris?&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
