<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Korea on Semi-author-ized writer</title>
    <link>http://ljwrites.blog/tags/korea/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Korea on Semi-author-ized writer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>CC BY-NC</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0900</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://ljwrites.blog/tags/korea/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Crystal stream from verdant mount</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/crystal-stream-verdant-mount/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/crystal-stream-verdant-mount/</guid>
      <description>Translation of a famous sijo from Chosun-era poet Hwang Jinyi</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Originally posted to the fedi on <a href="https://rage.love/web/statuses/107002808081339831">September 27, 2021</a>.
David McCann&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0zea3P4s-lM&amp;t=550s">lecture</a> about this sijo inspired some of my choices for this translation.</p>
<hr>
<div class="verse">
<p>靑山裏 碧溪水야 수이 감을 자랑마라<br />
  Thou crystal stream from verdant mount,<br />
  quit bragging on your easy flow.<br />
<br />
一到滄海하면 다시 오기 어려웨라<br />
  Once embraced by azure expanse,<br />
  you&rsquo;re not coming round no more.<br />
<br />
明月이 滿空山하니 쉬어 간들 어떠리<br />
  Void replete with lunar brilliance,<br />
  why not take a load off, love?<br /></p>
</div>
<p>&mdash; Hwang Jinyi (1506-1567), poet, artist, performer and courtesan.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laughing Alone (獨笑)</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/laughing-alone/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/laughing-alone/</guid>
      <description>This is but how the world goes all the time / Alone I laugh, and none do understand!</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>獨笑</strong></p>
<p><strong>Laughing Alone</strong></p>
<p>有粟無人食</p>
<p>The stores are full without a child to feed;</p>
<p>多男必患飢</p>
<p>Hunger does rule the home with many sons.</p>
<p>達官必憃愚</p>
<p>The man of office high is but a fool,</p>
<p>才者無所施</p>
<p>While talent true will languish quite unknown.</p>
<p>家室少完福</p>
<p>Rare is the home that knows of total bliss;</p>
<p>至道常陵遲</p>
<p>Virtue up high will to the grave be gone.</p>
<p>翁嗇子每蕩</p>
<p>What parents thrifted children&rsquo;s hands do waste,</p>
<p>婦慧郎必癡</p>
<p>The woman wise is tripped by feckless man.</p>
<p>月滿頻値雲</p>
<p>On full moon nights the clouds get in the way;</p>
<p>花開風誤之</p>
<p>Flowers in bloom are struck by straying winds.</p>
<p>物物盡如此</p>
<p>This is but how the world goes all the time,</p>
<p>獨笑無人知</p>
<p>Alone I laugh, and none do understand!</p>
<p>&mdash; 茶山 丁若鏞</p>
<p>Dasan Jeong Yak-yong (1762-1836), Korean bureaucrat, scholar, author, poet, philosopher, scientist, and engineer.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Feminist Pansori</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/feminist-pansori/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/feminist-pansori/</guid>
      <description>Pansori, a musical form born in openly misogynistic 17th-century Korea, recognizes and celebrates the humanity and worth of women in culturally and historically specific ways.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="pansori">Pansori?</h2>
<p>Pansori is a Korean musical form developed from around the 17th century, where one person sings and makes commentary following a set story to the accompaniment of a drummer.</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://ljwrites.blog/img/pansori/Korea-Busan_3404-06_Pansori.jpeg"
         alt="A female-presenting person in traditional Korean hanbok holding a closed fan stands before a painted screen, with a male-presenting person in hanbok sitting off to the right playing a drum."/> 
</figure>

<p>There are five traditional repertoires that have survived to the present day: Chunhyangga (The Song of Chunhyang), Shimcheongga (The Song of Shim Cheong), Sugungga (The Song of the Sea Palace), Jeokbyeokga (The Song of the Red Cliffs), and Heungboga (The Song of Heungbo).
In this post, I&rsquo;ll be discussing some of the story elements of Chunhyangga, Shimcheongga, and Sugungga.</p>
<p><strong>Content warning:</strong> The sections below contain discussions of dark subject matter including violence, death, and poverty.
More detailed warnings are given by section.</p>
<h2 id="chunhyangga-a-love-story-of-self-determination-and-respect">Chunhyangga: A love story of self-determination and respect</h2>
<p><strong>Content warning:</strong> Attempted sexual coercion, imprisonment, torture</p>
<p>Chunhyangga is the love story of teenagers Seong Chunhyang, who is the daughter of a retired gisaeng (courtesan), and Yi Mongryong, the son of a noble family.
Theirs are most certainly not two households both alike in dignity; in patriarchal and class-stratified Joseon Dynasty terms Chunhyang does not even <em>have</em> a house worth the name, for she has no father and the head of her family is a woman once indentured to the state to provide entertainment services.
Although Chunhyang&rsquo;s mother Wolmae retired in success and relative wealth and is no longer bound to be a courtesan, nor is Chunhyang herself formally a courtesan, her low birth still makes her vulnerable to abuse of power as the story will demonstrate.</p>
<p>Chunhyang and Mongryong meet and fall in love when Mongryong&rsquo;s father is appointed the governor of fair Namwon, where we lay our scene, a real town in Korea and a holy site to the art of pansori to this day.
Smitten, the two 16-year-olds declare themselves man and wife but their union cannot possibly be officially recognized due to the gaping chasm between their stations.
In Joseon, a kingdom whose founding order depended on a strict social hierarchy, at best Chunhyang could be Mongryong&rsquo;s concubine if he cared enough to keep her around.</p>
<p>The first calamity strikes our young lovers when Mongryong&rsquo;s father is called away to Hanyang (present-day Seoul) where Chunhyang cannot follow because, again, she was not a legally sanctioned wife.
Mongryong might have been able to take her with him if he were respectably married to a noblewoman and was the head of his own household, but as an officially unmarried boy he was part of his father&rsquo;s household and had to go where his father went.
The two part tearfully, promising to be faithful to each other, and Chunhyang begins her long wait for him, mourning their parting and hoping for him to return to her a successful man so that they can be together.
In the terms of the times this meant passing the state examination and winning high office.</p>
<p>The second and even worse disaster strikes in the form of the man who succeeds Mongryong&rsquo;s father as governor of Namwon: Byeon Hakdo.
A corrupt and lustful man, he hears of Chunhyang&rsquo;s famed beauty and just as famous virtue and commands her to attend to him as a courtesan.
This, even though she is not on the courtesan register and is legally a free woman.
She also considers herself married, to a nobleman at that, and will not pour drinks and smile for another man.</p>
<p>None of that is any protection against Byeon Hakdo&rsquo;s abuse of power, however, and when Chunhyang continues to refuse him he has her imprisoned and beaten into unconsciousness.
He imprisons her, declaring she would be put to death on his upcoming birthday for the crime of refusing him as a mere lowborn woman.</p>
<p>It is at this point, the night before Chunhyang&rsquo;s scheduled execution, that the long-awaited Lee Mongryong returns to Namwon&ndash;but at night, as a ragged itinerant whose once-proud house has fallen.
Wolmae, on seeing him, screams that her daughter Chunhyang is dead, for her one last hope of salvation is gone.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, Mongryong convinces his mother-in-law to let him see Chunhyang in prison, and the lovers have a touching reunion scene where Chunhyang, injured, imprisoned, and waiting to die, declares he is her love no matter what the circumstance and defends him to her irate and grieving mother.
All Chunhyang asks is that she be buried as Mongryong&rsquo;s faithful wife on his family&rsquo;s funerary grounds, his castoff clothes covering her in the coffin.</p>
<p>Morning comes, and Chunhyang is dragged before the governor Byeon Hakdo to be executed.
He tries one last time to get her to relent, offering to spare her life if she will do as he commands, and she refuses to the last.
Just as she is about to be killed, the troops of the King&rsquo;s Secret Inspector strike, arresting Byeon and his cronies.
Chunhyang, saved from the executioner&rsquo;s blade, comes face-to-face with the Inspector&ndash;her self-declared husband Lee Mongryong, who had returned in disguise hiding his high office to root out Byeon&rsquo;s abuses of power and to save her.
She is given a special dispensation to marry him, not as his concubine but as his lawful noble wife, and her virtue is praised throughout the land.</p>
<p>Within the limitations of the time and society it arose from, then,  Chunhyangga tells a deeply subversive, and of course fantastical and impossible, story of a lowborn woman daring to assert her own will, her own love and self-determination, in the face of power and have it legitimized by the broader society.
These are revolutionary ideas, though the story they appear in fits them into terms friendly to the existing order.</p>
<p>Though heavily mediated and limited by the patriarchal social system of the time, the themes of women&rsquo;s sexual and romantic autonomy free of the bounds of class are unmistakable.
Yes, obviously, it is not feminism as we recognize it for a woman&rsquo;s sexual and romantic decisions to be validated only if she is a free woman recognized as a nobleman&rsquo;s wife and guards her sexual loyalty with her literal life.
But if we call privilege by its true name, that is the granting of full humanity, we get a glimpse at the idea behind Chunhyang&rsquo;s story&ndash;a woman&rsquo;s yearning for respect as a person, which in the times she lived in and for her gender was only possible in partial form for a virtuous noblewoman.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s also worth noting that while the governor Byeon Hakdo&rsquo;s downfall for his corruption and cruelty is a political and subversive plotline, it is focused and mediated through his coercion and violence against the heroine.
The governor&rsquo;s persecution of Chunhyang is the main dramatic reason we want him to fall, and we want Mongryong to succeed because he is the man Chunhyang loves and the key to saving her life.</p>
<p>Misogynist violence, therefore, is not a side political issue in the story as it is often treated in real life.
Violence against women is THE political issue the story gets the audience to care about.
The governor is obviously corrupt and exploitative in numerous other ways, but it is his treatment of a lovestruck, brave, steadfast girl that brings his evil into full focus and gets us to root for this corrupt official&rsquo;s downfall.
This ties into the broader political subversiveness of pansori, which is outside the scope of this post but deserves mention as far as it touches on the theme of women&rsquo;s humanity and worth.</p>
<p>I will say that there is a parallel in the political subversiveness of pansori to the theme of women&rsquo;s autonomy in that the political subversiveness also dovetails into the existing order by use of fantasy.
In this case it&rsquo;s the fantasy that the political order under the King is a force for good that ends injustice and corruption, saving victims like Chunhyang.
This is not historical fact, of course, much as a courtesan&rsquo;s daughter becoming a noble wife was impossible in real life.
But again, this was a story told within the limitations of its times, often using fantastical elements to fit the events of the story into the worldview of the time.</p>
<h2 id="shimcheongga-a-father-as-his-daughter-s-all-loving-all-giving-caregiver">Shimcheongga: A father as his daughter&rsquo;s all-loving, all-giving caregiver</h2>
<p><strong>Content warning:</strong> Bereavement, human sacrifice, poverty, societal misogyny, breasts and breastfeeding</p>
<p>Shimcheongga tells the story of Shim Cheong and her daughterly love for her father Shim Hak-gyu.
The most famous part of the story is that Cheong sells herself as a human sacrifice so her father can afford a sizable donation to a Buddhist temple, a good deed that is promised to give her blind father his sight.</p>
<p>The love and devotion is hardly one way, however.
The actual story of Cheong and her father begins with, well, her birth of course, but the joy is swiftly and devastatingly eclipsed by her mother&rsquo;s death only a week later.
Cheong&rsquo;s mother Lady Gwak, a skilled seamstress, was the breadwinner of the family where Hak-gyu could not work due to his disability.
The death of the wife meant economic disaster for the family, especially since the couple had plowed their fortune into tithes and offerings trying to conceive a child at past forty.
With that fond dream realized, however, the tragedy of the new mother&rsquo;s death meant the father and infant daughter were staring down the barrel of imminent destitution and starvation.</p>
<p>Fortunately the community come through for this vulnerable family, and interestingly it&rsquo;s all women who are mentioned as helping them.
Centuries before the availability of baby formula and without the money to hire a wet nurse, baby Cheong would have starved to death without breastmilk.
When Hak-gyu goes out to the village well begging milk for his infant daughter, those of the village women who are lactating feed her themselves, saying they&rsquo;d rather let their own children go hungry than this poor thing.
Women with no milk give money, while women without money give rice.
It is also the community who feed this father and daughter throughout her childhood and teenage years as they beg food which is freely given to them.</p>
<p>Shimcheongga, then, begins with the story of a widowed single father, disabled and destitute, doing everything he can to raise his daughter&ndash;a daughter who was, in the terms of the time, a useless liability who would not be able to carry on his name or support him in his old age.</p>
<p>This point is actually foregrounded very early in the story, at Cheong&rsquo;s birth when her mother is still healthy.
Having had Cheong when the couple were both in their forties, Lady Gwak asks Hak-gyu if he isn&rsquo;t aggrieved that the only child they&rsquo;ll have is a girl.
The overjoyed father answers, not at all!
After all, Cheong can marry a good man and have sons who will support their maternal grandparents.
While constrained by the imagination of a heavily sexist time, the story nevertheless foregrounds the contributions women make to the welfare of their aged parents.</p>
<p>Besides, you can tell the conventional idea of girls being supposedly a burden is belied from the start of the story with Lady Gwak being the breadwinner of the household who supported her husband and, later, paid for the age&rsquo;s equivalent of fertility treatments.
Shim Cheong herself, at the age of ten, takes over the food-begging duties from her father at her own insistence and does better than him at it.</p>
<p>Shimcheongga, in other words, subverts gender roles with a father as his daughter&rsquo;s primary caregiver, and by also showing women as economic actors with agency.
Even more than that, it argues that women have inherent worth and are deserving of care and devotion through this story of a motherless girl who would have died without her father&rsquo;s and her community&rsquo;s loving care and generosity.</p>
<h2 id="sugungga-rabbit-revolutionary-dot">Sugungga: Rabbit, revolutionary.</h2>
<p><strong>Content warning:</strong> Attempted sacrifice and mutilation, body gendering, genitals</p>
<p>Sugungga, the most satirical of the five classic repertoires, has a female protagonist (or villain, depending) in the sense of a female animal.
In the story the Sea King falls ill and his trusted retainer, Terrapin, sets out to land to capture a rabbit whose liver the Sea King must eat in order to heal.
After a mishap with calling a Tiger instead of a Rabbit, the Terrapin finally meets and tricks Rabbit to the Sea Palace, luring it with promises of high office and honors.
At the Sea Palace the true purpose of the visit is revealed, and Rabbit is told it will be killed so the Sea King can be cured.
But not to worry, it&rsquo;ll be remembered and honored forever for its noble sacrifice!</p>
<p>Rabbit, instead of quaking in fear, claims it can live without a liver.
In fact, it takes out its liver every moon!
This happens to be one of the times Rabbit had its liver out, and it needs to go back to land to fetch the organ.
As proof of this unlikely tale Rabbit points out that it has three holes down there&ndash;one for pissing, one for crapping, and one to take its liver out and put it back.
Rabbit claims it is happy to hand some of its liver over to the Sea King and enjoy the high honors he will bestow in exchange.
The Sea King falls for this and Terrapin takes Rabbit back to land.
Of course Rabbit, once safely back on hand, mocks Terrapin soundly for its gullibility and runs off.</p>
<p>I mean the &ldquo;three holes&rdquo; part is a ruse that a crowd better versed in mammal anatomy would never have fallen for; it&rsquo;s pretty obvious to a landbound audience what the &ldquo;third hole&rdquo; is for and it wasn&rsquo;t for taking out any liver.
In this sense, the Terrapin&rsquo;s misadventures with the Tiger early on comes across like foreshadowing, with most versions saying it escaped by biting the tiger&rsquo;s balls.
This symbolism rings all the truer because in Korean folktale Tiger and Rabbit are often contrasted as symbols of the foolishness of the powerful and the wisdom of the powerless.
It would not be a stretch to read gender into that symbolism, with Tiger as a strong, aggressive man and Rabbit as a physically weak but witty woman.</p>
<p>The way Rabbit is tricked into almost being killed so the Sea King might live is also reminiscent of the way patriarchal systems, and in this case the Neo-Confucian hierarchy of this time, demand sacrifices of women.
Given that &ldquo;give out the liver and gallbladder&rdquo; is a common Korean expression for being a doormat without boundaries or the courage to say no, the entire premise of the story reads as satire for what believing the promises of the powerful does to you:
You&rsquo;re promised honor and prestige, and end up losing your selfhood and your very life.
Rabbit itself was lured by the false promises of patriarchy before it had a rude awakening of the system&rsquo;s true nature, and had to use its wits to survive that situation.</p>
<p>The story in this reading seems to ask, are you really going to give away your liver to a system that benefits only powerful men, and consent to live as a corpse with no will of your own, &ldquo;cherished&rdquo; in loving memory not as a vital, living being but for how you were deceived and exploited?
The story also exposes the true nature of hierarchies like the patriarchy, that they ultimately depend on taking people&rsquo;s will and lives, deceiving them into bargains that serve none but the powerful.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a message so subversive that it could only be told in metaphor:
Where Chunhyangga and Shimcheongga paid at least lip service to Confucian values including the beneficience of the King and familial piety, Sugungga, in the realm of talking animals and supernatural beings, fully took off the gloves and pilloried the sacred social values of the times.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s also an interesting contrast to be drawn between Shim Cheong&rsquo;s willingly becoming a human sacrifice for her father and Rabbit&rsquo;s refusal to sacrifice for the Sea King.
As discussed at length above, Cheong was giving her life for a father who had lovingly raised her in difficult circumstances, while Rabbit had no intention of dying for a king that it had no relationship with and who had no claim to its loyalty.
Though both sacrifices might be laudable in the logic of the worlds they take place in, in the case of Sugungga it would have been a hollow virtue without any grounding in reciprocal and loving relationships.
That difference gives us room to think about how virtues in a hierarchical social system can be connected to emotional values with resonance, ones that we might be able to expand on and adapt without keeping the whole oppressive structure.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>No one is suggesting that these stories about a woman willing to be executed to be loyal to an absent husband, another woman who dove to her death for her father, and talking animals in an underwater palace are the pinnacle of Western-style modern feminism.
What they do show is that the recognition of female autonomy and worth existed in Korean society far before full contact with the U.S. and Europe, and these ideas were not new to Koreans nor given to us wholesale by the West.
The specific expressions may differ, but the feminist yearnings, the desire of women to be recognized as fully human and live on our own terms, has always been there as seen in this small glimpse of Korean art.
It&rsquo;s a heritage worthy of rediscovery and interpretation as we look to exploring a myriad of different feminisms, each in our cultural, historical, and social contexts.</p>
<hr>
<p>This is an edited and expanded version of a thread originally <a href="https://rage.love/@ljwrites/105965761722179223">posted
to Mastodon</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>  No, Andrew Lee Is Not the &#34;Crown Prince of Korea&#34; (there is someone who comes close, though)
  </title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/crown-prince-korea/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/crown-prince-korea/</guid>
      <description>The Korean-American businessman Andrew Lee is not the Crown Prince of Korea. The last Crown Prince of Korea has a living heir, though.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Recently I was amused to read that Andrew Lee, the claimed &ldquo;Crown Prince of Korea,&rdquo; <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2021/05/freenode-irc-has-been-taken-over-by-the-crown-prince-of-korea/">took over the Freenode IRC network</a>.
I mean, not the part where he took over Freenode, of course, which is a shame and I hope users will find a better home if he can&rsquo;t be removed.</p>
<p>The part that amused me was that he claimed to be the Crown Prince of Korea, because a) that title doesn&rsquo;t exist anymore because neither Korea is a monarchy anymore&ndash;or at least not the same monarchy, in the case of the North&ndash;and b) to the extent it exists, it belongs to someone else entirely and Andrew Lee has no claim to it.</p>
<p>Why is that, and who is the &ldquo;real&rdquo; Crown Prince of Korea?
Dive down that rabbit hole with me if you like royal family trivia and/or history.</p>
<h2 id="andrew-lee-the-case-for-and-against">Andrew Lee: The case for and against</h2>
<p>First of all, let&rsquo;s look at Andrew Lee&rsquo;s claim to this title.
The claim is that Yi Seok, a grandson of Gojong who was the last king of Joseon and the first Emperor of the Daehan Empire, <a href="https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/andrew-lee-named-new-korean-crown-prince-300731986.html">passed on</a> the title to Lee in October of 2018.
(&ldquo;Lee&rdquo; and &ldquo;Yi&rdquo; are romanizations of the same Korean surname 이(李). I will use &ldquo;Yi&rdquo; for Korean names because it is the more modern and phonetically correct one.
I will also put the surname first for Korean names.)</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s true that Yi Seok is one of the grandsons of Emperor Gojong and a member of the royal family.
He is not, however, in the direct line of the last Crown Prince of Korea, and therefore cannot pass the title on.
It&rsquo;s also been pointed out that Andrew Lee has never made clear what his family ties to Yi Seok or the Korean royal family are, and if he is not a member of the royal family he is not eligible for any royal title in the first place.</p>
<h2 id="the-real-crown-prince--sort-of">The real Crown Prince (sort of)</h2>
<p>So is there an actual Crown Prince of Korea?
Well, technically, no.
The last guy to hold the title died in 1970 and he lost the title itself in 1910 when Japan took over Korea, and it was never restored because the monarchy was abolished.
The title of Crown Prince, in other words, has not existed in 110 years and the last person to hold it has been dead for over 50.</p>
<p>But also, sort-of kind-of, yes?
While the former royal family, the Yi family from Jeonju, no longer holds political power in Korea (individuals might, of course, but due to being elected in their personal capacity and not by family affiliation), the eldest man in the direct line of the former Crown Prince is acknowledged as the head of the family and holds rites for the royal ancestors.
His title is not Crown Prince, however, far less King, but the Rite-Giver (봉사자, 奉祀子) for the Daehan Royal Family.
As the former royal family they&rsquo;ve decided to recognize the royal line and pay respects to the old kings, a millennia-old tradition in cases where a royal family that lost power survives.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a strictly private title, of course, and has nothing to do with official government designation or power.
The Jeonju Yi family as a private association could call a dancing monkey their Rite-Giver and would be perfectly within their legal rights to do so.
They could also call the monkey (or anyone they chose) the Crown Prince and it would be as legal as it is officially meaningless, much like Andrew Lee&rsquo;s title.</p>
<p>The head of the former royal family and their Rite-Giver is not a monkey.</p>
<p>Nor is it Yi Seok or Andrew Lee.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s this guy:</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ljwrites.blog/img/koreanroyals/Yiwon_08JongmyoDaeje.jpg"
         alt="A male-presenting person in late middle age wearing a dark square hat with a row of colorful ornaments hanging from the front and back brim and a dark blue-grey robe with embroidery and a red panel in front, with a white robe underneath and red boots. He holds a long white piece of wood at waist level, pointing it upward."/> <figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Yi Won</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This is Yi Won, great-grandson of Gojong and grandson of Yi Eun, the aforementioned last Crown Prince of Korea.
Or, if you go by legally recognized terms, the grandson of Yi Gang, Yi Eun&rsquo;s brother.
I told you this was a rabbit hole.</p>
<h2 id="dot-dot-dot-why">&hellip;Why?</h2>
<p>But wait, didn&rsquo;t I say Yi Seok is a son of Yi Gang, making him Yi Won&rsquo;s uncle?
So why is Yi Won ahead of him in the family&rsquo;s pecking order?
Also what&rsquo;s this about Yi Won having two different grandfathers?</p>
<p>This all goes back to the three sons of Gojong, who was the 26th king of Joseon and first Emperor of the Daehan Empire.
Gojong&rsquo;s eldest surviving son Cheok became Sunjong, the second and soon last Emperor when Japan took over the country in 1910.
Sunjong had no son, so his Crown Prince was his younger half-brother Yi Eun, the last person to hold this title.</p>
<p>These two princes&rsquo; half-brother, Yi Gang, had a whopping 21 children.
The 10th son is Yi Seok while the 9th son, Yi Gab, had two sons and a daughter, the eldest son being Yi Won.</p>
<p>Here comes the family tree, a vastly simplified one of course that omits everyone who is not directly mentioned in this particular story (siblings arranged left to right in birth order):</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ljwrites.blog/img/koreanroyals/korean-royals-diagram.jpg"
         alt="A family tree diagram showing Gojong (Emperor) with three children below, Sunjong (Emperor), Yi Gang, and Yi Eun (Crown Prince) from left to right. Below Yi Gang are Yi Gab and Yi Seok. Below Yi Gab is Yi Won. Below Yi Eun (Crown Prince) is Yi Gu."/> <figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>A pared-down Korean royal family tree</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>So the first reason Yi Won has more seniority than Yi Seok and gets to be the head of the royal family is that while Yi Seok is older, Yi Won is the son of the older brother and that makes him more senior by direct line.</p>
<p>The more important reason, though, is that he was &ldquo;adopted&rdquo; under traditional family law that is no longer valid in Korea to Yi Eun&rsquo;s, that is the former Crown Prince&rsquo;s, line.
Yi Eun&rsquo;s son Yi Gu did not have sons, which broke the direct line of the Crown Prince.
In order to carry on that line, Yi Won became Yi Gu&rsquo;s adopted son.</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ljwrites.blog/img/koreanroyals/korean-royals-diagram-adoption.jpg"
         alt="The same diagram as above, except Yi Won is moved from below Yi Gab to below Yi Gu into Yi Eun (Crown Prince)&#39;s line with a yellow horizontal arrow reading &#39;adoption.&#39;"/> <figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Yoink!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The problem under modern Korean family law is that the &ldquo;adoption&rdquo; happened after Yi Gu&rsquo;s death, which makes it legally invalid.
Posthumous adoption of a male relative to carry on a broken family line, however, was fairly common in Korea prior to the 20th century.
Even if it&rsquo;s no longer legally valid, the Jeonju Yi family as a private association can decide its own rules of succession, and if they decree that Yi Won is Yi Eun&rsquo;s grandson by posthumous adoption, they&rsquo;re free to do that.
This would not be valid for the purpose of inheritance and other matters under Korean law, but for deciding who the family decides is its own head? Why not.</p>
<p>Just be glad it wasn&rsquo;t a monkey.
Or Andrew Lee.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Gardening (種花)</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/on-gardening-poem/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/on-gardening-poem/</guid>
      <description>開落摠愁人 未識種花 In bloom and fade I worry all the same; My heart does but the garden&amp;rsquo;s joys evade.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>種花</p>
<p>On Gardening</p>
<p class="verse">
種花愁未發 花發又愁落<br />
開落摠愁人 未識種花樂<br />
<br />
I plant the seed and fear it may not bloom;<br />
The flower blossoms, O but it will fade!<br />
In bloom and fade I worry all the same;<br />
My heart does but the garden's joys evade.<br />
</p>
<p>&mdash; Yi Gyubo (李奎報), 13th century Korean essayist and poet</p>
<p>Originally <a href="https://rage.love/@ljwrites/105195636537255709">posted on Mastodon</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
