<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>writing on Un-author-ized writer</title>
    <link>http://ljwrites.blog/categories/writing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in writing on Un-author-ized writer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>CC BY-NC</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0900</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://ljwrites.blog/categories/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Writing year in review: My 2022 writing habit on Emacs</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/2022-writing-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/2022-writing-review/</guid>
      <description>What is most meaningful to me about my writing habit is that the dream of writing this story is no longer a dream, but my waking reality.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My New Year&rsquo;s resolution for 2022 was to write 300 words every day on the first draft of my big fiction project.
Plot twist, I actually stuck to it!
Just don&rsquo;t ask about the state of my physical activity habit, please.</p>
<p>Here are the year&rsquo;s writing statistics from writing most days from January 2 to December 31, 2022, taken using functionalities and packages of Emacs Org Mode, and my takeaways from these numbers.</p>
<h2 id="the-words-and-the-hours">The words and the hours</h2>
<p>According to a word count and Org Mode&rsquo;s <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/The-clock-table.html">clock table</a> report, I wrote somewhere around <strong>170,000 words</strong> this year in 11 days, 2 hours, and 9 minutes, or around <strong>266 hours of writing.</strong></p>
<p>These numbers come with some caveats:
The word count function does give me an exact count, 174,369, but this is an overcount that includes elements that won&rsquo;t be exported such as header (scene) labels, in-file notes, and time stamps.
This works for me, since I only need a rough estimate of where I am and not a laser-precise word count.
Besides, even considering the overcount I know this is Too Much!
I&rsquo;m going to hate my first-draft self once I have my editing hat on, that&rsquo;s for sure.</p>
<p>The hours spent writing are similarly imprecise.
I started using Org Mode&rsquo;s <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Clocking-commands.html">clocking commands</a> fairly early in the year (January 5) to start keeping track of writing time, and there&rsquo;s some undercount from the first few days when the clock was not used.
Discounting that fairly small gap, which can&rsquo;t be by more than 2 hours, I was also inconsistent at times about running the clock.
Sometimes I ran the clock but was not writing, and at other times it was the other way around, though this was rarer.
For these reasons both the word count and reported time are more estimates than exact measures.</p>
<h2 id="words-per-hour-and-day">Words per hour and day</h2>
<p>Keeping those limitations in mind, a very rough estimate of my writing speed this year was <strong>639 words/hour</strong>, and I wrote an average of <strong>465 words a day</strong> during the year, counting the skipped days.
On the days I did write the average was <strong>544 words a day</strong>.</p>
<p>The estimated hourly word rate largely matches up with what I&rsquo;ve sensed on a regular day of writing, that I tend to produce about 100 words per 10 minutes or maybe a little more.
The per-day rate is a bit of a surprise, given that my goal was to write 300 words a day and I often did stop at almost exactly 300 words, especially on days the words weren&rsquo;t coming.
I guess it makes sense though, since I did overachieve a lot of days, by a lot at times.</p>
<p>The ironic/interesting part is, I think it was my keeping the goal at 300 words that allowed me to write an average of 500 words a day.
A lot of days I could only bear to start writing because I told myself I just had to do 300 words, and actually stopped at 300 when I was struggling and tired.
There were many days I could not have started at all at the thought of having to write 500 words a day, and that would have meant a lot fewer words.</p>
<h2 id="habit-consistency-and-achievement">Habit consistency and achievement</h2>
<p>In addition to writing and getting these stats in Org Mode, I had also been tracking my writing <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Tracking-your-habits.html">as a habit</a>.
At the end of 2022 I used a neat package called <a href="https://github.com/ml729/org-habit-stats">org-habit-stats</a> to get a calendar view and some statistics on the writing habit.</p>
<p>According to the statistics, I wrote <strong>312 days</strong> out of the year, or <strong>85%</strong> of days in 2022.
Nearly a third of the missed days come from February when I was having a hard time keeping up with writing, as seen in this calendar view of writing statistics:</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://ljwrites.blog/img/emacs/org-habit-stat-1-3.png"
         alt="Marked calendar view of habit from January to March with a handful of days missing from January and March, and more than half the days missing from February."/> 
</figure>

<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://ljwrites.blog/img/emacs/org-habit-stat-4-6.png"
         alt="Calendar view from April to June with two days missing from each month."/> 
</figure>

<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://ljwrites.blog/img/emacs/org-habit-stat-7-9.png"
         alt="Calendar view from July to September with two to four days missing from each month."/> 
</figure>

<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://ljwrites.blog/img/emacs/org-habit-stat-10-12.png"
         alt="Calendar view from October to December with three to four days missing from each month."/> 
</figure>

<p>As you can see I generally wrote on most days of the month, usually missing two to four days in a month.
Those would have been the days when I was overwhelmed by work or family obligations, or just needed a break.</p>
<p>The one outlier is February, when I was missing over half the days of the month.
This was likely because I was wrapping up my last academic gig during that month before I turned to full-time translation in March, something that made a huge difference in my free time and energy levels.</p>
<p>It wasn&rsquo;t as though I became a different person with more energy or &ldquo;willpower&rdquo; between the end of February and the start of March.
I had simply structured my life in a way that made room for writing and that made all the difference, which may be the true takeaway from this year of writing.</p>
<h2 id="numbers-for-what-they-re-worth">Numbers, for what they&rsquo;re worth</h2>
<p>Word count and hours spent writing are just numbers at the end of the day&ndash;or year, as it were.
They&rsquo;re mostly meaningful to me as an indication for how far I&rsquo;ve come, even as I realize how far I still have to go.
The story has grown in length far beyond my original expectations and I&rsquo;m just slogging on to get to the end of my originally envisioned story, so I can turn around to figure out stuff like editing (I expect to cut extravagantly) and book divisions.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;d frankly have been happier to have reached the end of my draft than to have written so many words, but I&rsquo;m letting the process take control for now as I try to feel out the world and narrative by writing through them.
Stats are one part of that journey but far from the whole experience, any more than kilometers and hours driven can tell you about the scenery seen outside the window or the smell of the car seats.</p>
<p>What is most meaningful to me about my writing habit is that the dream of writing this story is no longer a dream but my waking reality, and that it <em>will</em> be done at some point barring some huge, unforeseen change.
I know I am moving toward the endpoint, steadily if slowly.
Once I get there, I will know the key was the momentum of consistent habit.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How NaNoWriMo broke me, and what I learned from the experience</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/nanowrimo-experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/nanowrimo-experience/</guid>
      <description>I crashed and burned on overachieving NaNoWriMo, but learned some valuable lessons from the experience.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="intro-or-tl-dr">Intro, or TL; DR</h2>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t write 50,000 words of a novel in a month for Camp NaNoWriMo in July of 2014, one of the alternate months of the National Novel Writing Month challenge.</p>
<p>I wrote 100,000 words.</p>
<p>Then I promptly flamed out and could barely write for months at a time, in a writing slump that lasted for years.</p>
<p>Spoiler alert, there&rsquo;s an eventual happy ending, or happy ongoing:
I came back from the burnout after some years and now have a stable writing routine, making progress on the story.
Still, boy was that experience a crash course, emphasis on &ldquo;crash,&rdquo; in what does and does not work for me.</p>
<h2 id="in-which-we-start-out-with-great-expectations">In which we start out with great expectations</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;d been meaning for some time to work on the story idea I&rsquo;d been sporadically working on and researching for since around 2008.
I found the idea of National Novel-Writing Month attractive as a way of getting a first draft&ndash;no matter how shitty&ndash;in hand quickly.
Between grad school and a job, it was hard to get the time and energy to write and I thought forcing myself to write a Ridiculous Amount every day might be a way to do it.
You can probably glimpse the seeds of failure already in my line of thinking.</p>
<p>As I often do when I start something new, I read a whole book on the subject:
<em>No Plot? No Problem!</em> by the founder of NaNo himself.
I thought I had the idea down and liked the thought of getting words out in a gush from the subconscious, silencing the inner critic by making myself meet a word count threshold no matter what.</p>
<p>Already familiar with the technique from freewriting which I had used in journaling, I was ready to apply it to my first draft.
I also had an outline ready ahead of time, since I was used to writing by outline.</p>
<h2 id="in-which-our-hero-does-everything-right-or-so-she-thought">In which our hero does everything right, or so she thought</h2>
<p>Come July, I wrote every single day.
I wrote on subways and buses on commute; I wrote at home, I wrote riding on the exercise bike.
About 50,000 words into my original outline and with time left in the month, I decided the direction I was taking the story didn&rsquo;t work and outlined again.
The second outline was a bust, too, and so was the short-lived third outline.</p>
<p>Still, I kept writing no matter how crappy the output, trusting in the process and trying to soar on the wings of my subconscious through a maelstrom of terrible writing.
By the end of the month I had blown past the original 50,000-word goal and pushed out 100,000 words on three different drafts.
Progress, right?</p>
<p>Well&hellip; no.
Not in a straight line, anyway.
None of the drafts I had written ultimately worked, and I couldn&rsquo;t even bear to look back on them, not only because they were awful and no longer usable for my evolving conception of the story, but because they were associated with the memory of pushing myself to write beyond my own comfort.</p>
<p>My problems didn&rsquo;t stop with the unusable drafts: I also burned out on writing and couldn&rsquo;t work on the story for months.
I&rsquo;d work on it for a few days and then put it on hold for months, even over a year at a time, not helped by the continuing rush of school and work.
It would be a while and some life changes before I found a workable direction and a settled routine that let me make steady progress with the story.</p>
<h2 id="in-which-we-reflect-on-lessons-learned">In which we reflect on lessons learned</h2>
<p>Maybe NaNoWriMo did help me in the sense that I needed to run down those dead ends to get to where I am in the story, and NaNo let me get the trial-and-error out of the way on fast forward.
Even more valuable, though, was that I learned about my own process as a writer, both what works and doesn&rsquo;t work for me.</p>
<p>First, the freewriting-style &ldquo;let your subconscious take over&rdquo; school of writing does not work for me when writing fiction.
I&rsquo;d gotten some mileage out of it for journaling, as discussed, but it&rsquo;s just not how I work on story drafts, even first drafts.
I certainly don&rsquo;t need or want a perfect, or even good, first draft, but I do need to put some thought into making things at least coherent if I want to make the draft a meaningful basis for future work.</p>
<p>Second, for me, forcing a large word count is a recipe for burnout.
It&rsquo;s too painful, and ultimately unsustainable.
I&rsquo;m very much a &ldquo;slow and steady&rdquo; kind of writer, and in a way I owe that self-knowledge to NaNo.
Live and learn, though the lesson may be painful.</p>
<p>Third, my experience with NaNo may also have been when I started to let go of the fantasy of having it all, and realized I couldn&rsquo;t fill up all my time with work and then somehow cram writing in there as well.
I would have to make room in my life for a writing practice, and that would entail real life changes, scary as they were.
There were no shortcuts.
I had to put in the time, effort, and commitment.
Actually acting on this realization would take more time and effort, and is a story for another time.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion-don-t-look-back-in-anger">Conclusion: Don&rsquo;t look back in anger</h2>
<p>NaNo might not have worked for me and I will never do it in its full form again, but I learned from it and I wish good luck and good fun to the many thousands of writers who will be undertaking the challenge this coming November and afterward.
I&rsquo;ll be cheering from the sidelines, continuing in my own way and at my own pace.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
