<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>translation on Un-author-ized writer</title>
    <link>http://ljwrites.blog/categories/translation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in translation on Un-author-ized writer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>CC BY-NC</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0900</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://ljwrites.blog/categories/translation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Delightful Spring Night Rain</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/delightful-spring-night-rain/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/delightful-spring-night-rain/</guid>
      <description>It trails the wind, comes stealing in at night / Bedews all things with thin and soundless threads.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>春夜喜雨 (Delightful Spring Night Rain)</p>
<p>&mdash; Du Fu (杜甫), 8th century Chinese poet</p>
<div class="verse">
<p>好雨知時節 當春乃發生<br />
<br />
The good rain knows the season when it&rsquo;s right<br />
With spring upon us, timely does it tread<br />
<br />
隨風潛入夜 潤物細無聲<br />
<br />
It trails the wind, comes stealing in at night<br />
Bedews all things with thin and soundless threads.<br />
<br />
野徑雲俱黑 江船火獨明<br />
<br />
Above the wild paths all the clouds are black<br />
While lonely light on river barge does glow<br />
<br />
曉看紅濕處 花重錦官城<br />
<br />
At dawn the earth in spots is red and damp<br />
On Citadel of Silk<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> the blossoms blow.<br />
<br /></p>
</div>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Jinguancheng, the Citadel of the Silk Service (锦官城), was a nickname for Chengdu (成都) in Sichuan for the silk management bureau in that city. A variation on this name was Jincheng, the Silk Citadel (锦城), which is the one I used for cadence in this translation.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We Part as Friends</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/we-part-as-friends-translation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/we-part-as-friends-translation/</guid>
      <description>When on this ground we once do say farewell, / Alone, far-flung, we&amp;rsquo;ll tread a thousand miles.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>送友人 (We Part as Friends)</p>
<p>&mdash; Li Bai (李白), 8th-century Chinese poet</p>
<p>靑山橫北郭</p>
<p>The mountains green lie &rsquo;thwart the Northern walls,</p>
<p>白水遶東城</p>
<p>The river glows wrapped round the Eastern hold.</p>
<p>此地一爲別</p>
<p>When on this ground we once do say farewell,</p>
<p>孤蓬萬里征</p>
<p>Alone, far-flung, we&rsquo;ll tread a thousand miles.</p>
<p>浮雲遊子意</p>
<p>The clouds drift on as do our wanderers&rsquo; hearts;</p>
<p>落日故人情</p>
<p>The setting sun with strength of yearning burns.</p>
<p>揮手自玆去</p>
<p>We wave our hands and from this place depart&ndash;</p>
<p>蕭蕭班馬鳴</p>
<p>Our mounts call out on parting, quite forlorn.</p>
<hr>
<p>Yeah I took an ancient Chinese poem and made it cynical &amp; gay lol.
I was inspired by Zoë C.&rsquo;s translation of the same poem, <a href="https://zoe-translat.es/translations/a-parting-song/">found here</a>, to make a quite different translation.</p>
<p>The differences are very indicative of our styles, I think, and I enjoyed the understated and quietly intense lyricism and voice of Zoë&rsquo;s rendition.
Whereas I, as always, prefer classical iambic metre for classical poetry and use it to build up to big, dramatic emotions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crystal stream from verdant mount</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/crystal-stream-verdant-mount/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/crystal-stream-verdant-mount/</guid>
      <description>Translation of a famous sijo from Chosun-era poet Hwang Jinyi</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Originally posted to the fedi on <a href="https://rage.love/web/statuses/107002808081339831">September 27, 2021</a>.
David McCann&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0zea3P4s-lM&amp;t=550s">lecture</a> about this sijo inspired some of my choices for this translation.</p>
<hr>
<div class="verse">
<p>靑山裏 碧溪水야 수이 감을 자랑마라<br />
  Thou crystal stream from verdant mount,<br />
  quit bragging on your easy flow.<br />
<br />
一到滄海하면 다시 오기 어려웨라<br />
  Once embraced by azure expanse,<br />
  you&rsquo;re not coming round no more.<br />
<br />
明月이 滿空山하니 쉬어 간들 어떠리<br />
  Void replete with lunar brilliance,<br />
  why not take a load off, love?<br /></p>
</div>
<p>&mdash; Hwang Jinyi (1506-1567), poet, calligrapher, musician, dancer, and courtesan.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Ballad of Mulan</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/ballad-of-mulan/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/ballad-of-mulan/</guid>
      <description>The long, grim cloak of war do I cast off / The skirt of girlhood I put on with love.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Originally posted <a href="https://rage.love/@ljwrites/104828995995274477">on Mastodon</a> on September 8, 2020.</p>
<div class="verse">
<br />
唧唧復唧唧，木蘭當戶織。不聞機杼聲，惟聞女嘆息。<br />
<br />
Hark to the sound of murmurs fill the room;<br />
Mulan before the door does toil at loom.<br />
The shuttle slacks; the clacking silent falls,<br />
The only sound the maid's lamenting call.<br />
<br />
問女何所思，問女何所憶。女亦無所思，女亦無所憶。<br />
<br />
You wonder where the maiden's thoughts may bend,<br />
What memory might her give such sweet torment.<br />
Yet no phantasm grips her sturdy heart,<br />
Nor does remembrance cause her aught of doubt.<br />
<br />
昨夜見軍帖，可汗大點兵，軍書十二卷，卷卷有爺名。<br />
<br />
Past eve were seen the martial rosters grand;<br />
The Khan calls forth a muster 'cross the land.<br />
The names march onward far as you can look,<br />
And Father's name is found in every book.<br />
<br />
阿爺無大兒，木蘭無長兄，願爲市鞍馬，從此替爺徵。<br />
<br />
There's no grown son to stand in Father's stead;<br />
No brother rides so she may rest her head.<br />
At market will she buy her horse and gear,<br />
And take her Father's place wherefore to serve.<br />
<br />
東市買駿馬，西市買鞍韉，南市買轡頭，北市買長鞭。<br />
<br />
Eastward she goes, the finest horse to buy;<br />
Westward she goes for saddle fit to fly.<br />
Southward she goes for bridle and a rein,<br />
Northward she goes; a riding crop is gained.<br />
<br />
旦辭爺孃去，暮宿黃河邊，不聞爺孃喚女聲，但聞黃河流水鳴濺濺。<br />
<br />
At morning blush she rides, by parents blessed;<br />
At nighttime dark by Yellow River slept.<br />
No longer does she hear her parents' call,<br />
Only the mighty water crash and fall.<br />
<br />
旦辭黃河去，暮至黑山頭，不聞爺孃喚女聲，但聞燕山胡騎鳴啾啾。<br />
<br />
She rides at dawn, the river at her back;<br />
Encamp'd by night at the feet of Mountains Black.<br />
No longer does she hear her parents' voice,<br />
Only the savage horsemen's screaming noise.<br />
<br />
萬里赴戎機，關山度若飛。朔氣傳金柝，寒光照鐵衣。將軍百戰死，壯士十年歸。<br />
<br />
Machines of war a thousand leagues do blaze,<br />
Fly past the strongholds, 'cross the mountain ways.<br />
The frigid wind resounds with striking steel;<br />
A frozen light is burnt on coats of mail.<br />
A hundred battles fought, and many fall;<br />
A decade's strife finds some still standing tall.<br />
<br />
歸來見天子，天子坐明堂。策勳十二轉，賞賜百千強。<br />
<br />
They come before the Son of Heaven high<br />
Who sits in glory on the throne of light.<br />
By all reports, courageous deeds were done;<br />
Reward is given, just and princely sums.<br />
<br />
可汗問所欲，木蘭不用尚書郎，願馳千里足，送兒還故鄉。<br />
<br />
The Khan inquires, aught else does she desire?<br />
Mulan thinks not of office nor of honor,<br />
Her only wish to ride a thousand miles<br />
Bound for the much-loved home where she would dwell.<br />
<br />
爺孃聞女來，出郭相扶將；阿姊聞妹來，當戶理紅妝；小弟聞姊來，磨刀霍霍向豬羊。<br />
<br />
Her parents head outside the city gates;<br />
Clinging to one another, they but wait.<br />
Big Sister, told Mulan will soon be there,<br />
Puts on her dress and make-up with some care.<br />
The Little Brother, welcome feast to roast,<br />
Sharpens the knives and hurries to the goats.<br />
<br />
開我東閣門，坐我西閣牀，脫我戰時袍，著我舊時裳。當窗理雲鬢，對鏡貼花黃。<br />
<br />
"Eastward I open up the bower door;<br />
Westward I sit upon my platform chair.<br />
The long, grim cloak of war do I cast off;<br />
The skirt of girlhood I put on with love.<br />
By window clear I fix my cloud-soft hair;<br />
In mirror bright affix the flowers fair."<br />
<br />
出門看火伴，火伴皆驚忙：同行十二年，不知木蘭是女郎。<br />
<br />
Outside she steps to meet her comrades' eyes,<br />
And to a man they start in their surprise.<br />
A decade on, they've been through thick and thin;<br />
In all this time they never dreamed Mulan was not a man!<br />
<br />
雄兔腳撲朔，雌兔眼迷離；雙兔傍地走，安能辨我是雄雌？<br />
<br />
"When held, a rabbit male will kick its feet,<br />
While rabbit female looks through eyes that slit.<br />
When they run close to ground and side by side<br />
Female or male am I, can you decide?"<br />
</div>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laughing Alone (獨笑)</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/laughing-alone/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/laughing-alone/</guid>
      <description>This is but how the world goes all the time / Alone I laugh, and none do understand!</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>獨笑</strong></p>
<p><strong>Laughing Alone</strong></p>
<p>有粟無人食</p>
<p>The stores are full without a child to feed;</p>
<p>多男必患飢</p>
<p>Hunger does rule the home with many sons.</p>
<p>達官必憃愚</p>
<p>The man of office high is but a fool,</p>
<p>才者無所施</p>
<p>While talent true will languish quite unknown.</p>
<p>家室少完福</p>
<p>Rare is the home that knows of total bliss;</p>
<p>至道常陵遲</p>
<p>Virtue up high will to the grave be gone.</p>
<p>翁嗇子每蕩</p>
<p>What parents thrifted children&rsquo;s hands do waste,</p>
<p>婦慧郎必癡</p>
<p>The woman wise is tripped by feckless man.</p>
<p>月滿頻値雲</p>
<p>On full moon nights the clouds get in the way;</p>
<p>花開風誤之</p>
<p>Flowers in bloom are struck by straying winds.</p>
<p>物物盡如此</p>
<p>This is but how the world goes all the time,</p>
<p>獨笑無人知</p>
<p>Alone I laugh, and none do understand!</p>
<p>&mdash; 茶山 丁若鏞</p>
<p>Dasan Jeong Yak-yong (1762-1836), Korean bureaucrat, scholar, author, poet, philosopher, scientist, and engineer.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No True Dragon (非眞龍)</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/no-true-dragon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/no-true-dragon/</guid>
      <description>The dragon that can be penned in is no true dragon.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="verse">
<p>龍可豢 非眞龍 虎可搏 非眞虎<br />
故 爵祿可餌榮進之輩 必不可籠淡然無欲之人<br />
鼎鑊可及寵利之流 必不可加飄然引之士<br /></p>
</div>
<p>&mdash; 菜根譚 四. 閒適篇 一</p>
<div class="verse">
<p>The dragon that may be penned in is no true dragon.<br />
The tiger that may be bound is no true tiger.<br />
Therefore, though positions and riches may make underlings out of the ambitious,<br />
such bait can never cage a person of simple tastes free of greed.<br />
Punishment and tortures may reach those who wish for fame and fortune,<br />
but can never affect those who are free as the wind.<br /></p>
</div>
<p>&mdash; Words from Lean Times<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> Part 4: A Composed Life, 1.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>A self-help book from the Ming dynasty of China combining elements of Confucianism, Buddhism, and Daoism&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wind Blows Through the Bamboo Sparse (風來疎竹)</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/wind-bamboo-sparse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/wind-bamboo-sparse/</guid>
      <description>Though wind blows through the bamboo sparse / When it has passed the wood does not the sound retain.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="verse">
風來疎竹 風過而竹不留聲,<br />
鴈度寒潭 鴈去而潭不留影,<br />
故君孑事來而心始現 事去而心隨空.<br />
</p>
<p>&mdash; 菜根譚</p>
<p class="verse">
Though wind blows through the bamboo sparse,<br />
When it has passed the wood does not the sound retain.<br />
Wild goose flies o'er the cold clear lake;<br />
The flying shape does not on water long remain.<br />
Thusly, the thought arises in the man of virtue when th'occasion calls;<br />
When it has passed the mind again must turn serene.<br />
</p>
<p>&mdash; Words from Lean Times<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>A self-help book from the Ming dynasty of China combining elements of Confucianism, Buddhism, and Daoism&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Honking Osprey (關雎)</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/honking-osprey/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/honking-osprey/</guid>
      <description>The honking osprey rests upon / The islands of the River great / The lady of good bearing is / The man of virtue&amp;rsquo;s perfect mate.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This ancient song is the first listed in the Shijing(詩經), the collection of 300 Chinese songs dating back from as far as 1,000 BC. This particular song was highly praised by Confucius as the pinnacle of musical achievement. <strong>Content warning:</strong> Some people think it&rsquo;s about, well, <em>sex!</em></p>
<p class="verse">
關關雎鳩 在河之洲 窈窕淑女 君子好逑<br />
<br />
The honking osprey rests upon<br />
The islands of the River great;<br />
The lady of good bearing is<br />
The man of virtue's perfect mate.<br />
<br />
參差荇菜 左右流之 窈窕淑女 寤寐求之<br />
<br />
Wand'ring among the jagged fringe<br />
Of water lilies wet and slick,<br />
Through waking day and sleepless nights<br />
The lady perfect do I seek.<br />
<br />
求之不得 寤寐思服 悠哉悠哉 輾轉反側<br />
<br />
I seek but do not gain her yet<br />
And think upon her day and night;<br />
How long the night, how deep I long!<br />
I toss and turn until it's light.<br />
<br />
參差荇菜 左右采之 窈窕淑女 琴瑟友之<br />
<br />
Digging among the jagged fringe<br />
Of water lilies slick and wet;<br />
The lady of good bearing gives<br />
In happy union music sweet.<br />
<br />
參差荇菜 左右芼之 窈窕淑女 鐘鼓樂之<br />
<br />
Plucking among the jagged fringe<br />
Of water lilies slick and wet;<br />
The lady of good bearing joins<br />
In joyous union's rhythmic beat.<br />
</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Gardening (種花)</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/on-gardening-poem/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/on-gardening-poem/</guid>
      <description>開落摠愁人 未識種花 In bloom and fade I worry all the same; My heart does but the garden&amp;rsquo;s joys evade.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>種花</p>
<p>On Gardening</p>
<p class="verse">
種花愁未發 花發又愁落<br />
開落摠愁人 未識種花樂<br />
<br />
I plant the seed and fear it may not bloom;<br />
The flower blossoms, O but it will fade!<br />
In bloom and fade I worry all the same;<br />
My heart does but the garden's joys evade.<br />
</p>
<p>&mdash; Yi Gyubo (李奎報), 13th century Korean essayist and poet</p>
<p>Originally <a href="https://rage.love/@ljwrites/105195636537255709">posted on Mastodon</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
