<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Fannish on Semi-author-ized writer</title>
    <link>http://ljwrites.blog/categories/fannish/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fannish on Semi-author-ized writer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>CC BY-NC</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0900</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://ljwrites.blog/categories/fannish/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Review of The Lantern and the Night Moths for Exchanges</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/lantern-review-exchanges/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/lantern-review-exchanges/</guid>
      <description>My review of The Lantern and the Night Moths for Exchanges, a journal of literary translation.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I was delighted to work with <a href="https://exchanges.uiowa.edu/">Exchanges</a>, the University of Iowa&rsquo;s literary translation journal, to publish a long-form review of The Lantern and the Night Moths (Invisible Publishing, 2024), Yilin Wang&rsquo;s collection of translated modern Chinese poetry and essays.
It was an amazing experience to publish with a journal I admire for an author and work I&rsquo;m excited about, and my awesome editor helped me push the review far beyond my original vision to an even better place of engagement with and information on the book.</p>
<p>You can read <a href="https://exchanges.uiowa.edu/reviews/the-lantern-and-the-night-moths/">the review on the Exchanges website</a> or the reproduced text below:</p>
<p>—</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://ljwrites.blog/img/covers/lantern_night_moths.jpg"
         alt="The cover of The Lantern and the Night Moths by Yilin Wang, with  an ethereal moth dancing around the warm gold glow of a lamp against a backdrop of midnight blue sky and what might be white snow or sand."/> 
</figure>

<p><em>The Lantern and the Night Moths</em></p>
<p>Edited and Translated by Yilin Wang</p>
<p>Invisible Publishing, 120 pp., $16.95 (paper)</p>
<p>Review by L.J. Lee</p>
<div class="verse">
<p><em>The world&rsquo;s ten thousand beings are all ephemeral,</em><br />
    <em>but through being perceived they&rsquo;ll become born anew</em><br />
<br />
<em>Everything has changed and shall keep on changing,</em><br />
    <em>but through books the fleeting will be preserved for eternity</em><br />
<br />
– Excerpt from “Tiānyī Gé, the First Library Under the Sky” by Zhang Qiaohui, translated by Yilin Wang<br /></p>
</div>
<p>The preservation of the ephemeral and easily-forgotten is an explicit goal of <em>The Lantern and the Night Moths</em> (Invisible Publishing, 2024), a selection of poetry by five modern and contemporary Chinese poets translated by Chinese-Canadian writer and translator Yilin Wang.
The collection, accompanied by Wang’s original essays and notes, spans the first glimmers of the 20th century to the present.
It passes through the turmoil of China&rsquo;s Republic years, the exciting anxieties of the New Culture movement, and the imagery, dilemmas, and yearnings of 21st-century life.</p>
<p>Yet <em>Night Moths</em> takes a branch off the most-travelled paths across the vast landscape of modern Chinese poetry, offering a different scenery.
In making the selections, Wang deliberately avoided the most famous and translated modernist poets, stating “I also step around the latest, bestselling, and most renowned Sinophone literary works to seek out poetry that has been overlooked.”
Also, “By experimenting with recreating [the] work [of underrepresented poets] in English, I hope to expand existing understandings of Sinophone poetry in the Anglosphere.”</p>
<p>These are ambitious goals for a first collection, and the result of Wang’s design principle is a work that is less familiar, more female, and more eclectic than a conventional collection covering the same eras.
You will find no poems in these pages by mainstays like Xu Zhimo, Bei Dao, or Ai Qing.
The emerging and acclaimed women poets Zhang Qiaohui and Xiao Xi are published for the first time in English translation, and the anti-Qing Dynasty rebel Qiu Jin receives focus as a poet in addition to the historical figure she is conventionally known as.
Wang&rsquo;s self-assurance as a curator and translator of poetry is on full display, as is a confidence that this different view of Chinese modern and contemporary poetry is more than worth experiencing—and remembering.</p>
<p>Fortunately, the poet-translator does not simply leave readers unmoored in waters that may be unfamiliar even to the well-versed.
Wang ably guides the reader, not only intellectually but also emotionally, in essays and commentary included at the end of each poet’s section.
The varied approaches of these notes add further levels of understanding and reading pleasure:
the commentary on Qiu Jin’s poetry is an intimate epistolary essay addressed to the poet, who is Wang’s personal hero as well as scholarly and literary subject;
the short notes for each of Zhang Qiaohui’s poems explore diasporic yearnings and the fleeting nature of memory in a format that loses nothing for its brevity.
Fei Ming, meanwhile, is treated to an intensely researched intellectual and spiritual history, entwined with process notes for the difficult task of translating his infamously enigmatic work.
Poem-by-poem notes on Xiao Xi go over the challenges of translation in the context of contemporary history and references.
The final essay on the eminent early 20th-century poet and translator Dai Wangshu doubles as a partial biography that draws from his times to better understand our own.</p>
<p>There is a sense of urgency in this project of remembrance and celebration, as so much writing is forgotten and lost in the interplay between memory and oblivion.
In an anecdote shared in the translator’s note to “Soliloquy” by Zhang Qiaohui, Wang’s wàipó (maternal grandmother) was drafting a memoir which she promised to show her grandchild the next time they met.
After wàipó&rsquo;s death, however, Wang searched for the manuscript in vain.
What happened to it, and what story might it have told?
The answer is locked in shadows, much like the matrilineal history such a manuscript may have revealed to a grieving grandchild.
A driving force in <em>The Lantern and the Night Moths</em> is episodes like these:
the reality that women&rsquo;s voices and stories are disproportionately forgotten, lost, and erased.</p>
<p>If perception is the great resistance to oblivion, books may be the preservation of perception into a hope of eternity.
These books may find their way to someone&rsquo;s bedside and become a repository of their happiness, as Dai Wangshu said of his own books.
They may also be lovingly collected by eclectic routes ranging from ethnic grocery stores to the luggage bags of friends, like Wang’s own hard-won collection of Chinese-language books.
Books, after all, are a communion with their writers, and with the people who helped put the books in the reader’s hands, from booksellers to generous friends.
“the lantern light seems to have written a poem; / they feel lonesome since i won&rsquo;t read them,” Fei Ming writes in “lantern.”
To be unread is loneliness, a fading out from the shared memory of community.</p>
<p>A translated book, then, is the ultimate defiance against ephemerality, not only preserving the existence of a work but also expanding its reach to other lands and other peoples across the distance of language and context.
Surprising things emerge when this crossing is made:
In the translation of Dai Wangshu’s poem “Night Moths,” for instance, the poet’s shadow has been “abandoned . . . in grave darkness.”
Two lines down, the poem ends with “that day I transformed into a phoenix,” juxtaposing “grave darkness” with the common Western image of a phoenix coming back to life from the ashes.</p>
<p>Yet those familiar with the cultural conventions involved may realize that the original Chinese word fēng 凤 , meaning the male of mythical noble birds, does not traditionally have the connotation of periodic death and rebirth despite commonly being translated into English as “phoenix.”
Wang’s translation, refracting language and mythical reference through layers of subtly unmatched imagery and double meaning, lends the poem a new reading in English while staying true to the Chinese original by foregrounding the association of yōuàn 幽暗 (deep darkness) with the underground and graves.
One suspects Dai would have approved, as a culture-spanning poet-translator himself who wedded Zhuangzi to Descartes in the verse “I think, therefore I am a butterfly…” in the poem “I Think.”</p>
<p>At other times things are dropped in the crossing, echoing in the crevice between worlds.
A reader of both languages might mourn the loss of Qiu Jin&rsquo;s pun and rhyme in “A River of Crimson: A Brief Stay in the Glorious Capital,” where under Wang&rsquo;s hand, the lines</p>
<div class="verse">
<p>身不得, 男儿列; Shēnbùdé, nán’érliè;<br />
心却比, 男儿烈! Xīnquèbǐ, nán’érliè!<br /></p>
</div>
<p>became the following:</p>
<div class="verse">
<p>Not a man in the flesh,<br />
    unable to walk amongst them;<br />
but the heart exceeds,<br />
    more fierce than a man&rsquo;s!<br /></p>
</div>
<p>There was also the choice, freely acknowledged in the translation notes, to abandon the repetition of zhùyì 注意 in Xiao Xi&rsquo;s “the car is backing up, please pay attention,” in favor of using different wording for the many nuances of the word: “be mindful of,” “watch out for,” “take note of” and more.
Those who love the cadence and wordplay of the originals may object, but we who have taken the leap between languages know there is no such thing as having it all.</p>
<p>Knowing these limitations all too well, Wang calls the poetic translation process “cultivating the inexpressible,” where “every iteration bears testimony to that which has been lost, and even more importantly, all that courageously endures.”
Yet Wang rejects the facile narrative that poetry is “untranslatable,” citing Dai Wangshu&rsquo;s 1944 essay Brief Fragments on Poetic Theory that a poem, so long as it goes beyond superficial wordplay, should always be translatable into other languages.
Wang calls the power of literary translation &ldquo;infinite&rdquo; and demonstrates it in projects such as <a href="https://metatron.press/glyphoria/translating-language-and-sound/vivian-li-yilin-wang-five-ways-of-translating-li-qingzhaos-poem/">five different translations</a> of Song dynasty poet Li Qingzhao&rsquo;s poem, undertaken with Vivian (Xiao Wen) Li.</p>
<p>If remembrance is key to continued life in a community of memory, what does it mean when translated poetry is indeed recorded and perceived but the translator is unnamed, as though there never was one?
How fleeting, ephemeral, and forgotten is the translator of poetry whose carried-over words ring in the center of Empire like a disembodied echo!
Of course, the translator was and is not lost to inevitable, self-effacing invisibility, but rather actively erased, as the British Museum did in its uncredited, unauthorized use of Wang’s Qiu Jin translations—a disregard <a href="https://edition.cnn.com/style/article/yilin-wang-translator-british-museum-settlement-intl-hnk/index.html">it only corrected</a> after a much-publicized legal campaign.
This story recurs around the globe, backed by the dismissal of translation as easy and easily-replaced work that is nevertheless somehow good enough to be used. The exploitation is sometimes framed as a favor to the translator conferring prestige and visibility, as the British Museum&rsquo;s early correspondence with Wang implied.
Subtler forms of consent violations and disrespect abound every day, such as publishing translations without <a href="https://yilinwang.com/where-the-leaves-fall/">proper contracts</a>.</p>
<p>All this buildup is now set to spike to a crescendo of exploitation and erasure as never before, with the product of untold of hours of translators’ labor scraped into large language models that prognosticators smugly promise will make us obsolete.
Though the form may be new, the foundations of the rhetoric that translators are superfluous and outdated have been laid over decades:
Even Dai Wangshu, living in a period when literary translation was highly regarded and prized by writers and scholars, criticized the publishing industry’s devaluation of poetry translations in his day, matching Wang&rsquo;s observation of today’s mainstream Anglophone and Sinophone publishing spaces.</p>
<p>Yet, as Wang points out, “many poet-translators continue to work from the margins, as persistent as ever.”
The voices of these poets who lived through China&rsquo;s modernity from the beginning to the present moment, given life for an Anglophone audience by Wang&rsquo;s careful work and keen commentary, are not only a collection of poetry translations and essays, but a lively and continuing conversation.
<em>The Lantern and the Night Moths</em> speaks not only to fellow travellers straddling the two disciplines of poetry and translation regularly declared worthless, unnecessary, and obsolete, but also to a global community who bear the scars and triumphs of this construct called modernity, and to workforces around the world increasingly consigned to the shadows of corporate and technical glitz.
In this time, the words that Wang imagines Dai Wangshu speaking across the expanse of time resonate above all:
“Don&rsquo;t worry, poetry isn&rsquo;t what is lost in translation, but rather, what survives it.”</p>
<p>—</p>
<p><em>L.J. Lee is a professional legal translator from Korea, writer of historical fiction and occasional translator of classical Chinese poetry. Her essays and translations can be found at <a href="https://ljwrites.blog/">https://ljwrites.blog/</a> and she is on the Fediverse as @ljwrites@writeout.ink.
Her short story about palace espionage, romance, and queer community in 18th century Korea is coming out this year on the Lesbian Historic Motif Podcast.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Review] The Lantern and the Night Moths</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/lantern-night-moths-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/lantern-night-moths-review/</guid>
      <description>A remarkable new collection of translated Chinese poetry and original essays by the translator.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://ljwrites.blog/img/covers/lantern_night_moths.jpg"
         alt="The cover of The Lantern and the Night Moths by Yilin Wang, with  an ethereal moth dancing around the warm gold glow of a lamp against a backdrop of midnight blue sky and what might be white snow or sand."/> 
</figure>

<p><em>The Lantern and the Night Moths</em> (2024 Invisible Publishing) is a collection of modern and contemporary Chinese poetry translated by Yilin Wang and accompanied by Wang&rsquo;s original essays.
The diverse works and voices represented are made accessible by the lyrical, heartfelt translations no matter what the reader&rsquo;s relationship with the original language:
Shaky and uncertain in my case, but with no barriers to non-speakers and likely enjoyable even to fluent Chinese speakers for the lesser-traveled route through modernist Chinese poetry and the author&rsquo;s deft guide through poetics, literary history, and the art of translation.</p>
<p>It was quite the experience to be immersed in such different ages and styles in one volume, from feminist revolutionary Qiu Jin&rsquo;s fierce yearnings expressed in classical form, to early modernist Fei Ming&rsquo;s bridging between the old and new in experimental, enigmatic verse.
Poet-translator Dai Wangshu&rsquo;s wistful reflections, together with contemporary poets Zhang Qiaohui and Xiao Xi&rsquo;s everyday imagery and vivid poetic language, completed the journey through modernity to the present.</p>
<p>The effect is one of lively dialogue between these remarkable poets through their differences and convergences in style and imagery.
&ldquo;I shall declare, I have swept the dust of the world away,&rdquo; proclaims the rebellious warrior Qiu Jin, while Fei Ming philosophically muses, &ldquo;the universe is a particle of indestructible dust floating in the air.&rdquo;
Zhang Qiaohui patiently builds narrative in weighty blocks of language (&ldquo;a pseudo-classical reconstruction made of bricks and reinforced concrete/It comforts me with its mundanity&rdquo;) while Xiao Xi throws searing moments packaged in the rhythm of hyper-condensed language that beats with the consciousness of the now (&ldquo;some people . . . auction their kidneys off to pay for iPhones&rdquo;).
Dai Wangshu, a seasoned flyer between worlds of thought and language, casually melds Asian and European philosophy together (&ldquo;I think, therefore I am a butterfly&hellip;&rdquo;) and sinks deep into existential meditations that waver like a flame between meanings, skillfully captured by the translator.</p>
<p>A must-read for anyone with a stake in the art of poetry and its translation, <em>The Lantern and the Night Moths</em> is a unique and necessary collection that raises urgent questions about the future of translation and translators in an age of upheaval, where old forms of devaluation and exploitation&mdash;as brought home by the British Museum&rsquo;s uncredited and unpaid use of Wang&rsquo;s Qiu Jin translations for its 2023 exhibit&mdash;coexist with the new in the use of technological sleight-of-hand to erase and appropriate translators&rsquo; labor.
<em>The Lantern and the Night Moths</em> is both a literary treat and a clarion call that contains multitudes in a slim volume, a celebration, mourning, and hopeful anticipation of what has been and might yet be.</p>
<p>Note: I have received an advance copy of The Lantern and the Night Moths to write a review for Exchanges <a href="https://exchanges.uiowa.edu/reviews/the-lantern-and-the-night-moths/">available here</a>, but have also pre-ordered it on my own since.
This post was adapted from my <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6276127275">Goodreads review</a> posted on February 19, 2024.
<em>The Lantern and the Night Moths</em> is now available whereever books are sold!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Review] Sad Sacked by Liz Alterman</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/sad-sacked-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/sad-sacked-review/</guid>
      <description>This memoir of a middle-class family&amp;rsquo;s brush with unemployment was funny and vivid in parts, but ultimately unsatisfying.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://ljwrites.blog/img/covers/sad_sacked.jpg"
         alt="An unhappy-looking person runs in high heels hugging a folder and carrying two bags. Entangled in her legs is the title &#39;Sad Sacked&#39; against a background of running paint. Also included are review excerpts, &#39;Will have you laughing and crying... you need this book&#39; and &#39;A sweaty, funny examination into suburban marriage.&#39;"/> 
</figure>

<p>I was given an advance reader copy of this book through <a href="https://booksirens.com/">BookSirens</a>.
This post is an edited version of the  <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6460306678?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_source=like_notification&amp;ref_=pe_7171740_475446060">Goodreads review</a> I posted.
If you care about spoilers for non-fiction books, this review contains a discussion of the ending.</p>
<p>Also a warning for discussion of interpersonal antisemitism, which I did not include in the original Goodreads review.</p>
<p>Sad Sacked is a humorous and vividly-written exploration of a U.S. middle-class suburban family&rsquo;s brush with financial insecurity when the author&rsquo;s husband Rich loses his job and the family lives for a year on his severance package.
The whole time the author scrambles to keep everything together, taking on crappy writing jobs to pay the bills while trying to motivate Rich to get a new job.</p>
<p>I sympathized deeply with the author&rsquo;s growing anxiety and frustration as the shadow of her husband&rsquo;s unemployment grew longer and financial apocalypse loomed, all the while squeezed by the pressure to keep up with the Jones in her affluent New Jersey neighborhood.
It&rsquo;s both an intimate portrayal of one family&rsquo;s struggle and a dark look into the evaporation of employment and financial security even for the more affluent classes of U.S. society and elsewhere.</p>
<p>That said, I found the narrative ultimately limited by a seeming inability to think outside the status quo.
(This is solely based on what was in the book, of course, since no doubt a lot more took place in real life than could be written about.)
I found myself annoyed by the author and her husband&rsquo;s seeming unwillingness to communicate about what seemed like conflicting goals and wants.
The possibility of moving to a less expensive neighborhood is brought up but never seriously discussed or planned for in the narrative of the book, even though Rich drags his feet on looking for a new job for half a year.
It&rsquo;s mentioned from the start that he&rsquo;s unhappy and disenchanted with his job, yet this appears to be dismissed as unimportant in the overriding quest to keep the family in their current lifestyle and neighborhood.</p>
<p>This unwillingness to communicate builds up resentments and ugly fights between the couple as pressures and anxieties mount, culminating in an antisemitic moment over the holidays when the author tells her husband that Christmas&mdash;a holiday he had been celebrating with her and their three children all their marriage and possibly before&mdash;isn&rsquo;t his holiday.</p>
<p>It felt weird  because there&rsquo;s no self-reflection in the book about making such a hurtful and exclusionary comment, or a serious apology from what I could tell.
It&rsquo;s even more surreal because the very next scene is of their neighbor making a comment stereotyping Jewish people and the author, while recognizing the bigotry, doesn&rsquo;t push back against it.
So what I get out of what Liz Alterman has chosen to present in her own memoir, leaving aside the complexities of real life that I&rsquo;m not privy to, is that she gets bigoted toward her own husband when she&rsquo;s angry enough, doesn&rsquo;t apologize for it, and also doesn&rsquo;t defend him when others are bigoted against him.
That was certainly a choice.</p>
<p>Moving on to the ending: I usually wouldn&rsquo;t discuss endings in a review of a book that has a narrative, even non-fiction, but it&rsquo;s a big chunk of what spoiled (heh) the book for me so I figured I&rsquo;d go into it.
Spoiler alert, the husband does get a new and higher-paying job at the last minute as his severance runs out.
The family get to keep the house and go on as before.
Yay, all&rsquo;s well that ends well, right?</p>
<p>Unfortunately it rang hollow for me, because the only thing the couple seems to have learned from this time in their life is that they need to be grateful, not take anything for granted, and work hard.
Evidently it doesn&rsquo;t matter that the husband was miserable working in this field.
No, he should be grateful to have a job at all and he&rsquo;s learned his lesson!
Don&rsquo;t even think about the possibility of a new career/lifestyle or stepping off the light-speed social prestige treadmill, just keep your head down, say yes sir and yes ma&rsquo;am, and keep working!</p>
<p>The final chapter/epilogue where the author states these lessons felt creepily docile and saccharine, so unlike the verve and humor that had attracted me to the book in the first place.
Maybe that&rsquo;s appropriate for an ending that may read on the surface as happy but is actually one of accepting the status quo and learning to comply with it.
This lack of imagination, this beaten-down acquiescence to social pressure, may be the most sadsack thing about Sad Sacked.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overthinking the Schwarzschild Defence</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/overthinking-black-hole/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/overthinking-black-hole/</guid>
      <description>Fact-checking the 2023 short story The Schwarzschild Defence because I am a killjoy.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This post was adapted from a <a href="https://writeout.ink/@ljwrites/109724660651747328">Mastodon post</a> I wrote on January 21, 2023.</p>
<h2 id="read-the-story-first">Read the story first!</h2>
<p><a href="https://archive.is/SZbHa">The Schwarzschild Defence</a> (2023) by M. V. Melcer is a very fun short science fiction story and highly recommended reading.
UPDATE (June 23, 2024): Given the story is now paywalled, I replaced the link with an archived version.
I particularly love its punchy style that delivers so much in so few words.
Its choices are effective for the story told, from the format giving only one side of the interview to the downright chilling twists, delivered so nonchalantly.
It feels fresh while maintaining a classic sci-fi feel, down to the commentary on gender roles and violence against women (consider that a content warning).</p>
<p>Still, I can&rsquo;t be the only one who thinks the argument as presented doesn&rsquo;t work legally or even physics-wise, right?
If you like overthinking things, and more importantly if you&rsquo;ve read the story, maybe you&rsquo;d like  to join me in overthinking a delightful story!</p>
<p>Seriously. Read it. It&rsquo;s less than a thousand words and brilliantly written. I&rsquo;ll wait.</p>
<h2 id="checking-the-laws">Checking the laws</h2>
<p>So, can you see which parts don&rsquo;t hold up?
Legally speaking, even if we take the narrator of the story, let&rsquo;s call her &ldquo;Mileva,&rdquo; at her word that Xavier will not die (a claim I highly doubt, see below), she has by her admission committed some pretty serious crimes.</p>
<p>One is the crime of false imprisonment, meaning detaining someone against their will without legal justification.
Mileva sabotaged Xavier into an inescapable prison and there&rsquo;s no way this doesn&rsquo;t count as false imprisonment, <em>especially</em> when she was reckless enough to admit at least twice to the police that this wasn&rsquo;t what Xavier intended or wanted with the flight.</p>
<p>In the jurisdiction I live in, false imprisonment carries a penalty of up to 10 years&rsquo; incarceration if committed against a spouse or other close family member.
Committing cruel acts against a close family member while keeping them falsely imprisoned carries a penalty of at <em>least</em> 2 years&rsquo; imprisonment.
The penalty is increased by up to 50% if the false imprisonment is done with the possession of a dangerous object, and both the black hole and the tampered-with spaceship arguably qualify.</p>
<p>Overall, Mileva is looking at some pretty heavy charges and had better get her lawyers scrambling.
Given the severity of the effects, the incontrovertible evidence, and her intent, freely admitted to a police detective&mdash;without a lawyer to advise her, what was she thinking?!&mdash;to trap Xavier in the black hole, it is <em>very</em> likely she will have the book thrown at her.</p>
<p>Mileva has also, by her admission, tampered with sensitive equipment, damaging Xavier&rsquo;s property knowing he is undertaking a dangerous and sensitive flight.
Through this she caused Xavier to make unwanted contact with the event horizon of the black hole, which is battery.</p>
<p>Even <em>if</em> Xavier suffers no other physical harm (which I doubt, more on that soon), slowing down his physical process well beyond human levels is unwanted interference with his body, a form of inflicted physical injury that exacerbates the crimes of false imprisonment and battery.
I&rsquo;m sure there have been more crimes committed, but these are some of the big ones.</p>
<h2 id="checking-the-laws-of-physics">Checking the laws of physics</h2>
<p>The charges outlined above rest on Mileva&rsquo;s insistence that Xavier is physically unharmed and will live a long, long time in the black hole.
But will he?
I&rsquo;m not formally trained in physics so I&rsquo;m on less certain ground here, but it doesn&rsquo;t seem that way to me, and discussions like <a href="https://math.ucr.edu/home/baez/physics/Relativity/BlackHoles/fall_in.html">this one</a> seem to confirm my suspicion.</p>
<p>If time slows down as you go down a black hole and the gravitational pull becomes inescapable, wouldn&rsquo;t the parts of the spaceship and of Xavier be pulled down at different rates, meaning he and the spaceship will be literally atomized?
If anything he&rsquo;s going to have the longest, most protracted death ever.
Not that I care, the guy&rsquo;s an ass and deserves it, but the whole twist of the story depends on Mileva&rsquo;s actions not being murder.</p>
<p>I mean maybe Mileva is right, and the story was worded very cleverly here, that this Xavier-molasses and his eventual atom-level dissolution will happen so slowly in a Schwarzschild black hole, at a time scale well beyond everyone&rsquo;s lifespans, that it can&rsquo;t be murder in the conventional sense.
Murder revolves around the idea of cutting someone&rsquo;s life short, so what do you do when someone stretches it <em>out,</em> longer and longer beyond the shape lives were ever meant to take, before a horrible end?</p>
<p>This is why I believe the better legal tacks to take are false imprisonment, battery, and attendant serious injury with property damage and sabotage sprinkled in for spice.
But under no circumstance can Mileva get away scot-free as she claims.</p>
<h2 id="notes-and-conclusions">Notes &amp; conclusions</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;d like to note this isn&rsquo;t me endorsing the incarceral state, far less the misogyny and threats Mileva was subjected to by her account.
All I&rsquo;m doing is analyzing the internal logic of the story, which is remarkable for raising these questions at all.
If Isaac Asimov in his classic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Billiard_Ball">The Billiard Ball</a> (1967) can stretch, or shall we say fail to stretch, the science in almost exactly the same way,<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>  I don&rsquo;t see why M. V. Melcer can&rsquo;t be afforded the same leniency.
Science fiction is <em>fiction</em> in the end, and between perfect fidelity to the facts and a good story there&rsquo;s no harm in choosing the latter.</p>
<p>I also think that, if we read the story &ldquo;straight&rdquo; along with the fact-checking, a very different reading can emerge than the original impression of a domestic violence survivor putting her abuser away from good and walking away cackling with his fortune:
Instead the story can become one of a traumatized survivor who saved herself with an unthinkable act of desperation that has changed her forever, and ended up self-sabotaging herself in her panic and inability to accept the reality of what she&rsquo;s done.
That&rsquo;s another thing about fiction, that it&rsquo;s roomy enough for different interpretations, and arguably it&rsquo;s a great story that can admit so many readings in such an economy of words.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>In the author&rsquo;s notes for the edition of The Billiard Ball in one of his short story collections, Asimov freely admitted to fudging the science for that story to make the plot work. That discussion was a basis for my suspicion that the science in The Schwarzschild Defence doesn&rsquo;t quite hold together&mdash;any better than Xavier&rsquo;s body would! Too soon? :P&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Heroine of the Game Carto Is Nonspeaking (and It&#39;s Totally Cool)</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/carto-game-nonspeaking/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 May 2022 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/carto-game-nonspeaking/</guid>
      <description>The heroine of the indie game Carto is a nonspeaking girl, and it&amp;rsquo;s neither tragic nor remarkable.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I had a lot of fun playing the indie game <em>Carto</em> (2020), an innovative and enjoyable puzzle game where you put map pieces together, changing in-game reality itself to overcome obstacles and help reunite our heroine Carto and her grandmother.
I don&rsquo;t think I could add much to what has already been said about its gameplay and narrative, and there&rsquo;s a good selection of reviews linked from the game&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.metacritic.com/game/switch/carto">Metacritic page</a>.</p>
<p>What I haven&rsquo;t seen discussed as much is that the titular protagonist Carto appears to be a nonspeaking person, or one who only occasionally speaks.
Though reviews like <a href="https://worthplaying.com/article/2021/3/5/reviews/124568-switch-review-carto/">this one</a> or <a href="https://cogconnected.com/review/carto-review/">this one</a> alluded to her silence, they generally put it down to her being quiet or shy.
Carto may be quiet, but shy? Nah.
There&rsquo;s no reason to discount neurodivergence as an explanation and here&rsquo;s my case for it.</p>
<p><strong>SPOILER WARNING:</strong> The rest of this post contains spoilers about the world and story of the game <em>Carto.</em></p>
<h2 id="a-smile-is-worth-a-thousand-words">A smile is worth a thousand words :-)</h2>
<p>From the first I found it slightly odd that Carto&rsquo;s &ldquo;dialogue&rdquo; was represented by emojis, most commonly the smile emoji :-) accompanied by her sprite representation smiling.
Every other character&rsquo;s lines were represented by actual words, after all.
She also did not seem to be deaf, since she understood when other characters addressed her in spoken language.</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ljwrites.blog/img/carto/carto-smile.png"
         alt="Carto, a young girl in white with chin-length dark hair, smiles at a man in glasses. There is a smile emoji :-) representing a smiling face turned sideways in her speech bubble."/> 
</figure>

<p>I was excited at the thought that Carto might be hearing but nonspeaking, since my son is mostly nonspeaking and I&rsquo;m always thrilled at good autistic representation in media.
Still, I thought the emojis could be an abstraction of Carto&rsquo;s lines rather than a literal depiction so I didn&rsquo;t get my hopes up too much.
There was so much else to enjoy about the game, after all.</p>
<p>Undoubted confirmation came toward the end of the game, like a gift.
When Carto finally meets up with her grandmother, her best friend Shianan jokes about not hearing much about the grandmother because Carto is so quiet.</p>
<p>It looks like Shianan could have heard a lot about Grandma if she&rsquo;d had time to learn sign language, though, because Grandma&rsquo;s last letter prior to the meeting has a sketch of her and Carto signing to each other.</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ljwrites.blog/img/carto/carto-sign.jpg"
         alt="Part of a letter reading &#39;I can&#39;t wait to hold you in my arms. We have so much to explore together! Love, Granny,&#39; with a sketch of a larger hand and a smaller one making a sign with thumb and pinkie extended and the other fingers curled."/> 
</figure>

<p>Carto also speaks a little toward the end, mostly names&ndash;&ldquo;Grandma!&rdquo; &ldquo;Carto and Shianan!&rdquo; and so on, showing that her earlier emoji-talk was not an abstraction but actual representations of facial expressions without spoken words.</p>
<p>So there you have it, Carto is a hearing and nonspeaking or minimally speaking character who speaks primarily in sign language.
She seems to have little trouble with verbal comprehension or writing, the latter seen in a letter she sends Shianan in the epilogue.</p>
<p>It was such a rare case of a nonspeaking character, the main character at that, shown in a way that&rsquo;s not left open for interpretation or headcanons but made explicitly clear as canon.
It&rsquo;s hard to express the depth of my appreciation for this, except maybe by writing a giant review and shoutout post on that one subject I guess.</p>
<h2 id="no-big-deal-because-it-isn-t">No big deal, because it isn&rsquo;t</h2>
<p>Something else I found refreshing is that Carto&rsquo;s being nonspeaking is no big deal at all to the other characters.
Shianan mentions it once, as discussed above, in a gently teasing/apologetic way after she and Carto have become good friends.
Otherwise, the characters Carto comes across don&rsquo;t bring it up, interacting without making a fuss when Carto communicates nonverbally, such as by signing or showing &ldquo;sand&rdquo; to them when she wants directions to the desert.</p>
<p>One moment of respectful but casual accommodation that comes to mind is when Carto was at the volcano hotel<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> rebooting their water heating system.
The machinery is accessible by climbing a rope down a pit, and one of the hotel&rsquo;s proprietors remains at the top while Carto climbs down.
When Carto reaches the boiler room at the bottom, the proprietor calls out to her to pull on the rope when she wants to climb back up.</p>
<p>This left an impression because the two characters are never out of shouting distance from each other, and the proprietor guides Carto through the ultimately disastrous reboot sequence by vocal instruction.
The proprietor, in other words, noticed Carto doesn&rsquo;t speak and made no comment about it, but opted to give her the instruction to pull on the rope rather than shout, accommodating the lack of vocal communication.</p>
<p>In a better world this is how all accommodation would happen, respectfully and with minimal comment.
In an even better world hotel proprietors would also not send guests into dangerous locations to do their repair work.
But we can&rsquo;t have everything now, can we?</p>
<p>Maybe one reason the characters find Carto&rsquo;s neurodivergence entirely unremarkable is that the world of the game is itself diverse, with many different ways of life coexisting.
Carto&rsquo;s own clan fly all around the world on blimps.
We start her in-game adventures on an island where no one comes back home after leaving as a teenager.
Later we move on to a forest where people grow huge beards, have animal companions, and one chosen person guards a giant growing tree for decades, away from human settlements.</p>
<p>Against this backdrop a girl who doesn&rsquo;t speak is positively ordinary, and whether the reasons are neurological, cultural, or otherwise it doesn&rsquo;t seem to be considered anyone else&rsquo;s business.
Is she physically or neurologically unable to speak?
Does she not speak the local language?
Did she take a vow of silence?
Who knows, and what does it matter?</p>
<p>Cultural diversity leading to neurodivergence acceptance makes sense to me because neurotype normativity is just one of the many pressures for conformity that form the basis of bigotry in our world.
This kind of coexistence between vastly different peoples is a fascinating aspect of Carto&rsquo;s world.</p>
<h2 id="i-guess-there-should-be-a-conclusion">I guess there should be a conclusion</h2>
<p>Carto is a great little game that puzzle game lovers are likely to enjoy, one with a straightforward and entertaining story.
It may also enhance your enjoyment that the hero of the game is a nonspeaking and, to my mind, autistic girl who enjoys full respect from the people around her, who is at no point seen as an aberration or tragedy.</p>
<p>Needless to say, I highly recommend the game.
It&rsquo;s fun and a little different, like Carto herself.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Is anyone going to talk about how the volcano stage contains homage to <em>Legend of Kyrandia 2: The Hand of Fate,</em> much like the icebergs stage does for Tetris?&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Feminist Pansori</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/feminist-pansori/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/feminist-pansori/</guid>
      <description>Pansori, a musical form born in openly misogynistic 17th-century Korea, recognizes and celebrates the humanity and worth of women in culturally and historically specific ways.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="pansori">Pansori?</h2>
<p>Pansori is a Korean musical form developed from around the 17th century, where one person sings and makes commentary following a set story to the accompaniment of a drummer.</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://ljwrites.blog/img/pansori/Korea-Busan_3404-06_Pansori.jpeg"
         alt="A female-presenting person in traditional Korean hanbok holding a closed fan stands before a painted screen, with a male-presenting person in hanbok sitting off to the right playing a drum."/> 
</figure>

<p>There are five traditional repertoires that have survived to the present day: Chunhyangga (The Song of Chunhyang), Shimcheongga (The Song of Shim Cheong), Sugungga (The Song of the Sea Palace), Jeokbyeokga (The Song of the Red Cliffs), and Heungboga (The Song of Heungbo).
In this post, I&rsquo;ll be discussing some of the story elements of Chunhyangga, Shimcheongga, and Sugungga.</p>
<p><strong>Content warning:</strong> The sections below contain discussions of dark subject matter including violence, death, and poverty.
More detailed warnings are given by section.</p>
<h2 id="chunhyangga-a-love-story-of-self-determination-and-respect">Chunhyangga: A love story of self-determination and respect</h2>
<p><strong>Content warning:</strong> Attempted sexual coercion, imprisonment, torture</p>
<p>Chunhyangga is the love story of teenagers Seong Chunhyang, who is the daughter of a retired gisaeng (courtesan), and Yi Mongryong, the son of a noble family.
Theirs are most certainly not two households both alike in dignity; in patriarchal and class-stratified Joseon Dynasty terms Chunhyang does not even <em>have</em> a house worth the name, for she has no father and the head of her family is a woman once indentured to the state to provide entertainment services.
Although Chunhyang&rsquo;s mother Wolmae retired in success and relative wealth and is no longer bound to be a courtesan, nor is Chunhyang herself formally a courtesan, her low birth still makes her vulnerable to abuse of power as the story will demonstrate.</p>
<p>Chunhyang and Mongryong meet and fall in love when Mongryong&rsquo;s father is appointed the governor of fair Namwon, where we lay our scene, a real town in Korea and a holy site to the art of pansori to this day.
Smitten, the two 16-year-olds declare themselves man and wife but their union cannot possibly be officially recognized due to the gaping chasm between their stations.
In Joseon, a kingdom whose founding order depended on a strict social hierarchy, at best Chunhyang could be Mongryong&rsquo;s concubine if he cared enough to keep her around.</p>
<p>The first calamity strikes our young lovers when Mongryong&rsquo;s father is called away to Hanyang (present-day Seoul) where Chunhyang cannot follow because, again, she was not a legally sanctioned wife.
Mongryong might have been able to take her with him if he were respectably married to a noblewoman and was the head of his own household, but as an officially unmarried boy he was part of his father&rsquo;s household and had to go where his father went.
The two part tearfully, promising to be faithful to each other, and Chunhyang begins her long wait for him, mourning their parting and hoping for him to return to her a successful man so that they can be together.
In the terms of the times this meant passing the state examination and winning high office.</p>
<p>The second and even worse disaster strikes in the form of the man who succeeds Mongryong&rsquo;s father as governor of Namwon: Byeon Hakdo.
A corrupt and lustful man, he hears of Chunhyang&rsquo;s famed beauty and just as famous virtue and commands her to attend to him as a courtesan.
This, even though she is not on the courtesan register and is legally a free woman.
She also considers herself married, to a nobleman at that, and will not pour drinks and smile for another man.</p>
<p>None of that is any protection against Byeon Hakdo&rsquo;s abuse of power, however, and when Chunhyang continues to refuse him he has her imprisoned and beaten into unconsciousness.
He imprisons her, declaring she would be put to death on his upcoming birthday for the crime of refusing him as a mere lowborn woman.</p>
<p>It is at this point, the night before Chunhyang&rsquo;s scheduled execution, that the long-awaited Lee Mongryong returns to Namwon&ndash;but at night, as a ragged itinerant whose once-proud house has fallen.
Wolmae, on seeing him, screams that her daughter Chunhyang is dead, for her one last hope of salvation is gone.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, Mongryong convinces his mother-in-law to let him see Chunhyang in prison, and the lovers have a touching reunion scene where Chunhyang, injured, imprisoned, and waiting to die, declares he is her love no matter what the circumstance and defends him to her irate and grieving mother.
All Chunhyang asks is that she be buried as Mongryong&rsquo;s faithful wife on his family&rsquo;s funerary grounds, his castoff clothes covering her in the coffin.</p>
<p>Morning comes, and Chunhyang is dragged before the governor Byeon Hakdo to be executed.
He tries one last time to get her to relent, offering to spare her life if she will do as he commands, and she refuses to the last.
Just as she is about to be killed, the troops of the King&rsquo;s Secret Inspector strike, arresting Byeon and his cronies.
Chunhyang, saved from the executioner&rsquo;s blade, comes face-to-face with the Inspector&ndash;her self-declared husband Lee Mongryong, who had returned in disguise hiding his high office to root out Byeon&rsquo;s abuses of power and to save her.
She is given a special dispensation to marry him, not as his concubine but as his lawful noble wife, and her virtue is praised throughout the land.</p>
<p>Within the limitations of the time and society it arose from, then,  Chunhyangga tells a deeply subversive, and of course fantastical and impossible, story of a lowborn woman daring to assert her own will, her own love and self-determination, in the face of power and have it legitimized by the broader society.
These are revolutionary ideas, though the story they appear in fits them into terms friendly to the existing order.</p>
<p>Though heavily mediated and limited by the patriarchal social system of the time, the themes of women&rsquo;s sexual and romantic autonomy free of the bounds of class are unmistakable.
Yes, obviously, it is not feminism as we recognize it for a woman&rsquo;s sexual and romantic decisions to be validated only if she is a free woman recognized as a nobleman&rsquo;s wife and guards her sexual loyalty with her literal life.
But if we call privilege by its true name, that is the granting of full humanity, we get a glimpse at the idea behind Chunhyang&rsquo;s story&ndash;a woman&rsquo;s yearning for respect as a person, which in the times she lived in and for her gender was only possible in partial form for a virtuous noblewoman.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s also worth noting that while the governor Byeon Hakdo&rsquo;s downfall for his corruption and cruelty is a political and subversive plotline, it is focused and mediated through his coercion and violence against the heroine.
The governor&rsquo;s persecution of Chunhyang is the main dramatic reason we want him to fall, and we want Mongryong to succeed because he is the man Chunhyang loves and the key to saving her life.</p>
<p>Misogynist violence, therefore, is not a side political issue in the story as it is often treated in real life.
Violence against women is THE political issue the story gets the audience to care about.
The governor is obviously corrupt and exploitative in numerous other ways, but it is his treatment of a lovestruck, brave, steadfast girl that brings his evil into full focus and gets us to root for this corrupt official&rsquo;s downfall.
This ties into the broader political subversiveness of pansori, which is outside the scope of this post but deserves mention as far as it touches on the theme of women&rsquo;s humanity and worth.</p>
<p>I will say that there is a parallel in the political subversiveness of pansori to the theme of women&rsquo;s autonomy in that the political subversiveness also dovetails into the existing order by use of fantasy.
In this case it&rsquo;s the fantasy that the political order under the King is a force for good that ends injustice and corruption, saving victims like Chunhyang.
This is not historical fact, of course, much as a courtesan&rsquo;s daughter becoming a noble wife was impossible in real life.
But again, this was a story told within the limitations of its times, often using fantastical elements to fit the events of the story into the worldview of the time.</p>
<h2 id="shimcheongga-a-father-as-his-daughter-s-all-loving-all-giving-caregiver">Shimcheongga: A father as his daughter&rsquo;s all-loving, all-giving caregiver</h2>
<p><strong>Content warning:</strong> Bereavement, human sacrifice, poverty, societal misogyny, breasts and breastfeeding</p>
<p>Shimcheongga tells the story of Shim Cheong and her daughterly love for her father Shim Hak-gyu.
The most famous part of the story is that Cheong sells herself as a human sacrifice so her father can afford a sizable donation to a Buddhist temple, a good deed that is promised to give her blind father his sight.</p>
<p>The love and devotion is hardly one way, however.
The actual story of Cheong and her father begins with, well, her birth of course, but the joy is swiftly and devastatingly eclipsed by her mother&rsquo;s death only a week later.
Cheong&rsquo;s mother Lady Gwak, a skilled seamstress, was the breadwinner of the family where Hak-gyu could not work due to his disability.
The death of the wife meant economic disaster for the family, especially since the couple had plowed their fortune into tithes and offerings trying to conceive a child at past forty.
With that fond dream realized, however, the tragedy of the new mother&rsquo;s death meant the father and infant daughter were staring down the barrel of imminent destitution and starvation.</p>
<p>Fortunately the community come through for this vulnerable family, and interestingly it&rsquo;s all women who are mentioned as helping them.
Centuries before the availability of baby formula and without the money to hire a wet nurse, baby Cheong would have starved to death without breastmilk.
When Hak-gyu goes out to the village well begging milk for his infant daughter, those of the village women who are lactating feed her themselves, saying they&rsquo;d rather let their own children go hungry than this poor thing.
Women with no milk give money, while women without money give rice.
It is also the community who feed this father and daughter throughout her childhood and teenage years as they beg food which is freely given to them.</p>
<p>Shimcheongga, then, begins with the story of a widowed single father, disabled and destitute, doing everything he can to raise his daughter&ndash;a daughter who was, in the terms of the time, a useless liability who would not be able to carry on his name or support him in his old age.</p>
<p>This point is actually foregrounded very early in the story, at Cheong&rsquo;s birth when her mother is still healthy.
Having had Cheong when the couple were both in their forties, Lady Gwak asks Hak-gyu if he isn&rsquo;t aggrieved that the only child they&rsquo;ll have is a girl.
The overjoyed father answers, not at all!
After all, Cheong can marry a good man and have sons who will support their maternal grandparents.
While constrained by the imagination of a heavily sexist time, the story nevertheless foregrounds the contributions women make to the welfare of their aged parents.</p>
<p>Besides, you can tell the conventional idea of girls being supposedly a burden is belied from the start of the story with Lady Gwak being the breadwinner of the household who supported her husband and, later, paid for the age&rsquo;s equivalent of fertility treatments.
Shim Cheong herself, at the age of ten, takes over the food-begging duties from her father at her own insistence and does better than him at it.</p>
<p>Shimcheongga, in other words, subverts gender roles with a father as his daughter&rsquo;s primary caregiver, and by also showing women as economic actors with agency.
Even more than that, it argues that women have inherent worth and are deserving of care and devotion through this story of a motherless girl who would have died without her father&rsquo;s and her community&rsquo;s loving care and generosity.</p>
<h2 id="sugungga-rabbit-revolutionary-dot">Sugungga: Rabbit, revolutionary.</h2>
<p><strong>Content warning:</strong> Attempted sacrifice and mutilation, body gendering, genitals</p>
<p>Sugungga, the most satirical of the five classic repertoires, has a female protagonist (or villain, depending) in the sense of a female animal.
In the story the Sea King falls ill and his trusted retainer, Terrapin, sets out to land to capture a rabbit whose liver the Sea King must eat in order to heal.
After a mishap with calling a Tiger instead of a Rabbit, the Terrapin finally meets and tricks Rabbit to the Sea Palace, luring it with promises of high office and honors.
At the Sea Palace the true purpose of the visit is revealed, and Rabbit is told it will be killed so the Sea King can be cured.
But not to worry, it&rsquo;ll be remembered and honored forever for its noble sacrifice!</p>
<p>Rabbit, instead of quaking in fear, claims it can live without a liver.
In fact, it takes out its liver every moon!
This happens to be one of the times Rabbit had its liver out, and it needs to go back to land to fetch the organ.
As proof of this unlikely tale Rabbit points out that it has three holes down there&ndash;one for pissing, one for crapping, and one to take its liver out and put it back.
Rabbit claims it is happy to hand some of its liver over to the Sea King and enjoy the high honors he will bestow in exchange.
The Sea King falls for this and Terrapin takes Rabbit back to land.
Of course Rabbit, once safely back on hand, mocks Terrapin soundly for its gullibility and runs off.</p>
<p>I mean the &ldquo;three holes&rdquo; part is a ruse that a crowd better versed in mammal anatomy would never have fallen for; it&rsquo;s pretty obvious to a landbound audience what the &ldquo;third hole&rdquo; is for and it wasn&rsquo;t for taking out any liver.
In this sense, the Terrapin&rsquo;s misadventures with the Tiger early on comes across like foreshadowing, with most versions saying it escaped by biting the tiger&rsquo;s balls.
This symbolism rings all the truer because in Korean folktale Tiger and Rabbit are often contrasted as symbols of the foolishness of the powerful and the wisdom of the powerless.
It would not be a stretch to read gender into that symbolism, with Tiger as a strong, aggressive man and Rabbit as a physically weak but witty woman.</p>
<p>The way Rabbit is tricked into almost being killed so the Sea King might live is also reminiscent of the way patriarchal systems, and in this case the Neo-Confucian hierarchy of this time, demand sacrifices of women.
Given that &ldquo;give out the liver and gallbladder&rdquo; is a common Korean expression for being a doormat without boundaries or the courage to say no, the entire premise of the story reads as satire for what believing the promises of the powerful does to you:
You&rsquo;re promised honor and prestige, and end up losing your selfhood and your very life.
Rabbit itself was lured by the false promises of patriarchy before it had a rude awakening of the system&rsquo;s true nature, and had to use its wits to survive that situation.</p>
<p>The story in this reading seems to ask, are you really going to give away your liver to a system that benefits only powerful men, and consent to live as a corpse with no will of your own, &ldquo;cherished&rdquo; in loving memory not as a vital, living being but for how you were deceived and exploited?
The story also exposes the true nature of hierarchies like the patriarchy, that they ultimately depend on taking people&rsquo;s will and lives, deceiving them into bargains that serve none but the powerful.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a message so subversive that it could only be told in metaphor:
Where Chunhyangga and Shimcheongga paid at least lip service to Confucian values including the beneficience of the King and familial piety, Sugungga, in the realm of talking animals and supernatural beings, fully took off the gloves and pilloried the sacred social values of the times.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s also an interesting contrast to be drawn between Shim Cheong&rsquo;s willingly becoming a human sacrifice for her father and Rabbit&rsquo;s refusal to sacrifice for the Sea King.
As discussed at length above, Cheong was giving her life for a father who had lovingly raised her in difficult circumstances, while Rabbit had no intention of dying for a king that it had no relationship with and who had no claim to its loyalty.
Though both sacrifices might be laudable in the logic of the worlds they take place in, in the case of Sugungga it would have been a hollow virtue without any grounding in reciprocal and loving relationships.
That difference gives us room to think about how virtues in a hierarchical social system can be connected to emotional values with resonance, ones that we might be able to expand on and adapt without keeping the whole oppressive structure.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>No one is suggesting that these stories about a woman willing to be executed to be loyal to an absent husband, another woman who dove to her death for her father, and talking animals in an underwater palace are the pinnacle of Western-style modern feminism.
What they do show is that the recognition of female autonomy and worth existed in Korean society far before full contact with the U.S. and Europe, and these ideas were not new to Koreans nor given to us wholesale by the West.
The specific expressions may differ, but the feminist yearnings, the desire of women to be recognized as fully human and live on our own terms, has always been there as seen in this small glimpse of Korean art.
It&rsquo;s a heritage worthy of rediscovery and interpretation as we look to exploring a myriad of different feminisms, each in our cultural, historical, and social contexts.</p>
<hr>
<p>This is an edited and expanded version of a thread originally <a href="https://rage.love/@ljwrites/105965761722179223">posted
to Mastodon</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
