<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Science on Semi-author-ized writer</title>
    <link>http://ljwrites.blog/tags/science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Science on Semi-author-ized writer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>CC BY-NC</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0900</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://ljwrites.blog/tags/science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Overthinking the Schwarzschild Defense</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/overthinking-black-hole/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/overthinking-black-hole/</guid>
      <description>Fact-checking the 2023 short story The Schwarzschild Defense because I am a killjoy.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This post was adapted from a <a href="https://writeout.ink/@ljwrites/109724660651747328">Mastodon post</a> written on January 21, 2023.</p>
<h2 id="read-the-story-first">Read the story first!</h2>
<p>The <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-022-04550-2">Schwarzschild Defence</a> by M. V. Melcer is a very fun short science fiction story and highly recommended reading.
I particularly love its punchy style that delivers so much in so few words.
Its choices are effective for the story told, from the format of giving only one side of the interview to the downright chilling twists, delivered so nonchalantly.
It feels fresh while having a really classic sci-fi feel, down to the commentary on gender roles and violence against women (consider that a content warning).</p>
<p>Still, I can&rsquo;t be the only one who thinks it doesn&rsquo;t work legally or even physics-wise, right?
If you like overthinking things, and more importantly if you&rsquo;ve read the story, maybe you&rsquo;d like  to join me in overthinking a delightful story!</p>
<p>Seriously. Read it. It&rsquo;s less than a thousand words and brilliantly written. I&rsquo;ll wait.</p>
<h2 id="checking-the-laws">Checking the Laws</h2>
<p>So, can you see why it doesn&rsquo;t make sense?
Legally speaking, even if we take the narrator of the story, let&rsquo;s call her &ldquo;Mileva,&rdquo; at her word that Xavier will not die (a claim I highly doubt, see below), she has by her admission committed some pretty serious crimes.</p>
<p>One is the crime of false imprisonment, meaning detaining someone against their will without legal justification.
Mileva sabotaged Xavier into an inescapable prison and there&rsquo;s no way this doesn&rsquo;t count as false imprisonment, <em>especially</em> when she was reckless enough to admit at least twice to the police that this wasn&rsquo;t what Xavier intended or wanted with the flight.</p>
<p>In the jurisdiction I live in, false imprisonment carries a penalty of up to 10 years&rsquo; incarceration if committed against a spouse or other close family member.
Committing cruel acts against a close family member while keeping them falsely imprisoned carries a penalty of at <em>least</em> 2 years&rsquo; imprisonment.
The penalty is increased by up to 50% if the false imprisonment is done with the possession of a dangerous object, and both the black hole and the tampered-with spaceship arguably qualify.</p>
<p>Overall, Mileva is looking at some pretty heavy charges and had better get her lawyers scrambling.
Given the severity of the effects, the incontrovertible evidence, and her intent, freely admitted to a police detective&ndash;without a lawyer to advise her, what was she thinking?!&ndash;to trap Xavier in the black hole, it is <em>very</em> likely she will have the book thrown at her.</p>
<p>Mileva has also, by her admission, tampered with sensitive equipment, damaging Xavier&rsquo;s property knowing he is undertaking a dangerous and sensitive flight.
Through this she caused Xavier to make unwanted contact with the event horizon of the black hole, which is battery.</p>
<p>Even <em>if</em> Xavier suffers no other physical harm (which I doubt, more on that soon), slowing down his physical process well beyond human levels is unwanted interference with his body, a form of inflicted physical injury that exacerbates the crimes of false imprisonment and battery.
I&rsquo;m sure there have been more crimes committed, but these are some of the big ones.</p>
<h2 id="checking-the-laws-of-physics">Checking the Laws of Physics</h2>
<p>The charges outlined above rest on Mileva&rsquo;s insistence that Xavier is physically unharmed and will live a long, long time in the black hole.
But will he?
I&rsquo;m not formally trained in physics so I&rsquo;m on less certain ground here, but it doesn&rsquo;t seem that way to me, and discussions like <a href="https://math.ucr.edu/home/baez/physics/Relativity/BlackHoles/fall_in.html">this one</a> seem to confirm my suspicion.</p>
<p>If time slows down as you go down a black hole and the gravitational pull becomes inescapable, wouldn&rsquo;t the parts of the spaceship and of Xavier be pulled down at different rates, meaning he and the spaceship will be literally atomized?
If anything he&rsquo;s going to have the longest, most protracted death ever.
Not that I care, the guy&rsquo;s an ass and deserves it, but the whole twist of the story depends on Mileva&rsquo;s actions not being murder.</p>
<p>I mean maybe Mileva is right, and the story was worded very cleverly here, that this Xavier-molasses and his eventual atom-level explosion will happen so slowly in a Schwarzschild black hole, at a time scale well beyond everyone&rsquo;s lifespans, that it can&rsquo;t be murder in the conventional sense.
Murder revolves around the idea of cutting someone&rsquo;s life short, so what do you do when someone stretches it <em>out,</em> longer and longer beyond the shape lives were ever meant to take, before a horrible end?</p>
<p>This is why I believe the better legal tacks to take are false imprisonment, battery, and attendant serious injury with property damage and sabotage sprinkled in for spice.
But under no circumstance can Mileva get away scot-free as she claims.</p>
<h2 id="notes-and-conclusions">Notes &amp; Conclusions</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;d like to note this isn&rsquo;t me endorsing the incarceral state, far less the misogyny and threats Mileva was subjected to by her account.
All I&rsquo;m doing is analyzing the internal logic of the story, which is remarkable for raising these questions at all.
If Isaac Asimove can stretch, or shall we say fail to stretch, the science in almost exactly the same way in his classic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Billiard_Ball">The Billiard Ball</a> (1967), a fudging he freely admitted to, I don&rsquo;t see why M. V. Melcer can&rsquo;t be afforded the same leniency.
Science fiction is <em>fiction</em> in the end, and between perfect fidelity to the facts and a good story there&rsquo;s no harm in choosing the latter.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
