<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Un-author-ized writer</title>
    <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Un-author-ized writer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>CC BY-NC</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0900</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://ljwrites.blog/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Dragon&#39;s Son Defeats the God of Plague</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/cheoyong-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/cheoyong-story/</guid>
      <description>Before Koreans knew smallpox as a virus, we knew her as a god.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Note: This essay was originally posted in 2020 to the now-defunct history.expert, during the early days of the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
<h2 id="on-the-god-of-plague-and-the-story-of-cheoyong">On the god of plague and the story of Cheoyong</h2>
<p>Before Koreans knew smallpox as a virus, we knew her as a god.
With no way to prevent this terrible infectious disease which had a mortality rate of up to 80% and often left survivors scarred and disabled, we called smallpox by names like “Great Lady” or “Great Guest.”</p>
<p>You could not try to exorcise or even use medicine against the Lady-God; you offered her food and prayed to her in the hope she would spare your loved one, who all too often was a child.
Make her angry by disrespecting her, and she could kill the patient or leave them alive but badly scarred, even blinded.</p>
<p>Though the god of smallpox has been personified as different genders and forms from all walks of life, as befitting a disease that could be spread and suffered by anyone, the most familiar shamanic representation is that of a beautiful young woman and that is the version I will go with.</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://ljwrites.blog/img/history/smallpox-goddess.jpeg"
         alt="A smiling, richly dressed woman with her hands in full sleeves. Two well-dressed young children, a boy and a girl, stand on each side of her with their hands together."/> 
</figure>

<p>A painting of Hogumama, the smallpox goddess. <a href="https://blog.naver.com/PostView.naver?blogId=garamart0422&amp;logNo=221702103970&amp;categoryNo=22&amp;parentCategoryNo=0">Source</a></p>
<p>Now, one figure from the Korean kingdom of Silla in the late ninth century earned the respect and repentance of this terrible and formidable god.
This man, Cheoyong(處容), has a strange story of his own:</p>
<p>Heon-gang, the king of Silla at the time, was returning from a seaside excursion when all of a sudden cloud and fog rolled in, causing the entire party to lose their way.
The royal sun-administrator, as the weather official who was also in charge of weather-related omens and divination, advised the king that this was the work of the Dragon King of the East Sea, who should be appeased by some good deed.</p>
<p>Though the king was skeptical, no one could see anything because of the strange weather and he had to do something.
He ordered a temple be built in that place for the dragon; the instant he said the words, the fog and clouds disappeared.</p>
<p>Pleased at this respectful treatment from the king, the Dragon of the East Sea appeared before the royal retinue with his seven sons to dance and play music, praising the king’s virtue.
The dragon then left one of his sons, Cheoyong, with the king to aid him at the capital.
The king, happy to have the Dragon’s son by his side, arranged his match to a beautiful woman and gave him a high office to have him settle in the capital.</p>
<p>Cheoyong’s wife was very beautiful, and was admired by all. The god of plague, enamored of her, transformed to come to Cheoyong’s house and secretly lie in his wife’s bed.
Cheoyong came home late at night to look upon his bed, only to see two people in it.
One was his wife, but he did not recognize the other.
At the sight he withdrew, dancing and singing:</p>
<div class="verse">
<p>東京明期月良<br />
夜入伊遊行如可<br />
入良沙寢矣見昆<br />
脚烏伊四是良羅<br />
二兮隐吾下於叱古<br />
二兮隐誰支下焉古<br />
本矣吾下是如馬於隐<br />
奪叱良乙何如爲理古<br />
<br />
Through the city in the light of the moon<br />
I did frolic in the deep of night<br />
I look upon the couch on coming home<br />
And four legs greet my astonished sight.<br />
Two were mine<br />
Whose are the other two?<br />
What once was mine<br />
Was taken, what can I do?<br /></p>
</div>
<p>The god of plague showed her true form and knelt before Cheoyong, contrite.
Said she, “I envied your wife and have now violated her.
Yet you showed no anger at the sight, and this beautiful conduct has moved me deeply.
I swear to you, if I but see your form in paint I will not enter that door.”</p>
<p>This was how people started putting up portraits of Cheoyong to deter plague and for good luck.
The temple the king built for the dragon was called Mang-hae-sa(望海寺), the Temple of the Ocean View.
Cheoyong&rsquo;s song and dance, named Cheoyong’s Song and Cheoyong’s Dance, have been passed on to posterity and the dance is performed to this day, designated as a <a href="https://ich.unesco.org/en/RL/cheoyongmu-00189">UNESCO intangible heritage</a>.</p>
<h2 id="the-middle-eastern-hypothesis-of-cheoyong-s-origin">The Middle Eastern hypothesis of Cheoyong&rsquo;s origin</h2>
<p>One intriguing hypothesis about Cheoyong’s identity is that he was an Arab or Persian merchant, possibly a doctor.
Though there are no explicit records, traders from the Middle East may have been in Silla at this time.
At the very least the name Silla was known in the Middle East, with scholars such as Ibn Khurdaziba in the 9th century writing about Silla as a land beyond China where Muslims happily settled because it was a such a good and plentiful land&mdash;much like Cheoyong did in the story.
In the Persian epic poem <em>Kush-Nama</em> the hero Abtin marries Fararang, a princess of Basila which is alleged to be a mythical version of Silla.</p>
<p>Also, the later Korean dynasty of Goryeo clearly did engage in trade with the Islam world:
The name “Korea” itself became known to the West through the use by Middle Eastern merchants.
It is an intriguing possibility that exchange between the Korean Peninsula and the Middle East started even before it was recorded in the Goryeo era.</p>
<p>The accounts of Cheoyong’s appearance before the king are suggestive as well.
The fact that he and his family rose out of the sea could be a mythologized rendition of their seafaring, while their strange appearance and clothing astonished the Korean onlookers and caused them to call the strangers “spirits of the sea.”
More specifically, Cheoyong is referenced as having deep-set eyes and a prominent nose, features that have been preserved in an exaggerated form in his portraiture and the mask performers wear for his dance.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://ljwrites.blog/img/history/cheoyong-mask.jpg" alt="A dancer in Cheoyong&amp;rsquo;s mask. The dark-faced mask smiles wide. The rugged features include deep-set eyes, prominent nose and cheekbones, and facial hair."  />

A performance of Cheoyong&rsquo;s dance in his mask. <a href="https://mnews.imaeil.com/page/view/2017071400510727189">Source</a></p>
<p>The Islamic world also had some of the most advanced medical knowledge in the world at this time, building on the preserved knowledge from the classical world and adding to it with innovation and observation.
The year 879 when Cheoyong was said to have come from the sea was early in the career of Muhammad ibn Zakariya al-Razi (854-925), a Persian doctor and polymath who wrote a pioneering book on smallpox and measles.</p>
<p>If Cheoyong were a Middle Eastern man with medical knowledge he may well have had access to the kind of research and methods Al-Razi used, if not the specific book, which may have enabled him to treat people afflicted with smallpox.
These events may then have been mythologized as Koreans at the time understood it, as a ceremonial appeasement of the smallpox god, making him an enduring legend and himself a beloved god in our pantheon.</p>
<h2 id="in-conclusion-solidarity-in-times-of-plague">In conclusion: Solidarity in times of plague</h2>
<p>Cheoyong’s exact identity and background, including whether he was a real person, will always remain mysterious and up for debate.
Nevertheless, the possibility that he was an Arab or Persian is particularly poignant at a time when COVID-19 is bringing out virulent xenophobia and racism around the world.
Cheoyong may well have been a foreigner risking his life in a strange land to help patients struck with a deadly and highly contagious disease.</p>
<p>And now, 1,100 years later, Iran is hard hit by the disease and by the sanctions that are undercutting its response.
It is requesting Korea’s aid to secure more testing kits for citizens, an effort made difficult by the sanctions imposed against it.
This may very well be the time Korea can repay the debt it owes Cheoyong.
Wouldn’t such beautiful conduct move even the fearsome god of plague?</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p><strong>The original tale:</strong> <a href="https://ko.wikisource.org/wiki/%EB%B2%88%EC%97%AD:%EC%82%BC%EA%B5%AD%EC%9C%A0%EC%82%AC/%EA%B6%8C%EC%A0%9C2#%EC%B2%98%EC%9A%A9%EB%9E%91_%EB%A7%9D%ED%95%B4%EC%82%AC">Sir Cheoyong and the Temple of the Ocean View(處容郞望海寺)</a>, Book 2 of Stories from the Three Kingdoms(三國遺事).</p>
<p><strong>Cheoyong&rsquo;s tale as an appeasement of the smallpox god:</strong> Hwang Byeong-ik (2011). <a href="http://dbpia.co.kr/journal/articleDetail?nodeId=NODE01644915">The Study about Original Form of Small Pox Goddess &amp; the Meaning of Silla 〈Cheoyong-ga〉</a>. Journal of Korean Studies (formerly Journal of Spiritual Culture Studies), 34(2), 127-152.</p>
<p><strong>Silla-Middle East relations:</strong> Muhammad Kansu/Jeong Su-il (1990). The History of Relations Between Silla and Arab Muslim Countries. Ph.D. thesis for the History Department of Dankook University.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Delightful Spring Night Rain</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/delightful-spring-night-rain/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/delightful-spring-night-rain/</guid>
      <description>It trails the wind, comes stealing in at night / Bedews all things with thin and soundless threads.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>春夜喜雨 (Delightful Spring Night Rain)</p>
<p>&mdash; Du Fu (杜甫), 8th century Chinese poet</p>
<div class="verse">
<p>好雨知時節 當春乃發生<br />
<br />
The good rain knows the season when it&rsquo;s right<br />
With spring upon us, timely does it tread<br />
<br />
隨風潛入夜 潤物細無聲<br />
<br />
It trails the wind, comes stealing in at night<br />
Bedews all things with thin and soundless threads.<br />
<br />
野徑雲俱黑 江船火獨明<br />
<br />
Above the wild paths all the clouds are black<br />
While lonely light on river barge does glow<br />
<br />
曉看紅濕處 花重錦官城<br />
<br />
At dawn the earth in spots is red and damp<br />
On Citadel of Silk<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> the blossoms blow.<br />
<br /></p>
</div>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Jinguancheng, the Citadel of the Silk Service (锦官城), was a nickname for Chengdu (成都) in Sichuan for the silk management bureau in that city. A variation on this name was Jincheng, the Silk Citadel (锦城), which is the one I used for cadence in this translation.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We Part as Friends</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/we-part-as-friends-translation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/we-part-as-friends-translation/</guid>
      <description>When on this ground we once do say farewell, / Alone, far-flung, we&amp;rsquo;ll tread a thousand miles.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>送友人 (We Part as Friends)</p>
<p>&mdash; Li Bai (李白), 8th-century Chinese poet</p>
<p>靑山橫北郭</p>
<p>The mountains green lie &rsquo;thwart the Northern walls,</p>
<p>白水遶東城</p>
<p>The river glows wrapped round the Eastern hold.</p>
<p>此地一爲別</p>
<p>When on this ground we once do say farewell,</p>
<p>孤蓬萬里征</p>
<p>Alone, far-flung, we&rsquo;ll tread a thousand miles.</p>
<p>浮雲遊子意</p>
<p>The clouds drift on as do our wanderers&rsquo; hearts;</p>
<p>落日故人情</p>
<p>The setting sun with strength of yearning burns.</p>
<p>揮手自玆去</p>
<p>We wave our hands and from this place depart&ndash;</p>
<p>蕭蕭班馬鳴</p>
<p>Our mounts call out on parting, quite forlorn.</p>
<hr>
<p>Yeah I took an ancient Chinese poem and made it cynical &amp; gay lol.
I was inspired by Zoë C.&rsquo;s translation of the same poem, <a href="https://zoe-translat.es/translations/a-parting-song/">found here</a>, to make a quite different translation.</p>
<p>The differences are very indicative of our styles, I think, and I enjoyed the understated and quietly intense lyricism and voice of Zoë&rsquo;s rendition.
Whereas I, as always, prefer classical iambic metre for classical poetry and use it to build up to big, dramatic emotions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crystal stream from verdant mount</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/crystal-stream-verdant-mount/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/crystal-stream-verdant-mount/</guid>
      <description>Translation of a famous sijo from Chosun-era poet Hwang Jinyi</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Originally posted to the fedi on <a href="https://rage.love/web/statuses/107002808081339831">September 27, 2021</a>.
David McCann&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0zea3P4s-lM&amp;t=550s">lecture</a> about this sijo inspired some of my choices for this translation.</p>
<hr>
<div class="verse">
<p>靑山裏 碧溪水야 수이 감을 자랑마라<br />
  Thou crystal stream from verdant mount,<br />
  quit bragging on your easy flow.<br />
<br />
一到滄海하면 다시 오기 어려웨라<br />
  Once embraced by azure expanse,<br />
  you&rsquo;re not coming round no more.<br />
<br />
明月이 滿空山하니 쉬어 간들 어떠리<br />
  Void replete with lunar brilliance,<br />
  why not take a load off, love?<br /></p>
</div>
<p>&mdash; Hwang Jinyi (1506-1567), poet, artist, performer and courtesan.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing year in review: My 2022 writing habit on Emacs</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/2022-writing-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/2022-writing-review/</guid>
      <description>What is most meaningful to me about my writing habit is that the dream of writing this story is no longer a dream, but my waking reality.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My New Year&rsquo;s resolution for 2022 was to write 300 words every day on the first draft of my big fiction project.
Plot twist, I actually stuck to it!
Just don&rsquo;t ask about the state of my physical activity habit, please.</p>
<p>Here are the year&rsquo;s writing statistics from writing most days from January 2 to December 31, 2022, taken using functionalities and packages of Emacs Org Mode, and my takeaways from these numbers.</p>
<h2 id="the-words-and-the-hours">The words and the hours</h2>
<p>According to a word count and Org Mode&rsquo;s <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/The-clock-table.html">clock table</a> report, I wrote somewhere around <strong>170,000 words</strong> this year in 11 days, 2 hours, and 9 minutes, or around <strong>266 hours of writing.</strong></p>
<p>These numbers come with some caveats:
The word count function does give me an exact count, 174,369, but this is an overcount that includes elements that won&rsquo;t be exported such as header (scene) labels, in-file notes, and time stamps.
This works for me, since I only need a rough estimate of where I am and not a laser-precise word count.
Besides, even considering the overcount I know this is Too Much!
I&rsquo;m going to hate my first-draft self once I have my editing hat on, that&rsquo;s for sure.</p>
<p>The hours spent writing are similarly imprecise.
I started using Org Mode&rsquo;s <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Clocking-commands.html">clocking commands</a> fairly early in the year (January 5) to start keeping track of writing time, and there&rsquo;s some undercount from the first few days when the clock was not used.
Discounting that fairly small gap, which can&rsquo;t be by more than 2 hours, I was also inconsistent at times about running the clock.
Sometimes I ran the clock but was not writing, and at other times it was the other way around, though this was rarer.
For these reasons both the word count and reported time are more estimates than exact measures.</p>
<h2 id="words-per-hour-and-day">Words per hour and day</h2>
<p>Keeping those limitations in mind, a very rough estimate of my writing speed this year was <strong>639 words/hour</strong>, and I wrote an average of <strong>465 words a day</strong> during the year, counting the skipped days.
On the days I did write the average was <strong>544 words a day</strong>.</p>
<p>The estimated hourly word rate largely matches up with what I&rsquo;ve sensed on a regular day of writing, that I tend to produce about 100 words per 10 minutes or maybe a little more.
The per-day rate is a bit of a surprise, given that my goal was to write 300 words a day and I often did stop at almost exactly 300 words, especially on days the words weren&rsquo;t coming.
I guess it makes sense though, since I did overachieve a lot of days, by a lot at times.</p>
<p>The ironic/interesting part is, I think it was my keeping the goal at 300 words that allowed me to write an average of 500 words a day.
A lot of days I could only bear to start writing because I told myself I just had to do 300 words, and actually stopped at 300 when I was struggling and tired.
There were many days I could not have started at all at the thought of having to write 500 words a day, and that would have meant a lot fewer words.</p>
<h2 id="habit-consistency-and-achievement">Habit consistency and achievement</h2>
<p>In addition to writing and getting these stats in Org Mode, I had also been tracking my writing <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Tracking-your-habits.html">as a habit</a>.
At the end of 2022 I used a neat package called <a href="https://github.com/ml729/org-habit-stats">org-habit-stats</a> to get a calendar view and some statistics on the writing habit.</p>
<p>According to the statistics, I wrote <strong>312 days</strong> out of the year, or <strong>85%</strong> of days in 2022.
Nearly a third of the missed days come from February when I was having a hard time keeping up with writing, as seen in this calendar view of writing statistics:</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://ljwrites.blog/img/emacs/org-habit-stat-1-3.png"
         alt="Marked calendar view of habit from January to March with a handful of days missing from January and March, and more than half the days missing from February."/> 
</figure>

<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://ljwrites.blog/img/emacs/org-habit-stat-4-6.png"
         alt="Calendar view from April to June with two days missing from each month."/> 
</figure>

<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://ljwrites.blog/img/emacs/org-habit-stat-7-9.png"
         alt="Calendar view from July to September with two to four days missing from each month."/> 
</figure>

<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://ljwrites.blog/img/emacs/org-habit-stat-10-12.png"
         alt="Calendar view from October to December with three to four days missing from each month."/> 
</figure>

<p>As you can see I generally wrote on most days of the month, usually missing two to four days in a month.
Those would have been the days when I was overwhelmed by work or family obligations, or just needed a break.</p>
<p>The one outlier is February, when I was missing over half the days of the month.
This was likely because I was wrapping up my last academic gig during that month before I turned to full-time translation in March, something that made a huge difference in my free time and energy levels.</p>
<p>It wasn&rsquo;t as though I became a different person with more energy or &ldquo;willpower&rdquo; between the end of February and the start of March.
I had simply structured my life in a way that made room for writing and that made all the difference, which may be the true takeaway from this year of writing.</p>
<h2 id="numbers-for-what-they-re-worth">Numbers, for what they&rsquo;re worth</h2>
<p>Word count and hours spent writing are just numbers at the end of the day&ndash;or year, as it were.
They&rsquo;re mostly meaningful to me as an indication for how far I&rsquo;ve come, even as I realize how far I still have to go.
The story has grown in length far beyond my original expectations and I&rsquo;m just slogging on to get to the end of my originally envisioned story, so I can turn around to figure out stuff like editing (I expect to cut extravagantly) and book divisions.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;d frankly have been happier to have reached the end of my draft than to have written so many words, but I&rsquo;m letting the process take control for now as I try to feel out the world and narrative by writing through them.
Stats are one part of that journey but far from the whole experience, any more than kilometers and hours driven can tell you about the scenery seen outside the window or the smell of the car seats.</p>
<p>What is most meaningful to me about my writing habit is that the dream of writing this story is no longer a dream but my waking reality, and that it <em>will</em> be done at some point barring some huge, unforeseen change.
I know I am moving toward the endpoint, steadily if slowly.
Once I get there, I will know the key was the momentum of consistent habit.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Object storage on Mastodon with a Backblaze B2 bucket</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/mastodon-b2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/mastodon-b2/</guid>
      <description>Here&amp;rsquo;s how I set up a Backblaze B2 bucket with a local proxy for Mastodon object storage.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="a-little-background-and-why-b2">A little background &amp; why B2?</h2>
<p>It was kind of background knowledge for me that object storage was an option in Mastodon hosting, but I never felt much need for it on my tiny instance.
Then it became an urgent issue when fedi activity exploded in November in the wake of the Twitter meltdown.
My instance database started crashing from the 40 GB local drive overflowing with cached media, and constantly ran at above 30 GB even when I left only one day&rsquo;s worth of cache at media cleanup (<code>tootctl media remove --days 1</code>).</p>
<p>I already had a Backblaze/B2 account that I had been using for my personal offsite backups, and I calculated that I could similarly hook it up to my Hometown/Mastodon instance at a fraction of the cost of adding more storage volume to the Hetzner server.
I also wanted to keep using B2 for this rather than create a new account with AWS or some other storage service, feeling no need to complicate things with yet another account and service to keep track of.</p>
<p>The problem I ran into was that this particular combination of Mastodon and B2 is <em>woefully</em> underdocumented, even with B2&rsquo;s S3-compatibility.
This led me into a lot of trial and error because the documentation I did find was outdated<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> and/or did not mention issues unique to B2, like a huge authentication pitfall that I ended up pitching headfirst into.</p>
<p>Let me discuss that pitfall first, in case you don&rsquo;t need the rest of this guide:
<strong>You need to use a B2 application key, NOT a master application key, for this purpose.</strong>
If, like me, you have everything set up correctly and media uploads fail for an unexplained reason, this might be why.
More details in Step 1 below.</p>
<p>So here it is, the walkthrough of the process and settings that I wished I had when I configured my setup, put together from other sources and my own trial and error.</p>
<h2 id="step-1-set-up-a-b2-bucket-and-application-key-for-your-instance">Step 1: Set up a B2 bucket and application key for your instance</h2>
<p>This part is going to be pretty obvious if you already use B2.
Otherwise, the <a href="https://help.backblaze.com/hc/en-us/articles/1260803542610-Creating-a-B2-Bucket-using-the-Web-UI">official tutorial for creating a bucket</a> should be enough.
Everything I have read says the privacy setting of the bucket should be public, though this comes at a risk because it means anyone can download from the bucket which could potentially eat into your traffic limit and cost you.
If you haven&rsquo;t done so already, you might have to verify your email to set the bucket to public.</p>
<p>Make note of the bucket&rsquo;s address, which will be the endpoint noted in your bucket information preceded by your bucket name.
If you named your bucket <code>my-instance-media</code> your bucket address would be something like:</p>
<p>my-instance-media.s3.us-west-900.backblazeb2.com</p>
<p>You can verify this by uploading a file to the bucket and viewing the address of the file, which will be something like:</p>
<p>my-instance-media.s3.us-west-900.backblazeb2.com/my-test-file.txt</p>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t have a B2 application key, <a href="https://help.backblaze.com/hc/en-us/articles/360052129034-Creating-and-Managing-Application-Keys">their official tutorial</a> should get you started.
Also, as discussed above, make sure you use a <strong>non-master</strong> application key pair for this setup in Step 4 below.
Master application keys are <a href="https://kb.msp360.com/cloud-vendors/backblazeb2/backblazeb2-as-s3compatible">NOT S3-compatible</a> (see &ldquo;Warning&rdquo;), and if you set up your <code>.env.production</code> with it your setup will not work!</p>
<p>Note down the application key id-application key pair in a secure location such as your password manager, especially the application key which will only be shown once and never again in your browser interface or otherwise.</p>
<h2 id="step-2-set-up-a-proxy-on-nginx">Step 2: Set up a proxy on nginx</h2>
<p>As noted in the official Mastodon documentation, it is very much recommended that you set up a proxy local to the server to cache  media requested from the bucket on your server.
If every request were to go directly to your bucket your traffic meter could climb rapidly and cost you more money than it has to.
I modeled my nginx configuration for this on <a href="https://thomas-leister.de/en/mastodon-s3-media-storage/">a configuration for a different S3-compatible service</a>, and followed the directions in the <a href="https://docs.joinmastodon.org/admin/optional/object-storage-proxy/">Mastodon documentation</a> on configuring the proxy.</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s what my configuration, anonymized to <code>/etc/nginx/sites-available/files.example.com</code>, looks like:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>    proxy_cache_path   /tmp/nginx-cache-instance-media levels<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>1:2 keys_zone<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>s3_cache:10m max_size<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>10g inactive<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>48h use_temp_path<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>off;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    server <span style="color:#f92672">{</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      listen <span style="color:#ae81ff">443</span> ssl http2;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      listen <span style="color:#f92672">[</span>::<span style="color:#f92672">]</span>:443 ssl http2;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      <span style="color:#75715e"># CUSTOMIZE THE VALUE BELOW TO YOUR OWN SUBDOMAIN</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      server_name files.example.com;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      root /home/mastodon/live/public/system;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      access_log off;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      <span style="color:#75715e"># CUSTOMIZE THE VALUE BELOW TO YOUR DESIRED ERROR LOG FILE NAME</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      error_log /var/log/nginx/files-error.log;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      keepalive_timeout 60;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      location <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> / <span style="color:#f92672">{</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        index index.html;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      <span style="color:#f92672">}</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      location / <span style="color:#f92672">{</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        try_files $uri @s3;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      <span style="color:#f92672">}</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      <span style="color:#75715e"># CUSTOMIZE THE VALUE BELOW TO YOUR BUCKET ADDRESS</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      set $s3_backend <span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;https://my-instance-media.s3.us-west-900.backblazeb2.com&#39;</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span> location @s3 <span style="color:#f92672">{</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   limit_except GET <span style="color:#f92672">{</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>     deny all;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   <span style="color:#f92672">}</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   resolver 9.9.9.9;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   <span style="color:#75715e"># CUSTOMIZE THE VALUE BELOW TO YOUR BUCKET ADDRESS</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_set_header Host <span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;my-instance-media.s3.us-west-900.backblazeb2.com&#39;</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_set_header Connection <span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;&#39;</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_set_header Authorization <span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;&#39;</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_hide_header Set-Cookie;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_hide_header <span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;Access-Control-Allow-Origin&#39;</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_hide_header <span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;Access-Control-Allow-Methods&#39;</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_hide_header <span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;Access-Control-Allow-Headers&#39;</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_hide_header x-amz-id-2;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_hide_header x-amz-request-id;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_hide_header x-amz-meta-server-side-encryption;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_hide_header x-amz-server-side-encryption;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_hide_header x-amz-bucket-region;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_hide_header x-amzn-requestid;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_ignore_headers Set-Cookie;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_pass $s3_backend$uri;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_intercept_errors off;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_cache s3_cache;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_cache_valid <span style="color:#ae81ff">200</span> <span style="color:#ae81ff">304</span> 48h;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_cache_use_stale error timeout updating http_500 http_502 http_503 http_504;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   proxy_cache_lock on;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   expires 1y;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   add_header Cache-Control public;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   add_header <span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;Access-Control-Allow-Origin&#39;</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;*&#39;</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   add_header X-Cache-Status $upstream_cache_status;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#f92672">}</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#f92672">}</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>The specific addresses and names should be customized to your desired settings, as marked in the configuration text.</p>
<p>When the configuration file is written to your satisfaction, save it and symlink it from <code>/etc/nginx/sites-enabled</code>, and reload nginx by running (with <code>sudo</code> if you are not the <code>root</code> user here):</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>ln -s /etc/nginx/sites-available/files.example.com /etc/nginx/sites-enabled/
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>systemctl reload nginx
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Then get a SSL certificate for the domain, as seen in the Mastodon documentation.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>certbot --nginx -d files.example.com
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>systemctl reload nginx
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>This was the main place I diverged from the configuration posted on the thomas-leister.de website, by the way:
I use port 443 for an encrypted connection per the Mastodon documentation rather than 80 for an unencrypted one like Thomas Leister did, mainly because the unencrypted connection broke all the images on my instance lol.</p>
<h2 id="step-3-upload-existing-mastodon-media-to-your-bucket">Step 3: Upload existing Mastodon media to your bucket</h2>
<p>If your instance is already in use, you should upload previously downloaded media to the instance bucket.
There are several different tools to achieve this, and if you already use an S3-compatible tool like <code>aws</code> or <code>s3cmd</code> it should do the job.
Just be aware that you&rsquo;ll need to use an S3-compatible <strong>non</strong>-master B2 application key to authenticate it, as discussed.</p>
<p>I used the official <code>b2</code> command line tool, since it&rsquo;s a simple binary and fairly easy to use.
I downloaded b2 for Linux through the link on <a href="https://www.backblaze.com/b2/docs/quick_command_line.html">this page</a>, uploaded it to the <code>/home/mastodon/live</code> directory (though in hindsight its <code>bin</code> subdirectory would have been more fitting), changed the owner to the mastodon user with:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>sudo chown mastodon:mastodon b2-linux
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Switched to the mastodon user:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>sudo su - mastodon
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Changed the file name to <code>b2</code> for simplicity&rsquo;s sake:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>mv b2-linux b2
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Also gave it execution permission.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>chmod +x b2
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>I didn&rsquo;t mess with <code>$PATH</code> or anything like that, since this wasn&rsquo;t going to be an everyday operation.</p>
<p>You can then create an authentication profile using the application key ID and application key pair generated in Step 1 above.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>./b2 authorize-account --profile my-instance $B2_Application_Key_ID $B2_Application_Key
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>The variables <code>$B2_Application_Key_ID</code> and <code>$B2_Application_Key</code> should be replaced by the actual values, of course.
Or you can actually define the variables I guess, but I didn&rsquo;t feel the need since authentication was a one-time thing and, once successful, the switch <code>--profile my-instance</code> is enough to authenticate all operations.</p>
<p>After setting up the profile with <code>authorize-account</code> you can use some short, harmless command like list-buckets to test whether authentication works:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>./b2 list-buckets --profile my-instance
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Or maybe try uploading a small file or something.
The <code>--help</code> switch is helpful for figuring out the commands and syntax, or simply running b2 without any arguments will also bring up the help options.</p>
<p>Once authentication is confirmed to work, sync the <code>public/system</code> directory to the remote b2 bucket using the <code>sync</code> command. Assuming the command is run from the <code>/home/mastodon/live</code> directory:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>./b2 sync --profile my-instance ./public/system/ b2://my-instance-media/
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>You can read more about  <a href="https://b2-command-line-tool.readthedocs.io/en/master/subcommands/sync.html">b2&rsquo;s sync command options</a>, but I found the default options satisfactory.
It took me about an afternoon to upload 18.5 GB of preexisting data to the bucket.</p>
<h2 id="step-4-mastodon-configuration">Step 4: Mastodon configuration</h2>
<p>My Mastodon configuration in <code>live/.env.production</code> to enable the object storage looks something like this:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>S3_ENABLED<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>true
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>S3_PROTOCOL<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>https
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#75715e"># EVERYTHING BELOW THIS POINT SHOULD BE CUSTOMIZED</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>S3_BUCKET<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>my-instance-media
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>$B2_Application_Key_ID
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>$B2_Application_Key
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>S3_ALIAS_HOST<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>files.example.com
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>S3_HOSTNAME<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>files.example.com
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>S3_REGION<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>us-west-900
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>S3_ENDPOINT<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>https://s3.us-west-900.backblazeb2.com
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>In addition to the earlier point that the application key ID and application key pair should have been generated as a non-master application key, also note the <code>https://</code> in front of the <code>S3_ENDPOINT</code> value.
For me that was the final hurdle to getting the setup to work.</p>
<p>Switch to admin or some other user with <code>sudo</code> power.
From the mastodon user, it just takes an <code>exit</code> command in my case. Restart the Mastodon processes:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>sudo systemctl restart mastodon-*.service
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Check if the instance works normally.
If it&rsquo;s down, the API call to Backblaze storage may be failing and the key id and application key values should be double-checked.</p>
<h2 id="step-5-check-if-object-storage-is-working">Step 5: Check if object storage is working</h2>
<p>As discussed in the <a href="https://thomas-leister.de/en/mastodon-s3-media-storage/">Thomas Leister writeup</a> (&ldquo;Checking if it works&rdquo;), check the browser&rsquo;s console to see if the correct server proxy is loading up for media, and whether media are properly displayed.</p>
<p>Also, try attaching a piece of media to a post.
If the attachment fails with a 500 error, you need to check your settings.</p>
<p>Even after I ironed out the authentication issues with the application key I found media uploads were, understandably, slower than before and they sometimes timed out.
This was why I set the <code>keepalive_timeout</code> value to 60 rather than 30 in the nginx proxy settings and image uploads have not timed out since.</p>
<p>Though Mastodon will be uploading new media to the remote bucket and requesting it remotely, for preexisting media files it will look to the local <code>public/system</code> directory first.
This can make it harder to tell if the bucket setup is working or it&rsquo;s just the local storage doing the work, so if you&rsquo;re impatient you can get rid of that directory to force the instance to load everything from the bucket instead.
From <code>/home/mastodon/live/public</code> you can run:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>mv system/ system_/
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>to change the name of the <code>system</code> directory without immediately deleting everything in it.</p>
<p>You can&rsquo;t simply leave <code>public/system</code> missing, though, if you want to keep the nginx proxy settings as they are.
Guess who found out the hard way this will crash the instance&hellip; :&rsquo;)
Instead, create a new empty <code>system</code> directory so the setting will have somewhere to look to and not throw an error.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>mkdir system
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>If the media still loads properly after this, and new media is fetched and uploaded, it means the setup is working.
Yay!</p>
<h2 id="cleanup-afterwork-and-thoughts">Cleanup, afterwork and thoughts</h2>
<p>You can let this setup run a few days to see whether it keeps working, doesn&rsquo;t overrun your traffic meters etc., before you empty out your local <code>public/system</code> directory, or delete <code>public/system_</code> if you did the directory switch I detailed above.
I can tell you it was quite a weight off to reclaim half my disk space from all that media.</p>
<p>I also ran some <a href="https://docs.joinmastodon.org/admin/tootctl/#accounts-refresh">accounts refresh</a> jobs because I had missing remote profile pics from emergency media deletions, back when my disk had overflowed and the database crashed.
Yeah, things were that bad.</p>
<p>Media loads correctly again on my instance, though there is an initial loading time, and I can get a proper media cache going without my disk at constant risk of running out.
Instance management has become enjoyable again without the constant risk of unplanned server downtime, and I am now able to consider putting other services on the server.</p>
<p>In the long term, media storage is something federated software and communities are going to have to figure out.
Services like <a href="https://jortage.com/">Jortage</a> look interesting something like it may be the future of media storage in the fediverse.
For now I have found a solution that works for my instance, and if this write-up helps others avoid some of my confusion and mistakes I will be happy&ndash;although, let&rsquo;s be real, these tech posts have mainly been helpful to myself for the purpose of record-keeping and documentation.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>For instance, there was a gist stating that Mastodon could not directly interface with B2 for object storage because B2 was not S3-compatible, and MinIO would be needed as a relay. This was seemingly confirmed by documentation from Backblaze itself stating its S3 incompatibility. Turns out this was back in 2019-2020 and, as of late 2022, B2 is S3 compatible and MinIO no longer provides the relay function. Guess who only realized this after installing MinIO.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How NaNoWriMo Broke me, and What I Learned from the Experience</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/nanowrimo-experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/nanowrimo-experience/</guid>
      <description>I crashed and burned on overachieving NaNoWriMo, but learned some valuable lessons from the experience.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="intro-or-tl-dr">Intro, or TL; DR</h2>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t write 50,000 words of a novel in a month for Camp NaNoWriMo in July of 2014, one of the alternate months of the National Novel Writing Month challenge.</p>
<p>I wrote 100,000 words.</p>
<p>Then I promptly flamed out and could barely write for months at a time, in a writing slump that lasted for years.</p>
<p>Spoiler alert, there&rsquo;s an eventual happy ending, or happy ongoing:
I came back from the burnout after some years and now have a stable writing routine, making progress on the story.
Still, boy was that experience a crash course, emphasis on &ldquo;crash,&rdquo; in what does and does not work for me.</p>
<h2 id="in-which-we-start-out-with-great-expectations">In which we start out with great expectations</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;d been meaning for some time to work on the story idea I&rsquo;d been sporadically working on and researching for since around 2008.
I found the idea of National Novel-Writing Month attractive as a way of getting a first draft&ndash;no matter how shitty&ndash;in hand quickly.
Between grad school and a job, it was hard to get the time and energy to write and I thought forcing myself to write a Ridiculous Amount every day might be a way to do it.
You can probably glimpse the seeds of failure already in my line of thinking.</p>
<p>As I often do when I start something new, I read a whole book on the subject:
<em>No Plot? No Problem!</em> by the founder of NaNo himself.
I thought I had the idea down and liked the thought of getting words out in a gush from the subconscious, silencing the inner critic by making myself meet a word count threshold no matter what.</p>
<p>Already familiar with the technique from freewriting which I had used in journaling, I was ready to apply it to my first draft.
I also had an outline ready ahead of time, since I was used to writing by outline.</p>
<h2 id="in-which-our-hero-does-everything-right-or-so-she-thought">In which our hero does everything right, or so she thought</h2>
<p>Come July, I wrote every single day.
I wrote on subways and buses on commute; I wrote at home, I wrote riding on the exercise bike.
About 50,000 words into my original outline and with time left in the month, I decided the direction I was taking the story didn&rsquo;t work and outlined again.
The second outline was a bust, too, and so was the short-lived third outline.</p>
<p>Still, I kept writing no matter how crappy the output, trusting in the process and trying to soar on the wings of my subconscious through a maelstrom of terrible writing.
By the end of the month I had blown past the original 50,000-word goal and pushed out 100,000 words on three different drafts.
Progress, right?</p>
<p>Well&hellip; no.
Not in a straight line, anyway.
None of the drafts I had written ultimately worked, and I couldn&rsquo;t even bear to look back on them, not only because they were awful and no longer usable for my evolving conception of the story, but because they were associated with the memory of pushing myself to write beyond my own comfort.</p>
<p>My problems didn&rsquo;t stop with the unusable drafts: I also burned out on writing and couldn&rsquo;t work on the story for months.
I&rsquo;d work on it for a few days and then put it on hold for months, even over a year at a time, not helped by the continuing rush of school and work.
It would be a while and some life changes before I found a workable direction and a settled routine that let me make steady progress with the story.</p>
<h2 id="in-which-we-reflect-on-lessons-learned">In which we reflect on lessons learned</h2>
<p>Maybe NaNoWriMo did help me in the sense that I needed to run down those dead ends to get to where I am in the story, and NaNo let me get the trial-and-error out of the way on fast forward.
Even more valuable, though, was that I learned about my own process as a writer, both what works and doesn&rsquo;t work for me.</p>
<p>First, the freewriting-style &ldquo;let your subconscious take over&rdquo; school of writing does not work for me when writing fiction.
I&rsquo;d gotten some mileage out of it for journaling, as discussed, but it&rsquo;s just not how I work on story drafts, even first drafts.
I certainly don&rsquo;t need or want a perfect, or even good, first draft, but I do need to put some thought into making things at least coherent if I want to make the draft a meaningful basis for future work.</p>
<p>Second, for me, forcing a large word count is a recipe for burnout.
It&rsquo;s too painful, and ultimately unsustainable.
I&rsquo;m very much a &ldquo;slow and steady&rdquo; kind of writer, and in a way I owe that self-knowledge to NaNo.
Live and learn, though the lesson may be painful.</p>
<p>Third, my experience with NaNo may also have been when I started to let go of the fantasy of having it all, and realized I couldn&rsquo;t fill up all my time with work and then somehow cram writing in there as well.
I would have to make room in my life for a writing practice, and that would entail real life changes, scary as they were.
There were no shortcuts.
I had to put in the time, effort, and commitment.
Actually acting on this realization would take more time and effort, and is a story for another time.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion-don-t-look-back-in-anger">Conclusion: Don&rsquo;t look back in anger</h2>
<p>NaNo might not have worked for me and I will never do it in its full form again, but I learned from it and I wish good luck and good fun to the many thousands of writers who will be undertaking the challenge this coming November and afterward.
I&rsquo;ll be cheering from the sidelines, continuing in my own way and at my own pace.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Ballad of Mulan</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/ballad-of-mulan/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/ballad-of-mulan/</guid>
      <description>The long, grim cloak of war do I cast off / The skirt of girlhood I put on with love.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Originally posted <a href="https://rage.love/@ljwrites/104828995995274477">on Mastodon</a> on September 8, 2020.</p>
<div class="verse">
<br />
唧唧復唧唧，木蘭當戶織。不聞機杼聲，惟聞女嘆息。<br />
<br />
Hark to the sound of murmurs fill the room;<br />
Mulan before the door does toil at loom.<br />
The shuttle slacks; the clacking silent falls,<br />
The only sound the maid's lamenting call.<br />
<br />
問女何所思，問女何所憶。女亦無所思，女亦無所憶。<br />
<br />
You wonder where the maiden's thoughts may bend,<br />
What memory might her give such sweet torment.<br />
Yet no phantasm grips her sturdy heart,<br />
Nor does remembrance cause her aught of doubt.<br />
<br />
昨夜見軍帖，可汗大點兵，軍書十二卷，卷卷有爺名。<br />
<br />
Past eve were seen the martial rosters grand;<br />
The Khan calls forth a muster 'cross the land.<br />
The names march onward far as you can look,<br />
And Father's name is found in every book.<br />
<br />
阿爺無大兒，木蘭無長兄，願爲市鞍馬，從此替爺徵。<br />
<br />
There's no grown son to stand in Father's stead;<br />
No brother rides so she may rest her head.<br />
At market will she buy her horse and gear,<br />
And take her Father's place wherefore to serve.<br />
<br />
東市買駿馬，西市買鞍韉，南市買轡頭，北市買長鞭。<br />
<br />
Eastward she goes, the finest horse to buy;<br />
Westward she goes for saddle fit to fly.<br />
Southward she goes for bridle and a rein,<br />
Northward she goes; a riding crop is gained.<br />
<br />
旦辭爺孃去，暮宿黃河邊，不聞爺孃喚女聲，但聞黃河流水鳴濺濺。<br />
<br />
At morning blush she rides, by parents blessed;<br />
At nighttime dark by Yellow River slept.<br />
No longer does she hear her parents' call,<br />
Only the mighty water crash and fall.<br />
<br />
旦辭黃河去，暮至黑山頭，不聞爺孃喚女聲，但聞燕山胡騎鳴啾啾。<br />
<br />
She rides at dawn, the river at her back;<br />
Encamp'd by night at the feet of Mountains Black.<br />
No longer does she hear her parents' voice,<br />
Only the savage horsemen's screaming noise.<br />
<br />
萬里赴戎機，關山度若飛。朔氣傳金柝，寒光照鐵衣。將軍百戰死，壯士十年歸。<br />
<br />
Machines of war a thousand leagues do blaze,<br />
Fly past the strongholds, 'cross the mountain ways.<br />
The frigid wind resounds with striking steel;<br />
A frozen light is burnt on coats of mail.<br />
A hundred battles fought, and many fall;<br />
A decade's strife finds some still standing tall.<br />
<br />
歸來見天子，天子坐明堂。策勳十二轉，賞賜百千強。<br />
<br />
They come before the Son of Heaven high<br />
Who sits in glory on the throne of light.<br />
By all reports, courageous deeds were done;<br />
Reward is given, just and princely sums.<br />
<br />
可汗問所欲，木蘭不用尚書郎，願馳千里足，送兒還故鄉。<br />
<br />
The Khan inquires, aught else does she desire?<br />
Mulan thinks not of office nor of honor,<br />
Her only wish to ride a thousand miles<br />
Bound for the much-loved home where she would dwell.<br />
<br />
爺孃聞女來，出郭相扶將；阿姊聞妹來，當戶理紅妝；小弟聞姊來，磨刀霍霍向豬羊。<br />
<br />
Her parents head outside the city gates;<br />
Clinging to one another, they but wait.<br />
Big Sister, told Mulan will soon be there,<br />
Puts on her dress and make-up with some care.<br />
The Little Brother, welcome feast to roast,<br />
Sharpens the knives and hurries to the goats.<br />
<br />
開我東閣門，坐我西閣牀，脫我戰時袍，著我舊時裳。當窗理雲鬢，對鏡貼花黃。<br />
<br />
"Eastward I open up the bower door;<br />
Westward I sit upon my platform chair.<br />
The long, grim cloak of war do I cast off;<br />
The skirt of girlhood I put on with love.<br />
By window clear I fix my cloud-soft hair;<br />
In mirror bright affix the flowers fair."<br />
<br />
出門看火伴，火伴皆驚忙：同行十二年，不知木蘭是女郎。<br />
<br />
Outside she steps to meet her comrades' eyes,<br />
And to a man they start in their surprise.<br />
A decade on, they've been through thick and thin;<br />
In all this time they never dreamed Mulan was not a man!<br />
<br />
雄兔腳撲朔，雌兔眼迷離；雙兔傍地走，安能辨我是雄雌？<br />
<br />
"When held, a rabbit male will kick its feet,<br />
While rabbit female looks through eyes that slit.<br />
When they run close to ground and side by side<br />
Female or male am I, can you decide?"<br />
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Heroine of the Game Carto Is Nonspeaking (and It&#39;s Totally Cool)</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/carto-game-nonspeaking/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 May 2022 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/carto-game-nonspeaking/</guid>
      <description>The heroine of the indie game Carto is a nonspeaking girl, and it&amp;rsquo;s neither tragic nor remarkable.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I had a lot of fun playing the indie game <em>Carto</em> (2020), an innovative and enjoyable puzzle game where you put map pieces together, changing in-game reality itself to overcome obstacles and help reunite our heroine Carto and her grandmother.
I don&rsquo;t think I could add much to what has already been said about its gameplay and narrative, and there&rsquo;s a good selection of reviews linked from the game&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.metacritic.com/game/switch/carto">Metacritic page</a>.</p>
<p>What I haven&rsquo;t seen discussed as much is that the titular protagonist Carto appears to be a nonspeaking person, or one who only occasionally speaks.
Though reviews like <a href="https://worthplaying.com/article/2021/3/5/reviews/124568-switch-review-carto/">this one</a> or <a href="https://cogconnected.com/review/carto-review/">this one</a> alluded to her silence, they generally put it down to her being quiet or shy.
Carto may be quiet, but shy? Nah.
There&rsquo;s no reason to discount neurodivergence as an explanation and here&rsquo;s my case for it.</p>
<p><strong>SPOILER WARNING:</strong> The rest of this post contains spoilers about the world and story of the game <em>Carto.</em></p>
<h2 id="a-smile-is-worth-a-thousand-words">A smile is worth a thousand words :-)</h2>
<p>From the first I found it slightly odd that Carto&rsquo;s &ldquo;dialogue&rdquo; was represented by emojis, most commonly the smile emoji :-) accompanied by her sprite representation smiling.
Every other character&rsquo;s lines were represented by actual words, after all.
She also did not seem to be deaf, since she understood when other characters addressed her in spoken language.</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ljwrites.blog/img/carto/carto-smile.png"
         alt="Carto, a young girl in white with chin-length dark hair, smiles at a man in glasses. There is a smile emoji :-) representing a smiling face turned sideways in her speech bubble."/> 
</figure>

<p>I was excited at the thought that Carto might be hearing but nonspeaking, since my son is mostly nonspeaking and I&rsquo;m always thrilled at good autistic representation in media.
Still, I thought the emojis could be an abstraction of Carto&rsquo;s lines rather than a literal depiction so I didn&rsquo;t get my hopes up too much.
There was so much else to enjoy about the game, after all.</p>
<p>Undoubted confirmation came toward the end of the game, like a gift.
When Carto finally meets up with her grandmother, her best friend Shianan jokes about not hearing much about the grandmother because Carto is so quiet.</p>
<p>It looks like Shianan could have heard a lot about Grandma if she&rsquo;d had time to learn sign language, though, because Grandma&rsquo;s last letter prior to the meeting has a sketch of her and Carto signing to each other.</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ljwrites.blog/img/carto/carto-sign.jpg"
         alt="Part of a letter reading &#39;I can&#39;t wait to hold you in my arms. We have so much to explore together! Love, Granny,&#39; with a sketch of a larger hand and a smaller one making a sign with thumb and pinkie extended and the other fingers curled."/> 
</figure>

<p>Carto also speaks a little toward the end, mostly names&ndash;&ldquo;Grandma!&rdquo; &ldquo;Carto and Shianan!&rdquo; and so on, showing that her earlier emoji-talk was not an abstraction but actual representations of facial expressions without spoken words.</p>
<p>So there you have it, Carto is a hearing and nonspeaking or minimally speaking character who speaks primarily in sign language.
She seems to have little trouble with verbal comprehension or writing, the latter seen in a letter she sends Shianan in the epilogue.</p>
<p>It was such a rare case of a nonspeaking character, the main character at that, shown in a way that&rsquo;s not left open for interpretation or headcanons but made explicitly clear as canon.
It&rsquo;s hard to express the depth of my appreciation for this, except maybe by writing a giant review and shoutout post on that one subject I guess.</p>
<h2 id="no-big-deal-because-it-isn-t">No big deal, because it isn&rsquo;t</h2>
<p>Something else I found refreshing is that Carto&rsquo;s being nonspeaking is no big deal at all to the other characters.
Shianan mentions it once, as discussed above, in a gently teasing/apologetic way after she and Carto have become good friends.
Otherwise, the characters Carto comes across don&rsquo;t bring it up, interacting without making a fuss when Carto communicates nonverbally, such as by signing or showing &ldquo;sand&rdquo; to them when she wants directions to the desert.</p>
<p>One moment of respectful but casual accommodation that comes to mind is when Carto was at the volcano hotel<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> rebooting their water heating system.
The machinery is accessible by climbing a rope down a pit, and one of the hotel&rsquo;s proprietors remains at the top while Carto climbs down.
When Carto reaches the boiler room at the bottom, the proprietor calls out to her to pull on the rope when she wants to climb back up.</p>
<p>This left an impression because the two characters are never out of shouting distance from each other, and the proprietor guides Carto through the ultimately disastrous reboot sequence by vocal instruction.
The proprietor, in other words, noticed Carto doesn&rsquo;t speak and made no comment about it, but opted to give her the instruction to pull on the rope rather than shout, accommodating the lack of vocal communication.</p>
<p>In a better world this is how all accommodation would happen, respectfully and with minimal comment.
In an even better world hotel proprietors would also not send guests into dangerous locations to do their repair work.
But we can&rsquo;t have everything now, can we?</p>
<p>Maybe one reason the characters find Carto&rsquo;s neurodivergence entirely unremarkable is that the world of the game is itself diverse, with many different ways of life coexisting.
Carto&rsquo;s own clan fly all around the world on blimps.
We start her in-game adventures on an island where no one comes back home after leaving as a teenager.
Later we move on to a forest where people grow huge beards, have animal companions, and one chosen person guards a giant growing tree for decades, away from human settlements.</p>
<p>Against this backdrop a girl who doesn&rsquo;t speak is positively ordinary, and whether the reasons are neurological, cultural, or otherwise it doesn&rsquo;t seem to be considered anyone else&rsquo;s business.
Is she physically or neurologically unable to speak?
Does she not speak the local language?
Did she take a vow of silence?
Who knows, and what does it matter?</p>
<p>Cultural diversity leading to neurodivergence acceptance makes sense to me because neurotype normativity is just one of the many pressures for conformity that form the basis of bigotry in our world.
This kind of coexistence between vastly different peoples is a fascinating aspect of Carto&rsquo;s world.</p>
<h2 id="i-guess-there-should-be-a-conclusion">I guess there should be a conclusion</h2>
<p>Carto is a great little game that puzzle game lovers are likely to enjoy, one with a straightforward and entertaining story.
It may also enhance your enjoyment that the hero of the game is a nonspeaking and, to my mind, autistic girl who enjoys full respect from the people around her, who is at no point seen as an aberration or tragedy.</p>
<p>Needless to say, I highly recommend the game.
It&rsquo;s fun and a little different, like Carto herself.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Is anyone going to talk about how the volcano stage contains homage to <em>Legend of Kyrandia 2: The Hand of Fate,</em> much like the icebergs stage does for Tetris?&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resolving Arch Linux 404 and Dependency Errors</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/arch-linux-404-dependency/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/arch-linux-404-dependency/</guid>
      <description>Update the package database and manually resolve dependencies.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hey Arch Linux user!</p>
<p>Do you keep getting 404 errors when you try to install packages?
Did you rewrite your <code>/etc/pacman.d/mirrorlist</code> file for what feels like dozens of times?
Did you edit your <code>/etc/pacman.conf</code> file according to this Stack Exchange and forum post or that, hoping to get things to work?</p>
<p>If so, these tips just might help.
That&rsquo;s where I was, to the point of almost ragequitting Arch altogether, but trying these tips helped.</p>
<h2 id="update-the-package-database">Update the package database</h2>
<p>If you have your <code>mirrorlist</code> file arranged so the ones geographically closer to you are on top, it may be that you need to update your database.
You might want to try updating your package database with:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>$ sudo pacman -Sy
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Or you could do a full system upgrade with <code>-Syu</code>, your choice.
This landed me in dependency hell, though, see below, so I opted for just a database update this time around and it worked for me.</p>
<p>The reason 404 errors are common in Arch, according to a forum post I saw, is that old packages are deleted on the servers.
Therefore, if your package database is outdated <code>pacman</code> will ask for old deleted versions of packages, resulting in 404 errors.</p>
<p>Live and learn, right?</p>
<h2 id="the-next-level-dependency-hell">The next level: Dependency hell</h2>
<p>After updating the database Arch finally seemed ready to start installing packages again, but this time I fell into the dread&hellip; dependency hell.
It consisted of messages like this:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>:: poppler<span style="color:#f92672">(</span>21.07.0-1<span style="color:#f92672">)</span> 설치로 의존성 <span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;poppler=21.06.1&#39;</span><span style="color:#f92672">(</span>poppler-glib가 요구<span style="color:#f92672">)</span>가 깨집니다
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Which, translated into English, means that the package I was trying to install (kdenlive) required I upgrade <code>poppler</code> to version 21.07.0-1, which would break the dependency of <code>poppler-glib</code> on version 21.06.1.
Evidenly this would ultimately lead to a dependency breakage of Gnu Image Manipulation Program via <code>gegl</code>&rsquo;s dependency on that specific version of <code>poppler-glib</code>.</p>
<p>Running the install command with <code>--ignore poppler</code> didn&rsquo;t help, since pacman refused to install without the poppler upgrade.
Nor did trying to install with <code>sudo pacman -Sdd kdenlive</code> help, since this resulted in kdenlive installing without any dependencies and the package simply did not work.</p>
<p>So what I did was upgrade the offending dependency by itself, which was feasible in my case because there was just one, specifying a <code>-d</code> switch so the dependency version check was ignored:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>$ sudo pacman -Sd poppler
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>When I tried the kdenlive installation again it worked, and luckily the Image Manipulation Program wasn&rsquo;t broken by the poppler upgrade.
It very well could have been, though, since upgrades to dependencies do cause breakages.
That&rsquo;s why dependency version checks exist in the first place.</p>
<p>By ignoring dependency version checks, therefore, you do assume the risk of dependency breakages causing malfunctions, which is a long-running issue in the open source world.
Arch Linux, in particular, only allows one version of each package, raising the risk of dependency breakages&ndash;not a good combination with its fast-moving updates.</p>
<p>It should also be noted that running the kdenlive install with one <code>-d</code> switch instead of two might have had a similar result as installing the dependency package with <code>-d</code>, maybe in conjunction with <code>--ignore poppler</code>.
According to <code>man pacman</code> one <code>-d</code> switch just ignores dependency version checks while repeating it twice like I did ignores all dependencies, which in this case meant the app wouldn&rsquo;t work.</p>
<h2 id="keep-arching-on-dot-dot-dot-or-not">Keep Arching on&hellip; or not</h2>
<p>I don&rsquo;t claim these tips will solve every problem with the Arch package manager, but they could be helpful if your mirrorlist seems more or less in order yet all mirrors are failing with 404 errors.
And if dependency conflicts are tying up your package installations and system updates after the 404 errors are resolved, the second part of the advice would come into play.
If you don&rsquo;t want the risk of broken dependencies, or if ignoring dependencies result in apps breaking, you should file a bug report with the relevant projects.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s also a valid choice to decide that maybe Arch Linux isn&rsquo;t for you if you find these issues to be too much trouble.
Arch is a purposefully fast-moving distribution and by design requires a level of expertise or at least bloody-mindedness.
There are user-friendlier Arch-based distributions like Manjaro that stay a little behind the development curve and are said to be more stable as a result.
The price is in staler packages than mainline Arch, but it&rsquo;s my understanding packages are still newer than in something like Debian.
Besides, truly cutting-edge users don&rsquo;t find even Arch packages new enough and turn to the Arch User Repository for development versions or compile directly from project Git repos.</p>
<p>In the end you have to decide how important newer packages and upgrades are to you, and how much hassle you&rsquo;re willing to put up with.
If you want to keep going with Arch Linux, hopefully this post is helpful to you.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laughing Alone (獨笑)</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/laughing-alone/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/laughing-alone/</guid>
      <description>This is but how the world goes all the time / Alone I laugh, and none do understand!</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>獨笑</strong></p>
<p><strong>Laughing Alone</strong></p>
<p>有粟無人食</p>
<p>The stores are full without a child to feed;</p>
<p>多男必患飢</p>
<p>Hunger does rule the home with many sons.</p>
<p>達官必憃愚</p>
<p>The man of office high is but a fool,</p>
<p>才者無所施</p>
<p>While talent true will languish quite unknown.</p>
<p>家室少完福</p>
<p>Rare is the home that knows of total bliss;</p>
<p>至道常陵遲</p>
<p>Virtue up high will to the grave be gone.</p>
<p>翁嗇子每蕩</p>
<p>What parents thrifted children&rsquo;s hands do waste,</p>
<p>婦慧郎必癡</p>
<p>The woman wise is tripped by feckless man.</p>
<p>月滿頻値雲</p>
<p>On full moon nights the clouds get in the way;</p>
<p>花開風誤之</p>
<p>Flowers in bloom are struck by straying winds.</p>
<p>物物盡如此</p>
<p>This is but how the world goes all the time,</p>
<p>獨笑無人知</p>
<p>Alone I laugh, and none do understand!</p>
<p>&mdash; 茶山 丁若鏞</p>
<p>Dasan Jeong Yak-yong (1762-1836), Korean bureaucrat, scholar, author, poet, philosopher, scientist, and engineer.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is &#34;Narcissistic Abuse&#34; a useful term?</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/questioning-narcissistic-abuse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/questioning-narcissistic-abuse/</guid>
      <description>&amp;lsquo;Narcissistic abuse&amp;rsquo; as a term is extremely stigmatizing to people with NPD while its utility to survivors seems limited.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Narcissists have a bad reputation, to put it mildly.
More and more &ldquo;narcissist&rdquo; seems to be used interchangeably with &ldquo;abuser,&rdquo; with terms like &ldquo;narcissistic abuse&rdquo; and &ldquo;narcissistic parenting&rdquo; in common use.
Armchair diagnoses and labelling are common on threads about abusive behavior.</p>
<p>This is, needless to say, tremendously stigmatizing to people with Narcissistic Personality Disorder (NPD), and doesn&rsquo;t make it any easier for people to seek help with a disorder that is already said to be resistant to treatment.
As others have pointed out, no other mental disorder is  intrinsically linked in people&rsquo;s minds to being an abuser as NPD is, except perhaps borderline personality disorder (BPD) and the so-called antisocial personality disorders.
Even these other massively armchair-diagnosed and stigmatized disorders, however, are not automatically associated with abuse the way NPD is:
&ldquo;Borderline abuse&rdquo; and &ldquo;psychopathic/sociopathic abuse&rdquo; have not entered the popular vernacular the way &ldquo;narcissistic abuse&rdquo; has.</p>
<p>What I don&rsquo;t want to do, obviously, is dismiss the specific concerns and issues arising from being abused by people with narcissistic traits.
An abuser&rsquo;s narcissistic traits, like any other trait of abusers, can cause distinct issues in victims and survivors.
These are absolutely issues that should be discussed and researched, and the last thing I want to do is silence survivors or take away the language they need to understand and heal.
This is all the more because I was myself abused by someone with strong narcissistic tendencies, such as preoccupation with success and perfection and expectation of special treatment, and I&rsquo;m still unpacking the impact this left on me.</p>
<p>My problem with &ldquo;narcissistic abuse&rdquo; as a term is that it is extremely stigmatizing against people with NPD while its utility to survivors seems limited.
The term is flawed by inaccurate and overbroad thinking about narcissism and demonization of narcissistic traits.
It also places the focus on the abuser&rsquo;s characteristics and speculative or real diagnosis, and not on the effects on the survivor.
I know I have issues from the inordinate expectations placed on me by someone who saw me as an extension of the self to fulfill some fantasy of glory, and who treated any negative reactions on my part as a personal affront.
Are these issues distinct to being abused by someone with narcissistic traits?
Are they distinct enough to be separated from abuse in general?
Or is the distinction meaningless because ALL abuse is actually narcissistic in nature?</p>
<p>This lack of clarity about the definitional boundaries and implications of &ldquo;narcissistic abuse&rdquo; makes it not so much a diagnostic criterion or resource for survivors as a snarled insult, an expression of rage toward a poorly-defined group rather than a means to confront and heal.
Don&rsquo;t get me wrong, the rage of victims is absolutely necessary and can be a powerful force.
However, this is rage at a group of people that may or may not include the actual abusers but certainly does include people who are not toxic or abusive, and whose mental illness is moralized and conflated with toxicity EXACTLY as we know we shouldn&rsquo;t for just about any other mental illness.</p>
<p>The way &ldquo;narcissistic&rdquo; has been turned into a synonym for &ldquo;abusive&rdquo; also means that it&rsquo;s difficult to conceive of non-abusive narcissistic people, far less narcissistic people as victims.
Even though people with narcissistic traits, up to full-blown NPD, have clear vulnerabilities to abuse due to their sense of emptiness and hunger for validation, when narcissism and abuse come up it&rsquo;s exclusively about narcissists as the perpetrators.</p>
<p>To the extent we accept that narcissistic traits may make a person likelier to be abusive, the lack of resources on preventing and managing such risks as a narcissistic person is striking.
It&rsquo;s as though narcissistic people as a class, not just the ones who are toxic/abusive, have been written off as unworthy of protection and unable or unwilling to make choices to be better.
This is what dehumanization looks like.</p>
<p>Is this what the classification of &ldquo;narcissistic abuse,&rdquo; and the discourse surrounding narcissism in general, are meant to achieve?
To provide no meaningful guidance to victims whose abusers have narcissistic tendencies beyond what could be achieved by simply calling it abuse, while demonizing a whole class of mentally ill people as inherently toxic and evil?
Then what&rsquo;s the use of it?
Where&rsquo;s the reason to continue using it?</p>
<p>Again, and I want to make this clear, I believe there are potential uses in delving into the characteristics of abusers and the circumstances of abuse.
Spiritual abuse gives rise to distinct issues, for instance, as do financial, physical, sexual, verbal, and emotional abuse.
Parental abuse, sibling abuse, workplace abuse, and peer abuse can all be very different from each other.
An abuser with narcissistic tendencies might similarly cause distinct issues that survivors must navigate.</p>
<p>A lot more clarity is required, however, for the categorization to be useful to survivors without being stigmatizing to people with NPD.
I suspect it&rsquo;ll have to be broken down much more than simply &ldquo;narcissistic,&rdquo; too, such as the reality-warping effect of being made to participate in overinflated fantasies, or living with the onus of perfection to fulfill the abuser&rsquo;s preoccupations.
I equally suspect that many of the things people call narcissistic abuse are just plain entitlement that can arise with all kinds of pathologies and not just NPD, or the lack of any pathology at all.</p>
<p>There is great emotional power in having an Other to rail against, and clarity in having one answer, like narcissism, for everything.
When the chosen target is wrong, however, and the answer is inaccurate, we end up doing harm to others and ourselves.
The way things stand now, &ldquo;narcissistic abuse&rdquo; is one of those inaccurate and harmful categories.
It&rsquo;s time to retire it and do better.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No True Dragon (非眞龍)</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/no-true-dragon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/no-true-dragon/</guid>
      <description>The dragon that can be penned in is no true dragon.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="verse">
<p>龍可豢 非眞龍 虎可搏 非眞虎<br />
故 爵祿可餌榮進之輩 必不可籠淡然無欲之人<br />
鼎鑊可及寵利之流 必不可加飄然引之士<br /></p>
</div>
<p>&mdash; 菜根譚 四. 閒適篇 一</p>
<div class="verse">
<p>The dragon that may be penned in is no true dragon.<br />
The tiger that may be bound is no true tiger.<br />
Therefore, though positions and riches may make underlings out of the ambitious,<br />
such bait can never cage a person of simple tastes free of greed.<br />
Punishment and tortures may reach those who wish for fame and fortune,<br />
but can never affect those who are free as the wind.<br /></p>
</div>
<p>&mdash; Words from Lean Times<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> Part 4: A Composed Life, 1.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>A self-help book from the Ming dynasty of China combining elements of Confucianism, Buddhism, and Daoism&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wind Blows Through the Bamboo Sparse (風來疎竹)</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/wind-bamboo-sparse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/wind-bamboo-sparse/</guid>
      <description>Though wind blows through the bamboo sparse / When it has passed the wood does not the sound retain.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="verse">
<p>風來疎竹 風過而竹不留聲,<br />
鴈度寒潭 鴈去而潭不留影,<br />
故君孑事來而心始現 事去而心隨空.<br /></p>
</div>
<p>&mdash; 菜根譚</p>
<div class="verse">
<p>Though wind blows through the bamboo sparse,<br />
When it has passed the wood does not the sound retain.<br />
Wild goose flies o&rsquo;er the cold clear lake;<br />
The flying shape does not on water long remain.<br />
Thusly, the thought arises in the man of virtue when th&rsquo;occasion calls;<br />
When it has passed the mind again must turn serene.<br /></p>
</div>
<p>&mdash; Words from Lean Times<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>A self-help book from the Ming dynasty of China combining elements of Confucianism, Buddhism, and Daoism&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I Got into Emacs</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/how-i-got-into-emacs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/how-i-got-into-emacs/</guid>
      <description>The true gift of Emacs may be the ability to make it your own in every sense.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From time to time I&rsquo;m asked, perhaps especially as a non-dev who uses Emacs every day, how I got into what is considered development software and one seen as esoteric and antiquated at that.
I thought I&rsquo;d write about my experience with Emacs and the advice I would personally give to people who are thinking of getting into it.</p>
<h2 id="destination-emacs">Destination: Emacs</h2>
<p>It probably helped lead me to Emacs that I&rsquo;ve been a hobby coder for decades and like to fiddle with computers.
I&rsquo;m known as the tech person in my family, and have written small apps in Python 2 including an IRC dicebot in the 00&rsquo;s.
Yes, I&rsquo;m That old.
I&rsquo;ve used PHP and MySQL to run hosted blogs; I&rsquo;ve tried Ubuntu and now use an Arch Linux installation daily.
Coding and computers don&rsquo;t scare me, and what I lack in expertise and training I make up for in sheer determination and willingness to pour countless hours into solving a problem (thanks, ADHD hyperfocus!!).
So in a way a developer&rsquo;s tool like Emacs was a natural fit for me.</p>
<p>Even so, I don&rsquo;t think I would have bothered with something as complex as Emacs if it weren&rsquo;t for my growing discontentment with the software I used in my writing.
LibreOffice was and is my favorite word processor but still, it&rsquo;s a word processor.
They have their uses and are necessary for my work, but the mix of formatting and content was constraining for first drafts, and the completely linear treatment of the text did not lend itself to flexible thinking about the text and content.
Ultimately, in my workflow, word processors are for presenting text, not creating it.</p>
<p>Scrivener was great while it lasted.
At the time it was a completely new paradigm of writing software for me, with the ability to make text modular and to rearrange it, and snapshots as a rudimentary form of version control.
Still, it too had its problems.
The lack of certain functions like mobile editing, good collaboration support, and portable files became increasingly glaring.
The last straw came when I was locked out of software I had paid for&ndash;twice, on Windows and later Macbook!&ndash;due to the company&rsquo;s server problems.
Shortly afterward I moved to Linux for the reasons discussed in <a href="https://linuxrig.com/2021/03/31/the-linux-setup-l-j-lee-translator-researcher-writer/">my Linux Setup submission</a>, and using Scrivener became a moot point anyway.
Years of experience with Scrivener did give me a better idea of what I wanted in a piece of writing software, however:
Separation of content and presentation, version control, and the ability to move pieces of text around and edit them individually.
I also wanted them in a form that couldn&rsquo;t be arbitrarily locked down, corrupted, or otherwise made inaccessible.</p>
<p>Obviously, I learned over time that the things I wanted were doable by editing in plain text formats.
I looked around for plaintext editing options that would also allow for making text modular.
LaTeX was in serious running for a while and I even read a book about it before deciding it wasn&rsquo;t right for me and my non-technical use-case.
AsciiDoc was great and I worked on a fair number of projects with it writing on Vim, which was when I completely fell in love with Vim&rsquo;s editing capabilities.
The modular treatment of text was incomplete at best under this format and software combination, however.</p>
<p>I thought about writing an Atom plugin or even writing a text editor myself to get the functions I wanted&ndash;yeah, that would have gone well lol&ndash;before, as so many do, I found out about Emacs and Org Mode.
(Update 2022-10-22: And, of course, GitHub has since <a href="https://github.blog/2022-06-08-sunsetting-atom/">pulled the plug on Atom</a> while Emacs is still going as it has for decades before Atom ever existed.)
Through my research I learned Org had everything I was looking for, could be exported to a bunch of other formats, <em>and</em> that it emulated Vim commands through Evil Mode.
Sold, sold, and sold.
I decided to make the jump.
I installed Emacs and very slowly started trying things on it and learning the ropes.</p>
<h2 id="building-up-my-emacs-configuration">Building up my Emacs configuration</h2>
<p>It took me a while to &ldquo;warm up&rdquo; to real configuration work on Emacs.
I used it intermittently  for months with the default splash screen enabled (cringe!), learning basic commands.
I did the built-in tutorial, read or watched some guides like this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oJTwQvgfgMM&amp;t=84s">amazing talk by Org Mode creator Carsten Dominik</a>, and tried to get used to the interface when I had spare time.</p>
<p>At first I didn&rsquo;t even install Evil Mode despite not liking the default Emacs movement keys at all.
For one thing I hadn&rsquo;t figured out the package system yet, and even though it was always the plan to install Evil Mode and its availability was one reason I made the jump from Vim to Emacs, I wanted to give the native Emacs commands a fair shake and at least learn the basics.</p>
<p>I slowly got into things like Org Mode, using the most basic functions which were more than enough at first when I was still new to it.
As Carsten Dominik put it, that&rsquo;s a great thing about Org, that you can start as simply as you like and work your way up to as much or as little complexity as you need.</p>
<p>It was only after months of having at least a shaky grasp of basic Emacs functions that I started doing things like configuring visuals and adding packages, spurred on in part by the Emacs from Scratch videos on the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCAiiOTio8Yu69c3XnR7nQBQ">System Crafters</a> channel that was just taking off at the time.
I didn&rsquo; use even a fraction of the advice given on that channel, though.
Instead I mostly used the videos as inspiration and a jumping-off point for more research on how to do specific things when I saw the host doing stuff I wanted for my own setup.</p>
<h2 id="satisfied-mode">Satisfied Mode</h2>
<p>Since then I&rsquo;ve read two books about Emacs, <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/learning-gnu-emacs/0596006489/">Learning Gnu Emacs</a> and <a href="https://www.masteringemacs.org/">Mastering Emacs</a>.
I found them engaging reads that taught me a lot more about how Emacs works.
I have also been intermittently reading the <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/">Org Mode Manual</a>, from which I learned a lot of little tricks to make Org more versatile and convenient for me.</p>
<p>Between this and a lot of things I found out through YouTube, Reddit, and online friends, my init.el has grown to a little over 300 lines.
That&rsquo;s tiny in comparison to Emacs veterans, of course, but is in keeping with my motto, as they say, to move slow and fix things.
I&rsquo;m not technically ambitious or highly skilled; I just want a tool that works more or less how I want it to and doesn&rsquo;t require my data to be sent to a company, one that would not stop being supported because it&rsquo;s no longer profitable.
GNU Emacs, configured little by little entirely at my own pace and actively developed for decades by a worldwide team of maintainers and contributors, exactly fits that bill.</p>
<p>The good news is, that means you can use Emacs too as someone who isn&rsquo;t necessarily technologically proficient and just wants a stable working environment, if you don&rsquo;t mind a slow pace and some work including a little coding.</p>
<h2 id="general-advice">General advice</h2>
<p>My best advice based on personal experience? Don&rsquo;t rush it!</p>
<p>Emacs can seem big and intimidating if you want to learn the ins and outs and to customize it to your exact needs, and honestly it <em>is</em> intimidating and time-consuming to do all that.</p>
<p>It becomes more manageable, though, when you start simple and go slowly.
Add configurations and packages as you feel the need and as you become more comfortable with the platform and Emacs Lisp, the language of Emacs.</p>
<p>Going step by step, breaking and then fixing things as you go, will help you understand your configuration and learn with it.
It&rsquo;ll make the dreaded &ldquo;.emacs bankruptcy&rdquo; where your configuration breaks beyond repair less likely, both because your configuration will be easier to debug when it changes in increments and because you understand what went into it.</p>
<p>I guess the above tips my hand on the &ldquo;vanilla or packaged distro&rdquo; issue, too.
By packaged distros I mean distributions like Doom Emacs or Space Emacs that come with a lot of configurations out of the box, with Vim-style keybindings in the case of both Doom and Space Emacs.</p>
<p>To be clear, I&rsquo;m not about to tell anyone not to get an Emacs distro.
They do cool stuff at only a fraction of the time and effort of setting up vanilla Emacs, and I can see why they&rsquo;re popular.
If spending a lot of painstaking effort on configurations isn&rsquo;t your thing and a distro looks right for you, by all means go for it.</p>
<p>That said, I would not install a distro myself because I&rsquo;ve heard stories of the codebase breaking or no longer being supported in some environments.
This is not the kind of risk I&rsquo;m willing to take, to lose an entire working environment I&rsquo;ve come to rely on with no practical way to get it back.
For me vanilla GNU Emacs, configured by my hand, is much more versatile and easier to repair in case something breaks or changes.</p>
<p>Distros are a valid choice depending on your personal balance of stability versus convenience.
I just happen to fall more on the stability side of things, and it doesn&rsquo;t hurt that I actually like to spend time on configurations because I find them fun to do, in reasonable doses.</p>
<p>Above all, I hope you&rsquo;ll have fun with it!
Emacs is a practical and powerful platform, but it can also be a deeply personal project that is molded to you and changes according to your needs, preferences, and growing skill.
Emacs is my main software for writing, my file manager, my task and schedule manager, my email program, my main git interface&hellip; so much of my life is tied into it.
It&rsquo;s an experience like no other I&rsquo;ve had with software and can be a rollercoaster of excitement for the new, the comfort of the familiar, and, I&rsquo;ll be honest, bouts of hair-tearing frustration.
There&rsquo;s also the good, solid satisfaction of crafting a tool you use daily with your own hands, piece by piece.
You can make it uniquely yours if you&rsquo;re willing to put in the work.
That may be the true gift of Emacs, the ability to make it your own in every sense.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>  Troubleshooting &#34;Unmanaged Device&#34; Network Connection Error
  </title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/troubleshoot-network/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/troubleshoot-network/</guid>
      <description>Here&amp;rsquo;s how I solved it when there was an unmanaged device error with NetworkManager and systemd.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The computer wasn&rsquo;t connecting to the internet this morning with the nm-applet on the status bar saying network connections were unusable.
Sigh. To be fair I had done a system upgrade of Arch Linux the day before, so I guess can this kind of thing Happens.
When I ran:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>$ nmcli c
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip;to check wi-fi connections none of was was showing a device, and when I tried to connect to my usual network using</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>$ nmcli con up <span style="color:#f92672">[</span>device-uuid<span style="color:#f92672">]</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>I got an error that the connection couldn&rsquo;t be activated because &ldquo;No suitable device found for this connection (device lo not available because device is strictly unmanaged).&rdquo;</p>
<p>I searched for the error and, as per <a href="https://askubuntu.com/questions/1190504/why-is-nmcli-not-configuring-device">an answer</a> that was downvoted because it didn&rsquo;t work on Ubuntu but worked for me, I added:</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code class="language-nil" data-lang="nil">[ifupdown]
managed=true
</code></pre><p>to <code>/etc/NetworkManager/NetworkManager.conf</code>.</p>
<p>Restarted NetworkManager with</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code class="language-nil" data-lang="nil">$ sudo systemctl restart NetworkManager.service
</code></pre><p>Worked instantly. When I checked connections with <code>$ nmcli c</code> again my usual connection had been assigned my main network device, and the nm-applet updated accordingly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mu4e Error in Process Sentinel: Mu Server Process Ended with Exit 1</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/mu4e-mu-server-process-error/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/mu4e-mu-server-process-error/</guid>
      <description>Shutting down mu server turned out to be effective when mu4e wouldn&amp;rsquo;t start.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Because no upgrade goes unpunished, Mu4e was refusing to start up in Emacs, throwing an &ldquo;error in process sentinel: Mu server process ended with exit 1&rdquo; error.
I couldn&rsquo;t find this exact error message online, but a look through posts about similar error messages revealed that complaints about the Mu server were often caused by the server still running.
I took the advice in <a href="https://github.com/djcb/mu/issues/8">this Mu4e issue thread</a> and ran:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>pkill -2 -u $UID mu
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip;exactly like that, without replacing the <code>$UID</code> with anything.
Mu4e sprang right back up afterward, having grabbed control of the database back from the server process that had been running.</p>
<p>Still waiting wearily for more troubles to happen, but in the meantime at least I can read emails again.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Honking Osprey (關雎)</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/honking-osprey/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/honking-osprey/</guid>
      <description>The honking osprey rests upon / The islands of the River great / The lady of good bearing is / The man of virtue&amp;rsquo;s perfect mate.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This ancient song is the first listed in the Shijing(詩經), the collection of 300 Chinese songs dating back from as far as 1,000 BC. This particular song was highly praised by Confucius as the pinnacle of musical achievement. <strong>Content warning:</strong> Some people think it&rsquo;s about, well, <em>sex!</em></p>
<p class="verse">
關關雎鳩 在河之洲 窈窕淑女 君子好逑<br />
<br />
The honking osprey rests upon<br />
The islands of the River great;<br />
The lady of good bearing is<br />
The man of virtue's perfect mate.<br />
<br />
參差荇菜 左右流之 窈窕淑女 寤寐求之<br />
<br />
Wand'ring among the jagged fringe<br />
Of water lilies wet and slick,<br />
Through waking day and sleepless nights<br />
The lady perfect do I seek.<br />
<br />
求之不得 寤寐思服 悠哉悠哉 輾轉反側<br />
<br />
I seek but do not gain her yet<br />
And think upon her day and night;<br />
How long the night, how deep I long!<br />
I toss and turn until it's light.<br />
<br />
參差荇菜 左右采之 窈窕淑女 琴瑟友之<br />
<br />
Digging among the jagged fringe<br />
Of water lilies slick and wet;<br />
The lady of good bearing gives<br />
In happy union music sweet.<br />
<br />
參差荇菜 左右芼之 窈窕淑女 鐘鼓樂之<br />
<br />
Plucking among the jagged fringe<br />
Of water lilies slick and wet;<br />
The lady of good bearing joins<br />
In joyous union's rhythmic beat.<br />
</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Feminist Pansori</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/feminist-pansori/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/feminist-pansori/</guid>
      <description>Pansori, a musical form born in openly misogynistic 17th-century Korea, recognizes and celebrates the humanity and worth of women in culturally and historically specific ways.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="pansori">Pansori?</h2>
<p>Pansori is a Korean musical form developed from around the 17th century, where one person sings and makes commentary following a set story to the accompaniment of a drummer.</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://ljwrites.blog/img/pansori/Korea-Busan_3404-06_Pansori.jpeg"
         alt="A female-presenting person in traditional Korean hanbok holding a closed fan stands before a painted screen, with a male-presenting person in hanbok sitting off to the right playing a drum."/> 
</figure>

<p>There are five traditional repertoires that have survived to the present day: Chunhyangga (The Song of Chunhyang), Shimcheongga (The Song of Shim Cheong), Sugungga (The Song of the Sea Palace), Jeokbyeokga (The Song of the Red Cliffs), and Heungboga (The Song of Heungbo).
In this post, I&rsquo;ll be discussing some of the story elements of Chunhyangga, Shimcheongga, and Sugungga.</p>
<p><strong>Content warning:</strong> The sections below contain discussions of dark subject matter including violence, death, and poverty.
More detailed warnings are given by section.</p>
<h2 id="chunhyangga-a-love-story-of-self-determination-and-respect">Chunhyangga: A love story of self-determination and respect</h2>
<p><strong>Content warning:</strong> Attempted sexual coercion, imprisonment, torture</p>
<p>Chunhyangga is the love story of teenagers Seong Chunhyang, who is the daughter of a retired gisaeng (courtesan), and Yi Mongryong, the son of a noble family.
Theirs are most certainly not two households both alike in dignity; in patriarchal and class-stratified Joseon Dynasty terms Chunhyang does not even <em>have</em> a house worth the name, for she has no father and the head of her family is a woman once indentured to the state to provide entertainment services.
Although Chunhyang&rsquo;s mother Wolmae retired in success and relative wealth and is no longer bound to be a courtesan, nor is Chunhyang herself formally a courtesan, her low birth still makes her vulnerable to abuse of power as the story will demonstrate.</p>
<p>Chunhyang and Mongryong meet and fall in love when Mongryong&rsquo;s father is appointed the governor of fair Namwon, where we lay our scene, a real town in Korea and a holy site to the art of pansori to this day.
Smitten, the two 16-year-olds declare themselves man and wife but their union cannot possibly be officially recognized due to the gaping chasm between their stations.
In Joseon, a kingdom whose founding order depended on a strict social hierarchy, at best Chunhyang could be Mongryong&rsquo;s concubine if he cared enough to keep her around.</p>
<p>The first calamity strikes our young lovers when Mongryong&rsquo;s father is called away to Hanyang (present-day Seoul) where Chunhyang cannot follow because, again, she was not a legally sanctioned wife.
Mongryong might have been able to take her with him if he were respectably married to a noblewoman and was the head of his own household, but as an officially unmarried boy he was part of his father&rsquo;s household and had to go where his father went.
The two part tearfully, promising to be faithful to each other, and Chunhyang begins her long wait for him, mourning their parting and hoping for him to return to her a successful man so that they can be together.
In the terms of the times this meant passing the state examination and winning high office.</p>
<p>The second and even worse disaster strikes in the form of the man who succeeds Mongryong&rsquo;s father as governor of Namwon: Byeon Hakdo.
A corrupt and lustful man, he hears of Chunhyang&rsquo;s famed beauty and just as famous virtue and commands her to attend to him as a courtesan.
This, even though she is not on the courtesan register and is legally a free woman.
She also considers herself married, to a nobleman at that, and will not pour drinks and smile for another man.</p>
<p>None of that is any protection against Byeon Hakdo&rsquo;s abuse of power, however, and when Chunhyang continues to refuse him he has her imprisoned and beaten into unconsciousness.
He imprisons her, declaring she would be put to death on his upcoming birthday for the crime of refusing him as a mere lowborn woman.</p>
<p>It is at this point, the night before Chunhyang&rsquo;s scheduled execution, that the long-awaited Lee Mongryong returns to Namwon&ndash;but at night, as a ragged itinerant whose once-proud house has fallen.
Wolmae, on seeing him, screams that her daughter Chunhyang is dead, for her one last hope of salvation is gone.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, Mongryong convinces his mother-in-law to let him see Chunhyang in prison, and the lovers have a touching reunion scene where Chunhyang, injured, imprisoned, and waiting to die, declares he is her love no matter what the circumstance and defends him to her irate and grieving mother.
All Chunhyang asks is that she be buried as Mongryong&rsquo;s faithful wife on his family&rsquo;s funerary grounds, his castoff clothes covering her in the coffin.</p>
<p>Morning comes, and Chunhyang is dragged before the governor Byeon Hakdo to be executed.
He tries one last time to get her to relent, offering to spare her life if she will do as he commands, and she refuses to the last.
Just as she is about to be killed, the troops of the King&rsquo;s Secret Inspector strike, arresting Byeon and his cronies.
Chunhyang, saved from the executioner&rsquo;s blade, comes face-to-face with the Inspector&ndash;her self-declared husband Lee Mongryong, who had returned in disguise hiding his high office to root out Byeon&rsquo;s abuses of power and to save her.
She is given a special dispensation to marry him, not as his concubine but as his lawful noble wife, and her virtue is praised throughout the land.</p>
<p>Within the limitations of the time and society it arose from, then,  Chunhyangga tells a deeply subversive, and of course fantastical and impossible, story of a lowborn woman daring to assert her own will, her own love and self-determination, in the face of power and have it legitimized by the broader society.
These are revolutionary ideas, though the story they appear in fits them into terms friendly to the existing order.</p>
<p>Though heavily mediated and limited by the patriarchal social system of the time, the themes of women&rsquo;s sexual and romantic autonomy free of the bounds of class are unmistakable.
Yes, obviously, it is not feminism as we recognize it for a woman&rsquo;s sexual and romantic decisions to be validated only if she is a free woman recognized as a nobleman&rsquo;s wife and guards her sexual loyalty with her literal life.
But if we call privilege by its true name, that is the granting of full humanity, we get a glimpse at the idea behind Chunhyang&rsquo;s story&ndash;a woman&rsquo;s yearning for respect as a person, which in the times she lived in and for her gender was only possible in partial form for a virtuous noblewoman.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s also worth noting that while the governor Byeon Hakdo&rsquo;s downfall for his corruption and cruelty is a political and subversive plotline, it is focused and mediated through his coercion and violence against the heroine.
The governor&rsquo;s persecution of Chunhyang is the main dramatic reason we want him to fall, and we want Mongryong to succeed because he is the man Chunhyang loves and the key to saving her life.</p>
<p>Misogynist violence, therefore, is not a side political issue in the story as it is often treated in real life.
Violence against women is THE political issue the story gets the audience to care about.
The governor is obviously corrupt and exploitative in numerous other ways, but it is his treatment of a lovestruck, brave, steadfast girl that brings his evil into full focus and gets us to root for this corrupt official&rsquo;s downfall.
This ties into the broader political subversiveness of pansori, which is outside the scope of this post but deserves mention as far as it touches on the theme of women&rsquo;s humanity and worth.</p>
<p>I will say that there is a parallel in the political subversiveness of pansori to the theme of women&rsquo;s autonomy in that the political subversiveness also dovetails into the existing order by use of fantasy.
In this case it&rsquo;s the fantasy that the political order under the King is a force for good that ends injustice and corruption, saving victims like Chunhyang.
This is not historical fact, of course, much as a courtesan&rsquo;s daughter becoming a noble wife was impossible in real life.
But again, this was a story told within the limitations of its times, often using fantastical elements to fit the events of the story into the worldview of the time.</p>
<h2 id="shimcheongga-a-father-as-his-daughter-s-all-loving-all-giving-caregiver">Shimcheongga: A father as his daughter&rsquo;s all-loving, all-giving caregiver</h2>
<p><strong>Content warning:</strong> Bereavement, human sacrifice, poverty, societal misogyny, breasts and breastfeeding</p>
<p>Shimcheongga tells the story of Shim Cheong and her daughterly love for her father Shim Hak-gyu.
The most famous part of the story is that Cheong sells herself as a human sacrifice so her father can afford a sizable donation to a Buddhist temple, a good deed that is promised to give her blind father his sight.</p>
<p>The love and devotion is hardly one way, however.
The actual story of Cheong and her father begins with, well, her birth of course, but the joy is swiftly and devastatingly eclipsed by her mother&rsquo;s death only a week later.
Cheong&rsquo;s mother Lady Gwak, a skilled seamstress, was the breadwinner of the family where Hak-gyu could not work due to his disability.
The death of the wife meant economic disaster for the family, especially since the couple had plowed their fortune into tithes and offerings trying to conceive a child at past forty.
With that fond dream realized, however, the tragedy of the new mother&rsquo;s death meant the father and infant daughter were staring down the barrel of imminent destitution and starvation.</p>
<p>Fortunately the community come through for this vulnerable family, and interestingly it&rsquo;s all women who are mentioned as helping them.
Centuries before the availability of baby formula and without the money to hire a wet nurse, baby Cheong would have starved to death without breastmilk.
When Hak-gyu goes out to the village well begging milk for his infant daughter, those of the village women who are lactating feed her themselves, saying they&rsquo;d rather let their own children go hungry than this poor thing.
Women with no milk give money, while women without money give rice.
It is also the community who feed this father and daughter throughout her childhood and teenage years as they beg food which is freely given to them.</p>
<p>Shimcheongga, then, begins with the story of a widowed single father, disabled and destitute, doing everything he can to raise his daughter&ndash;a daughter who was, in the terms of the time, a useless liability who would not be able to carry on his name or support him in his old age.</p>
<p>This point is actually foregrounded very early in the story, at Cheong&rsquo;s birth when her mother is still healthy.
Having had Cheong when the couple were both in their forties, Lady Gwak asks Hak-gyu if he isn&rsquo;t aggrieved that the only child they&rsquo;ll have is a girl.
The overjoyed father answers, not at all!
After all, Cheong can marry a good man and have sons who will support their maternal grandparents.
While constrained by the imagination of a heavily sexist time, the story nevertheless foregrounds the contributions women make to the welfare of their aged parents.</p>
<p>Besides, you can tell the conventional idea of girls being supposedly a burden is belied from the start of the story with Lady Gwak being the breadwinner of the household who supported her husband and, later, paid for the age&rsquo;s equivalent of fertility treatments.
Shim Cheong herself, at the age of ten, takes over the food-begging duties from her father at her own insistence and does better than him at it.</p>
<p>Shimcheongga, in other words, subverts gender roles with a father as his daughter&rsquo;s primary caregiver, and by also showing women as economic actors with agency.
Even more than that, it argues that women have inherent worth and are deserving of care and devotion through this story of a motherless girl who would have died without her father&rsquo;s and her community&rsquo;s loving care and generosity.</p>
<h2 id="sugungga-rabbit-revolutionary-dot">Sugungga: Rabbit, revolutionary.</h2>
<p><strong>Content warning:</strong> Attempted sacrifice and mutilation, body gendering, genitals</p>
<p>Sugungga, the most satirical of the five classic repertoires, has a female protagonist (or villain, depending) in the sense of a female animal.
In the story the Sea King falls ill and his trusted retainer, Terrapin, sets out to land to capture a rabbit whose liver the Sea King must eat in order to heal.
After a mishap with calling a Tiger instead of a Rabbit, the Terrapin finally meets and tricks Rabbit to the Sea Palace, luring it with promises of high office and honors.
At the Sea Palace the true purpose of the visit is revealed, and Rabbit is told it will be killed so the Sea King can be cured.
But not to worry, it&rsquo;ll be remembered and honored forever for its noble sacrifice!</p>
<p>Rabbit, instead of quaking in fear, claims it can live without a liver.
In fact, it takes out its liver every moon!
This happens to be one of the times Rabbit had its liver out, and it needs to go back to land to fetch the organ.
As proof of this unlikely tale Rabbit points out that it has three holes down there&ndash;one for pissing, one for crapping, and one to take its liver out and put it back.
Rabbit claims it is happy to hand some of its liver over to the Sea King and enjoy the high honors he will bestow in exchange.
The Sea King falls for this and Terrapin takes Rabbit back to land.
Of course Rabbit, once safely back on hand, mocks Terrapin soundly for its gullibility and runs off.</p>
<p>I mean the &ldquo;three holes&rdquo; part is a ruse that a crowd better versed in mammal anatomy would never have fallen for; it&rsquo;s pretty obvious to a landbound audience what the &ldquo;third hole&rdquo; is for and it wasn&rsquo;t for taking out any liver.
In this sense, the Terrapin&rsquo;s misadventures with the Tiger early on comes across like foreshadowing, with most versions saying it escaped by biting the tiger&rsquo;s balls.
This symbolism rings all the truer because in Korean folktale Tiger and Rabbit are often contrasted as symbols of the foolishness of the powerful and the wisdom of the powerless.
It would not be a stretch to read gender into that symbolism, with Tiger as a strong, aggressive man and Rabbit as a physically weak but witty woman.</p>
<p>The way Rabbit is tricked into almost being killed so the Sea King might live is also reminiscent of the way patriarchal systems, and in this case the Neo-Confucian hierarchy of this time, demand sacrifices of women.
Given that &ldquo;give out the liver and gallbladder&rdquo; is a common Korean expression for being a doormat without boundaries or the courage to say no, the entire premise of the story reads as satire for what believing the promises of the powerful does to you:
You&rsquo;re promised honor and prestige, and end up losing your selfhood and your very life.
Rabbit itself was lured by the false promises of patriarchy before it had a rude awakening of the system&rsquo;s true nature, and had to use its wits to survive that situation.</p>
<p>The story in this reading seems to ask, are you really going to give away your liver to a system that benefits only powerful men, and consent to live as a corpse with no will of your own, &ldquo;cherished&rdquo; in loving memory not as a vital, living being but for how you were deceived and exploited?
The story also exposes the true nature of hierarchies like the patriarchy, that they ultimately depend on taking people&rsquo;s will and lives, deceiving them into bargains that serve none but the powerful.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a message so subversive that it could only be told in metaphor:
Where Chunhyangga and Shimcheongga paid at least lip service to Confucian values including the beneficience of the King and familial piety, Sugungga, in the realm of talking animals and supernatural beings, fully took off the gloves and pilloried the sacred social values of the times.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s also an interesting contrast to be drawn between Shim Cheong&rsquo;s willingly becoming a human sacrifice for her father and Rabbit&rsquo;s refusal to sacrifice for the Sea King.
As discussed at length above, Cheong was giving her life for a father who had lovingly raised her in difficult circumstances, while Rabbit had no intention of dying for a king that it had no relationship with and who had no claim to its loyalty.
Though both sacrifices might be laudable in the logic of the worlds they take place in, in the case of Sugungga it would have been a hollow virtue without any grounding in reciprocal and loving relationships.
That difference gives us room to think about how virtues in a hierarchical social system can be connected to emotional values with resonance, ones that we might be able to expand on and adapt without keeping the whole oppressive structure.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>No one is suggesting that these stories about a woman willing to be executed to be loyal to an absent husband, another woman who dove to her death for her father, and talking animals in an underwater palace are the pinnacle of Western-style modern feminism.
What they do show is that the recognition of female autonomy and worth existed in Korean society far before full contact with the U.S. and Europe, and these ideas were not new to Koreans nor given to us wholesale by the West.
The specific expressions may differ, but the feminist yearnings, the desire of women to be recognized as fully human and live on our own terms, has always been there as seen in this small glimpse of Korean art.
It&rsquo;s a heritage worthy of rediscovery and interpretation as we look to exploring a myriad of different feminisms, each in our cultural, historical, and social contexts.</p>
<hr>
<p>This is an edited and expanded version of a thread originally <a href="https://rage.love/@ljwrites/105965761722179223">posted
to Mastodon</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>  No, Andrew Lee Is Not the &#34;Crown Prince of Korea&#34; (there is someone who comes close, though)
  </title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/crown-prince-korea/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/crown-prince-korea/</guid>
      <description>The Korean-American businessman Andrew Lee is not the Crown Prince of Korea. The last Crown Prince of Korea has a living heir, though.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Recently I was amused to read that Andrew Lee, the claimed &ldquo;Crown Prince of Korea,&rdquo; <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2021/05/freenode-irc-has-been-taken-over-by-the-crown-prince-of-korea/">took over the Freenode IRC network</a>.
I mean, not the part where he took over Freenode, of course, which is a shame and I hope users will find a better home if he can&rsquo;t be removed.</p>
<p>The part that amused me was that he claimed to be the Crown Prince of Korea, because a) that title doesn&rsquo;t exist anymore because neither Korea is a monarchy anymore&ndash;or at least not the same monarchy, in the case of the North&ndash;and b) to the extent it exists, it belongs to someone else entirely and Andrew Lee has no claim to it.</p>
<p>Why is that, and who is the &ldquo;real&rdquo; Crown Prince of Korea?
Dive down that rabbit hole with me if you like royal family trivia and/or history.</p>
<h2 id="andrew-lee-the-case-for-and-against">Andrew Lee: The case for and against</h2>
<p>First of all, let&rsquo;s look at Andrew Lee&rsquo;s claim to this title.
The claim is that Yi Seok, a grandson of Gojong who was the last king of Joseon and the first Emperor of the Daehan Empire, <a href="https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/andrew-lee-named-new-korean-crown-prince-300731986.html">passed on</a> the title to Lee in October of 2018.
(&ldquo;Lee&rdquo; and &ldquo;Yi&rdquo; are romanizations of the same Korean surname 이(李). I will use &ldquo;Yi&rdquo; for Korean names because it is the more modern and phonetically correct one.
I will also put the surname first for Korean names.)</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s true that Yi Seok is one of the grandsons of Emperor Gojong and a member of the royal family.
He is not, however, in the direct line of the last Crown Prince of Korea, and therefore cannot pass the title on.
It&rsquo;s also been pointed out that Andrew Lee has never made clear what his family ties to Yi Seok or the Korean royal family are, and if he is not a member of the royal family he is not eligible for any royal title in the first place.</p>
<h2 id="the-real-crown-prince--sort-of">The real Crown Prince (sort of)</h2>
<p>So is there an actual Crown Prince of Korea?
Well, technically, no.
The last guy to hold the title died in 1970 and he lost the title itself in 1910 when Japan took over Korea, and it was never restored because the monarchy was abolished.
The title of Crown Prince, in other words, has not existed in 110 years and the last person to hold it has been dead for over 50.</p>
<p>But also, sort-of kind-of, yes?
While the former royal family, the Yi family from Jeonju, no longer holds political power in Korea (individuals might, of course, but due to being elected in their personal capacity and not by family affiliation), the eldest man in the direct line of the former Crown Prince is acknowledged as the head of the family and holds rites for the royal ancestors.
His title is not Crown Prince, however, far less King, but the Rite-Giver (봉사자, 奉祀子) for the Daehan Royal Family.
As the former royal family they&rsquo;ve decided to recognize the royal line and pay respects to the old kings, a millennia-old tradition in cases where a royal family that lost power survives.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a strictly private title, of course, and has nothing to do with official government designation or power.
The Jeonju Yi family as a private association could call a dancing monkey their Rite-Giver and would be perfectly within their legal rights to do so.
They could also call the monkey (or anyone they chose) the Crown Prince and it would be as legal as it is officially meaningless, much like Andrew Lee&rsquo;s title.</p>
<p>The head of the former royal family and their Rite-Giver is not a monkey.</p>
<p>Nor is it Yi Seok or Andrew Lee.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s this guy:</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ljwrites.blog/img/koreanroyals/Yiwon_08JongmyoDaeje.jpg"
         alt="A male-presenting person in late middle age wearing a dark square hat with a row of colorful ornaments hanging from the front and back brim and an dark blue-grey robe with embroidery and a red panel in front, with a white robe underneath and red boots. He holds a long white piece of wood at waist level, pointing it upward."/> <figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Yi Won</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This is Yi Won, great-grandson of Gojong and grandson of Yi Eun, the aforementioned last Crown Prince of Korea.
Or, if you go by legally recognized terms, the grandson of Yi Gang, Yi Eun&rsquo;s brother.
I told you this was a rabbit hole.</p>
<h2 id="dot-dot-dot-why">&hellip;Why?</h2>
<p>But wait, didn&rsquo;t I say Yi Seok is a son of Yi Gang, making him Yi Won&rsquo;s uncle?
So why is Yi Won ahead of him in the family&rsquo;s pecking order?
Also what&rsquo;s this about Yi Won having two different grandfathers?</p>
<p>This all goes back to the three sons of Gojong, who was the 26th king of Joseon and first Emperor of the Daehan Empire.
Gojong&rsquo;s eldest surviving son Cheok became Sunjong, the second and soon last Emperor when Japan took over the country in 1910.
Sunjong had no son, so his Crown Prince was his younger half-brother Yi Eun, the last person to hold this title.</p>
<p>These two princes&rsquo; half-brother, Yi Gang, had a whopping 21 children.
The 10th son is Yi Seok while the 9th son, Yi Gab, had two sons and a daughter, the eldest son being Yi Won.</p>
<p>Here comes the family tree, a vastly simplified one of course that omits everyone who is not directly mentioned in this particular story (siblings arranged left to right in birth order):</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ljwrites.blog/img/koreanroyals/korean-royals-diagram.jpg"
         alt="A family tree diagram showing Gojong (Emperor) with three children below, Sunjong (Emperor), Yi Gang, and Yi Eun (Crown Prince) from left to right. Below Yi Gang are Yi Gab and Yi Seok. Below Yi Gab is Yi Won. Below Yi Eun (Crown Prince) is Yi Gu."/> <figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>A pared-down Korean royal family tree</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>So the first reason Yi Won has more seniority than Yi Seok and gets to be the head of the royal family is that while Yi Seok is older, Yi Won is the son of the older brother and that makes him more senior by direct line.</p>
<p>The more important reason, though, is that he was &ldquo;adopted&rdquo; under traditional family law that is no longer valid in Korea to Yi Eun&rsquo;s, that is the former Crown Prince&rsquo;s, line.
Yi Eun&rsquo;s son Yi Gu did not have sons, which broke the direct line of the Crown Prince.
In order to carry on that line, Yi Won became Yi Gu&rsquo;s adopted son.</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ljwrites.blog/img/koreanroyals/korean-royals-diagram-adoption.jpg"
         alt="The same diagram as above, except Yi Won is moved from below Yi Gab to below Yi Gu into Yi Eun (Crown Prince)&#39;s line with a yellow horizontal arrow reading &#39;adoption.&#39;"/> <figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Yoink!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The problem under modern Korean family law is that the &ldquo;adoption&rdquo; happened after Yi Gu&rsquo;s death, which makes it legally invalid.
Posthumous adoption of a male relative to carry on a broken family line, however, was fairly common in Korea prior to the 20th century.
Even if it&rsquo;s no longer legally valid, the Jeonju Yi family as a private association can decide its own rules of succession, and if they decree that Yi Won is Yi Eun&rsquo;s grandson by posthumous adoption, they&rsquo;re free to do that.
This would not be valid for the purpose of inheritance and other matters under Korean law, but for deciding who the family decides is its own head? Why not.</p>
<p>Just be glad it wasn&rsquo;t a monkey.
Or Andrew Lee.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
