<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Life on Semi-author-ized writer</title>
    <link>http://ljwrites.blog/categories/life/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Life on Semi-author-ized writer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>CC BY-NC</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0900</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://ljwrites.blog/categories/life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Starting—and staying—small with housecleaning</title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/small-cleaning/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/small-cleaning/</guid>
      <description>On doing better and stressing less about the house with small, unambitious habits</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m not really good about keeping a tip-top house, and chances are I never will be.
Still, lately I&rsquo;ve been doing a little better and am feeling less stressed by giving myself permission to do things in small increments without feeling the need to turn the house upside down or do everything at once.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been aware for a while that I should do things in small increments, but it really came into focus for me with housekeeping advice videos I&rsquo;ve been listening to.
They all emphasized that cleaning is a matter of habit, not the occasional Herculean effort and helped me realize I&rsquo;d been psyching myself out of consistent cleaning by thinking I needed to take out a full day to get EVERYTHING done in one go.</p>
<p>Unfortunately that was how I was brought up, with my mom telling me I should do the whole house when I cleaned because otherwise the dirt would spread from the uncleaned rooms to the clean one.
So I ended up not cleaning on days I couldn&rsquo;t do the whole house, which was most days&hellip; all days&hellip; yeah.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s some truth in what she said and I know she meant to help and not sabotage me, but it turned out to be unhelpful once I started keeping a home.
I&rsquo;m not a stay-at-home mom the way she was, I work for income in a home that&rsquo;s still in the process of decluttering.
Daily full house-cleaning is just not in the cards at this point.
The dirt-spreading effect is also greatly reduced if rooms are cleaned on rotation because there&rsquo;s less dirt overall to spread around.
It&rsquo;s a heck of a lot better than not getting started in the first place, don&rsquo;t let the perfect be the enemy of the good enough, etc.</p>
<p>Once I accepted my starting point and circumstances instead of holding myself to standards for a completely different situation, I could start cleaning and tidying in bits and pieces rather than try to do everything all at once or organize a Grand Day of Reckoning after which everything would be perfect.
Not like I&rsquo;m opposed to big cleaning days, they can be satisfying and helpful, but a) they are intimidating to arrange and get started on, and b) I know myself well enough to realize that without a consistent habit things are going to fall apart around my ears again.
Ask me how I know.
<em>Cries in years of exhausted ADHD working parent</em></p>
<p>In recent days I&rsquo;ve been setting myself limited tasks every day, ideally with just one focus, such as &ldquo;get the gross grease and food gunk off the kitchen floor with Magic Blocks and elbow oil. Yeah, just the floor, do not do the counters, do not clean the oven,&rdquo; or &ldquo;sweep the home office floor&mdash;yeah I know it&rsquo;s a huge cluttered mess, we can get to that, just clean the reachable parts, please.&rdquo;</p>
<p>And you know what?
Things are better.
Not perfect, I can still identify problems everywhere I look, but floors are cleaner and don&rsquo;t feel disgusting to walk on.
It gives me more energy and confidence to start working on bigger-ticket items, like space management in the home office, the big&hellip; basically&hellip; pile of garbage on the verandah, and the related entanglements of family-given items we don&rsquo;t have a use for, the organizational issues of tossing vs. rehoming, guilt about potentially creating so much waste and so on.</p>
<p>And that&rsquo;s okay.
We&rsquo;ll figure it out as we go.
Not in one fell swoop, not on a Day of Salvation that will be the end of our problems, but bit by bit as time goes on and while we&rsquo;re kind to ourselves moving the business of Life along.</p>
<p>This morning my husband and I cleaned the living room sitting mat and the floor underneath which was ick but doable, and we felt a lot better afterward.
That&rsquo;s our cleaning for today.
Tomorrow I&rsquo;ll probably wipe down and clean the big bedroom floor.
That&rsquo;ll be it for tomorrow.
Eventually we&rsquo;ll figure out things that take more organization and have more moving pieces, and we&rsquo;ll get there.
We will gradually, inexorably, habitually unfuck our habitat and feel more in control and relaxed about the house.</p>
<p>We&rsquo;ll never live in a magazine-ready home but it&rsquo;ll be cozy and ours, which is what counts.
I know it works, because it&rsquo;s already working and we&rsquo;ll keep at it.
It&rsquo;ll be okay.
Never perfect, but okay.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>  Is &#34;Narcissistic Abuse&#34; a Useful Term?
  </title>
      <link>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/questioning-narcissistic-abuse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ljwrites.blog/posts/questioning-narcissistic-abuse/</guid>
      <description>&amp;lsquo;Narcissistic abuse&amp;rsquo; as a term is extremely stigmatizing to people with NPD while its utility to survivors seems limited.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Narcissists have a bad reputation, to put it mildly.
More and more &ldquo;narcissist&rdquo; seems to be used interchangeably with &ldquo;abuser,&rdquo; with terms like &ldquo;narcissistic abuse&rdquo; and &ldquo;narcissistic parenting&rdquo; in common use.
Armchair diagnoses and labelling are common on threads about abusive behavior.</p>
<p>This is, needless to say, tremendously stigmatizing to people with Narcissistic Personality Disorder (NPD), and doesn&rsquo;t make it any easier for people to seek help with a disorder that is already said to be resistant to treatment.
As others have pointed out, no other mental disorder is  intrinsically linked in people&rsquo;s minds to being an abuser as NPD is, except perhaps borderline personality disorder (BPD) and the so-called antisocial personality disorders.
Even these other massively armchair-diagnosed and stigmatized disorders, however, are not automatically associated with abuse the way NPD is:
&ldquo;Borderline abuse&rdquo; and &ldquo;psychopathic/sociopathic abuse&rdquo; have not entered the popular vernacular the way &ldquo;narcissistic abuse&rdquo; has.</p>
<p>What I don&rsquo;t want to do, obviously, is dismiss the specific concerns and issues arising from being abused by people with narcissistic traits.
An abuser&rsquo;s narcissistic traits, like any other trait of abusers, can cause distinct issues in victims and survivors.
These are absolutely issues that should be discussed and researched, and the last thing I want to do is silence survivors or take away the language they need to understand and heal.
This is all the more because I was myself abused by someone with strong narcissistic tendencies, such as preoccupation with success and perfection and expectation of special treatment, and I&rsquo;m still unpacking the impact this left on me.</p>
<p>My problem with &ldquo;narcissistic abuse&rdquo; as a term is that it is extremely stigmatizing against people with NPD while its utility to survivors seems limited.
The term is flawed by inaccurate and overbroad thinking about narcissism and demonization of narcissistic traits.
It also places the focus on the abuser&rsquo;s characteristics and speculative or real diagnosis, and not on the effects on the survivor.
I know I have issues from the inordinate expectations placed on me by someone who saw me as an extension of the self to fulfill some fantasy of glory, and who treated any negative reactions on my part as a personal affront.
Are these issues distinct to being abused by someone with narcissistic traits?
Are they distinct enough to be separated from abuse in general?
Or is the distinction meaningless because ALL abuse is actually narcissistic in nature?</p>
<p>This lack of clarity about the definitional boundaries and implications of &ldquo;narcissistic abuse&rdquo; makes it not so much a diagnostic criterion or resource for survivors as a snarled insult, an expression of rage toward a poorly-defined group rather than a means to confront and heal.
Don&rsquo;t get me wrong, the rage of victims is absolutely necessary and can be a powerful force.
However, this is rage at a group of people that may or may not include the actual abusers but certainly does include people who are not toxic or abusive, and whose mental illness is moralized and conflated with toxicity EXACTLY as we know we shouldn&rsquo;t for just about any other mental illness.</p>
<p>The way &ldquo;narcissistic&rdquo; has been turned into a synonym for &ldquo;abusive&rdquo; also means that it&rsquo;s difficult to conceive of non-abusive narcissistic people, far less narcissistic people as victims.
Even though people with narcissistic traits, up to full-blown NPD, have clear vulnerabilities to abuse due to their sense of emptiness and hunger for validation, when narcissism and abuse come up it&rsquo;s exclusively about narcissists as the perpetrators.</p>
<p>To the extent we accept that narcissistic traits may make a person likelier to be abusive, the lack of resources on preventing and managing such risks as a narcissistic person is striking.
It&rsquo;s as though narcissistic people as a class, not just the ones who are toxic/abusive, have been written off as unworthy of protection and unable or unwilling to make choices to be better.
This is what dehumanization looks like.</p>
<p>Is this what the classification of &ldquo;narcissistic abuse,&rdquo; and the discourse surrounding narcissism in general, are meant to achieve?
To provide no meaningful guidance to victims whose abusers have narcissistic tendencies beyond what could be achieved by simply calling it abuse, while demonizing a whole class of mentally ill people as inherently toxic and evil?
Then what&rsquo;s the use of it?
Where&rsquo;s the reason to continue using it?</p>
<p>Again, and I want to make this clear, I believe there are potential uses in delving into the characteristics of abusers and the circumstances of abuse.
Spiritual abuse gives rise to distinct issues, for instance, as do financial, physical, sexual, verbal, and emotional abuse.
Parental abuse, sibling abuse, workplace abuse, and peer abuse can all be very different from each other.
An abuser with narcissistic tendencies might similarly cause distinct issues that survivors must navigate.</p>
<p>A lot more clarity is required, however, for the categorization to be useful to survivors without being stigmatizing to people with NPD.
I suspect it&rsquo;ll have to be broken down much more than simply &ldquo;narcissistic,&rdquo; too, such as the reality-warping effect of being made to participate in overinflated fantasies, or living with the onus of perfection to fulfill the abuser&rsquo;s preoccupations.
I equally suspect that many of the things people call narcissistic abuse are just plain entitlement that can arise with all kinds of pathologies and not just NPD, or the lack of any pathology at all.</p>
<p>There is great emotional power in having an Other to rail against, and clarity in having one answer, like narcissism, for everything.
When the chosen target is wrong, however, and the answer is inaccurate, we end up doing harm to others and ourselves.
The way things stand now, &ldquo;narcissistic abuse&rdquo; is one of those inaccurate and harmful categories.
It&rsquo;s time to retire it and do better.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
